<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<tafsir>
  <code>Asrar</code>
  <mufassir>Kashf Al-Asrar</mufassir>
  <isTafsir>Y</isTafsir>
  <copyright>Content reproduced with permission of www.AlTafsir.com</copyright>
  <chapter index="1">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>In the name of God, the All-Merciful, the Ever-Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Praise belongs to God, the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>The All-Merciful, the Ever-Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>The owner of the Day of Judgment.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Thee alone we worship, and from Thee alone we ask for help.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>Guide us on the straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="2">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Alif, lām, mīm.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>This is the writing in which there is no doubt, a guidance for the godwary.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who have faith in the Unseen and perform the prayer and spend of what We have provided them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>And those who have faith in what has been sent down to thee and what was sent down before thee and who are certain of the next world.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Those are upon a guidance from their Lord.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely it is the same for those who disbelieve whether thou warnest them or thou warnest them not; they will not have faith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>God has sealed their hearts.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>Among the people are those who say, "We have faith in God."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>And when it is said to them, "Have faith as the people have faith," they say, "Shall we have faith as fools have faith?" Surely it is they who are the fools, but they do not know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>He who made for you the earth a carpet and the heaven a building, and who sent down from heaven water by which He brought forth fruits for you as provision. So do not set up peers for God knowingly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>If you are in doubt about what We have sent down on Our servant, then bring a surah the like of it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>And give good news to those who have faith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>How do you disbelieve in God, seeing that you were dead, and He brought you to life. Then He shall make you dead, then He shall bring you to life.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who created for you all that is in the earth, then He went up to heaven and proportioned it as seven heavens, and He is knower of everything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>And when thy Lord said to the angels, "I am setting in the earth a vicegerent," they said, "What, wilt Thou set therein one who will work corruption there, and shed blood, while we glorify Thy praise and call Thee holy?" He said, "Surely I know what you do not know."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>And when We said to the angels, "Prostrate yourselves before Adam!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>Dwell thou and thy spouse in the Garden!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>36</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>36</lastVerse>
      <text>Then Satan made them slip therefrom.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>Then Adam received from his Lord some words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>O children of Israel! Remember My blessings with which I blessed you. And be loyal to My covenant; I will be loyal to your covenant. And of Me have dread.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>42</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>And confuse not truth with falsehood.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>45</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>45</lastVerse>
      <text>And seek help in patience and the prayer, though it indeed is hard, except for the humble.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>And when We gave Moses the book and the discernment.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>When Moses said to his people, "O my people, you have wronged your souls by taking up the calf, so kill your own souls! That is better for you with your Creator."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>57</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>57</lastVerse>
      <text>And We shaded you with clouds. This is an allusion to the Lord's gentleness and generosity. His loving kindness toward the servants is such that the Lord of the Worlds says, "O hapless child of Adam! Why do you not love Me? For I am worthy of love. Why do you not trade with Me? For I am munificent and bounteous. Why do you not engage in transactions with Me? For I am a bestower who is ample in bestowal. My mercy is not tight, nor do I hold back blessings from anyone.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>67</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>67</lastVerse>
      <text>And When Moses said to his people, "God commands you to sacrifice a cow."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>Then your hearts became hardened after that, so they were like stones or even harder. And there are stones from which rivers come gushing, and among them are those that split and water comes forth from them, and among them are those that fall down in fear of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>77</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>77</lastVerse>
      <text>Do they not know that God knows what they keep secret and what they announce?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>78</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>78</lastVerse>
      <text>And among them are the unlettered.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>82</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>82</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who have faith and do wholesome deeds-those are the companions of the Garden, and they shall be there forever.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>97</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>97</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "Whoever is an enemy of Gabriel-he it is who sent it down upon thy heart."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>106</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>106</lastVerse>
      <text>Whatever verse We abrogate or cause to be forgotten-We bring better than it or its like.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>112</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>112</lastVerse>
      <text>No, whosoever submits his face to God, doing the beautiful, shall have his wage with his Lord, and no fear shall be upon them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>114</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>114</lastVerse>
      <text>Who does greater wrong than he who bars God's places of prostration?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>116</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>116</lastVerse>
      <text>They say, "God has taken a son." Glory be to Him! Rather, to Him belongs what is in the heavens and the earth; all are devoted to Him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>121</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>121</lastVerse>
      <text>Those to whom We have given the Book and who recite it with the rightful due of recitation.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>124</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>124</lastVerse>
      <text>And when his Lord tried Abraham with some words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>129</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>129</lastVerse>
      <text>"Our Lord, and raise up amidst them a messenger from among them, who will recite Thy signs to them, teach them the Book and the Wisdom, and purify them. Surely Thou art the Exalted, the Wise."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>130</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>130</lastVerse>
      <text>And who shrinks from the creed of Abraham but one foolish in himself? We chose him in this world, and in the next world he shall be among the wholesome.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>131</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>131</lastVerse>
      <text>When his Lord said to him, "Submit," he said, "I submit to the Lord of the Worlds."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>137</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>137</lastVerse>
      <text>If they have faith in the like of that in which you have faith, they will have found guidance; but if they turn away, they will have split from you. God will suffice you against them; He is the hearing, the knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>138</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>138</lastVerse>
      <text>God's color-and who is more beautiful in color than God?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>143</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>143</lastVerse>
      <text>Thus We appointed you a midmost community.... Surely God is clement, ever-merciful toward the people.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>144</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>144</lastVerse>
      <text>We have seen thy face turning about in heaven. Now We shall turn thee toward a kiblah that thou shalt approve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>148</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>148</lastVerse>
      <text>Everyone has a direction to which he turns.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>152</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>152</lastVerse>
      <text>So remember Me; I will remember you. And be grateful for Me and not ungrateful toward Me.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>154</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>154</lastVerse>
      <text>Say not of those who are slain in the path of God, "They are dead." No, they are alive, but you are unaware.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>155</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>155</lastVerse>
      <text>And We will indeed try you with something of fear and hunger, and decrease of wealth, souls, and fruits; and give good news to the patient.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>163</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>163</lastVerse>
      <text>And your God is one God. There is no god but He, the All-Merciful, the Ever-Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>164</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>164</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely in the creation of the heavens and the earth, the alternation of the night and the day, the ships that run on the sea with what benefits people, the water that God sends down from heaven giving life to the earth after its death, the scattering of every beast therein, the shifting of the winds, the clouds subjected between heaven and earth-there are signs for a people who have intellect.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>165</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>165</lastVerse>
      <text>Among the people are some who take peers apart from God, loving them as if loving God. And those who have faith are more intense in love for God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>166</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>166</lastVerse>
      <text>When those who were followed declare themselves quit of those who followed them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>177</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>177</lastVerse>
      <text>Piety is not that you turn your faces to the east and the west. Rather, piety is he who has faith in God, the Last Day, the angels, the Book, and the prophets; who gives wealth despite loving it to kinsfolk, orphans, the indigent, the son of the road, beggars, and slaves; and who performs the prayer and give the alms tax; those who are loyal to the covenant when they make a covenant; those who are patient in misfortune, hardship, and moments of peril. It is they who have been truthful, and it is they who are the godwary.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>178</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>178</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Written for you is retaliation in the case of the slain.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>180</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>180</lastVerse>
      <text>It is written for you, when death is present for one of you and he is leaving behind some good, to make a will for parents and kinsfolk honorably, as something rightfully due from the godwary.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>183</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>183</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Written for you is fasting.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>185</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>185</lastVerse>
      <text>The month of Ramadan is that wherein the Qur'an was sent down as guidance.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>186</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>186</lastVerse>
      <text>And when My servants ask about Me, surely I am near. I respond to the supplication of the supplicator when he supplicates Me. So let them respond to Me and have faith in Me. Perhaps they will be led aright.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>189</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>189</lastVerse>
      <text>They ask thee about the new moons.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>190</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>190</lastVerse>
      <text>And fight in the path of God those who fight against you, but do not transgress. God loves not the transgressors.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>195</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>195</lastVerse>
      <text>Expend in the path of God.... And do what is beautiful. Surely God loves the beautiful-doers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>196</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>196</lastVerse>
      <text>And complete the hajj and the umrah for God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>201</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>201</lastVerse>
      <text>Among them is he who says, "Our Lord, give us in this world something beautiful, and in the next world something beautiful."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>203</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>203</lastVerse>
      <text>And remember God in certain numbered days, but if someone hastens on after two days, no sin shall be upon him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>213</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>213</lastVerse>
      <text>The people were one community. Then God sent the prophets as bringers of good news and warning.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>214</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>214</lastVerse>
      <text>Or do you reckon that you will enter the Garden?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>215</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>215</lastVerse>
      <text>They ask thee what they should expend. Say: "Whatever good you expend should be for parents and kinsmen, orphans, the indigent, and the son of the road." And whatever good you do, God knows it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>218</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>218</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who have faith, those who emigrate, and those who struggle in God's path-it is they who hope for God's mercy, and God is the Forgiving, the Ever-Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>219</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>219</lastVerse>
      <text>They ask thee about wine and gambling.... And they ask thee what they should expend.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>223</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>223</lastVerse>
      <text>Your women are your tillage, so come to your tillage as you like.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>226</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>226</lastVerse>
      <text>For those who forswear their women, a wait of four months. But if they revert, God is forgiving, ever-merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>229</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>229</lastVerse>
      <text>Divorce is twice, then retention with honor or setting free with beautiful doing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>233</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>233</lastVerse>
      <text>Mothers shall suckle their children two whole years-for those who desire to complete the suckling.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>237</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>237</lastVerse>
      <text>And that you pardon is nearer to godwariness. And forget not bounty among yourselves. Surely God sees what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>238</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>238</lastVerse>
      <text>Guard over the prayers, and the middle prayer, and stand before God devoutly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>245</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>245</lastVerse>
      <text>Who is it that will lend to God a beautiful loan, and He will multiply it for him many times? And God contracts and expands, and to Him you shall be returned.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>248</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>248</lastVerse>
      <text>Their prophet said to them, "The sign of his kingship is that there will come to you the ark within which is tranquility from your Lord."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>255</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>255</lastVerse>
      <text>God, there is no god but He, the Living, the Self-Standing. Slumber takes Him not, nor sleep. To Him belong whatsoever is in the heavens and whatsoever is in the earth. Who will intercede with Him save by His leave? He knows what is before them and what is behind them, and they encompass nothing of His knowledge save as He wills. His Footstool embraces the heavens and the earth, and He is the High, the Tremendous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>257</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>257</lastVerse>
      <text>God is the friend of those who have faith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>260</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>260</lastVerse>
      <text>When Abraham said to his Lord, "Show me how Thou givest life to the dead." He said, "Dost thou not have faith?" He said, "Yes indeed, but that my heart may be serene."... And know that God is exalted, wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>264</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>264</lastVerse>
      <text>O You who have faith, do not void your charity by counting it a favor and causing discomfort.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>268</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>268</lastVerse>
      <text>Satan promises you poverty and commands you to indecency, and God promises you forgiveness from Him, and bounty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>269</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>269</lastVerse>
      <text>He gives wisdom to whomsoever He wills.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>273</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>273</lastVerse>
      <text>[It is] for the poor, who are constrained in the path of God and are not able to travel in the earth. The ignorant man counts them as rich because of their self-restraint. Thou shalt recognize them by their mark-they do not ask of the people imploringly. And whatever good you expend, surely God knows it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>274</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>274</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who expend their wealth night and day, secretly and openly, shall have their wage with their Lord, and no fear shall be upon them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>277</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>277</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who have faith and do wholesome deeds, who perform the prayer and give the alms tax, shall have their wage with their Lord, and no fear shall be upon them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>284</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>284</lastVerse>
      <text>To God belongs whatsoever is in the heavens and whatsoever is in the earth. Whether you show what is in your souls or you hide it, God will bring you to account for it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>285</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>286</lastVerse>
      <text>The Messenger has faith in what was sent down to him from his Lord, and the faithful. Each one has faith in God, His angels, His books, and His messengers: "We make no distinction among any of His messengers." They say, "We hear and we obey! Thy forgiveness, our Lord! And to Thee is the homecoming." God takes no soul to task beyond its capacity. It shall have what it has earned, and against it shall be what it has acquired. "Our Lord, take us not to task if we forget or make mistakes. Our Lord, put not upon us a burden such as that Thou hast put on those before us. Our Lord, and do not burden us with what we do not have the strength to bear. And pardon us, and forgive us, and have mercy upon us. Thou art our Patron, so help us against the people of the unbelievers."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="3">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who forms you in the wombs as He wills.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who has sent down upon thee the Book, wherein are firm verses, which are the mother of the Book, and others ambiguous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>Our Lord, let not our hearts stray after Thou hast guided us, and give us mercy from Thee.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>As for the unbelievers, their possessions will not take away their need for God, neither their children, and it is they who will be fuel for the Fire.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>Adorned for people is love of appetites, like women, children, heaped-up heaps of gold and silver, horses of mark, cattle, and tillage. That is the enjoyment of the life of this world.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>Shall I tell you of something better than that? For those who are godwary there shall be with their Lord gardens beneath which rivers flow, therein dwelling forever, and spouses made pure, and approval from God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>The patient, the truthful, the devoted, the expenders, those who ask forgiveness at dawn.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>God bears witness that there is no god but He-and the angels, and the possessors of knowledge-upholding justice; there is no god but He, the Exalted, the Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely the religion with God is the submission.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>Let not the faithful take the disbelievers as friends instead of the faithful". God warns you of Himself, and God is clement to the servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>On the day when every soul shall find the good it has done made present, and the ugly it has done. It will wish that there were a far interval between itself and that. God warns you of Himself, and God is clement to the servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: If you love God, follow me; God will love you and forgive you your sins.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>He said, "My Lord, appoint for me a sign." He said, "Your sign is that you shall not speak to the people for three days, except by intimation. And remember thy Lord often and glorify Him at evening and dawn."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>45</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>45</lastVerse>
      <text>When the angels said, "O Mary, surely God gives thee the good news of a word from Him, whose name is the Messiah, Jesus son of Mary, celebrated in this world and the next, and one of those given proximity." In this verse the God of the universe, the enactor of the world's folk, the assigner of daily provisions to the servants, the bestower of bounty and the lovingly kind, the caresser of the friends, caresses Mary and honors her. With this honoring He gives her excellence over the women of the world and separates her from all of them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>48</lastVerse>
      <text>And He will teach him the Book, the wisdom, the Torah, and the Gospel.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>And they deceived, and God deceived, and God is the best of deceivers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>The truth is from thy Lord, so be not among the doubters.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>64</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: " O Folk of the Book! Come to a word common between us and you: that we worship none but God, that we associate nothing with Him, and that some of us not take others of us as lords apart from God. "</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>73</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>73</lastVerse>
      <text>Do not have faith in any but those who follow your religion. Say: "Surely the guidance is God's guidance," lest anyone should be given the like of what you have been given, or dispute with you before your Lord. Say: "Surely the bounty is in God's hand. He gives it to whomsoever He wills." And God is all-embracing, knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>He singles out for His mercy whomsoever He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>79</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>It belongs to no mortal man that God should give him the Book, the judgment, and prophethood, and then he should say to the people, "Be servants of me instead of God!" But, "Be you lordly ones from having taught the Book and from having studied!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>81</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>81</lastVerse>
      <text>And when God took the compact of the prophets, "I have given you of the Book and wisdom. Then a messenger will come to you confirming what is with you. You shall surely have faith in him and you shall surely help him."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>Whosoever wants a religion other than the submission, it will not be accepted from him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, be wary of God as is the rightful due of His wariness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>104</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>104</lastVerse>
      <text>Let there be a community of you inviting to the good.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>105</lastVerse>
      <text>And do not be like those who became dispersed and disagreed.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>119</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>119</lastVerse>
      <text>Ha! There you are: You love them, but they do not love you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>123</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>123</lastVerse>
      <text>God surely helped you at Badr while you were abased.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>134</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>134</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who spend in prosperity and adversity, those who curb rage, and those who pardon people-and God loves the beautiful-doers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>144</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>144</lastVerse>
      <text>Muḥammad is only a messenger. Messengers have passed away before him. What, if he dies or is killed, will you turn back on your heels? If anyone turns back on his heels, he will not harm God in anything, and God will recompense the grateful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>148</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>148</lastVerse>
      <text>God gave them this world's reward and the beauty of the next world's reward, and God loves the beautiful-doers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>152</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>152</lastVerse>
      <text>Among you are those who desire this world, and among you are those who desire the next world.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>159</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>159</lastVerse>
      <text>It was by a mercy of God that thou wert soft with them. Hadst thou been harsh and hard of heart, they would have scattered from around thee. So pardon them, ask forgiveness for them, and consult with them in the affair. And when thou art resolved, trust in God. Surely God loves those who trust.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>169</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>169</lastVerse>
      <text>Count not those who were killed in God's path as dead, rather, alive with their Lord, provided for.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>171</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>172</lastVerse>
      <text>They rejoice in blessings from God and bounty, and that God does not leave to waste the wage of the faithful, those who answered God and the Messenger after the wound had befallen them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>180</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>180</lastVerse>
      <text>Let not those who are niggardly with the bounty that God has given them reckon that it is better for them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>191</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>191</lastVerse>
      <text>Who remember God, standing, sitting, and on their sides, and reflect on the creation of the heavens and the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>194</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>194</lastVerse>
      <text>Our Lord, and give us what Thou hast promised us through Thy messengers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>195</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>195</lastVerse>
      <text>And their Lord responded to them, "I will not waste the deed of any doer among you, male or female. The one of you is as the other. And those who emigrated, were expelled from their homes, were tormented in My path, who fought and were killed, I shall surely acquit them of their ugly deeds and enter them into Gardens under which rivers flow, a reward from God."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="4">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>O people, be wary of your Lord, who created you from one soul, created from it its mate, and scattered forth from the two many men and women. And be wary of God, whom you ask against one another, and of the wombs. Surely God is watcher over you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who eat the property of orphans wrongly will be eating only fire in their bellies and will roast in a blaze.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>For you half of what your wives leave, if they have no children.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>It is for God to turn only toward those who ignorantly do what is ugly and then soon turn. Those-God will turn toward them. And God is knowing, wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>This turning will not belong to those who keep on doing ugly deeds until death is present for one of them, and then he says: "Surely now I have turned."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, it is not lawful for you to inherit women against their will, neither debar them from marriage that you may go off with part of what you have given them, unless they commit a flagrant indecency. Consort with them honorably. For, if you are averse to them, it may be that you are averse to something within which God has placed much good.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>If you desire to exchange a wife in place of another...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Forbidden to you are your mothers and daughters, your sisters".</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>And man was created weak.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>If you avoid the great sins prohibited to you, We will acquit you of your ugly deeds and admit you to a generous admitting place.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>Do not wish for that whereby God has preferred some of you over others. Men shall have a portion of what they have earned, and women shall have a portion of what they have earned. But ask God of His bounty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>The men stand over the women through that with which God has preferred some of them over others and that which they expend of their wealth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>36</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>36</lastVerse>
      <text>Worship God, and associate nothing with Him, and act beautifully toward parents, and toward kinsfolk, orphans, the indigent, and the neighbor who is of kin, and the neighbor who is a stranger, and the companion at your side, and the son of the road, and what your right hands own.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Do not approach the prayer when you are intoxicated until you know what you are saying, or defiled-except for travelers on the road-until you have made the full ablution.... Surely God is pardoning, forgiving.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>48</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God does not forgive that anything be associated with Him, but less than that He forgives for whomsoever He wills.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>49</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>Hast thou not seen those who deem themselves pure? No, God alone deems pure whomsoever He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>And We gave them a tremendous kingdom.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>58</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God commands you to deliver trusts back to their owners.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>64</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>We sent not any messenger but that he should be obeyed by God's leave.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>Then they will not find in themselves any tightness from what thou decreest and will surrender with full submission.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>69</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>69</lastVerse>
      <text>Whosoever obeys God and the Messenger-they will be with those whom God has blessed: the prophets, the sincerely truthful, the witnesses, and the wholesome. What beautiful companions they!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>86</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>86</lastVerse>
      <text>When you are greeted with a greeting, greet with one more beautiful than it, or return it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>94</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>94</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! When you strike forth on the path of God, look clearly, and say not to him who offers you peace, "You are not of the faithful," seeking the chance goods of this world's life.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>100</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>Whosoever emigrates in the path of God will find in the earth many a road and expanse.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>103</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>103</lastVerse>
      <text>When you have completed the prayer, remember God, standing and sitting and on your sides.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>114</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>114</lastVerse>
      <text>No good is there in much of their whispering, except for him who bids to charity, or the honorable, or making things wholesome among the people. Whosoever does this, seeking God's approval, We shall give him a tremendous wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>119</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>119</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely I will misguide them and fill them with wishes.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>125</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>125</lastVerse>
      <text>Who is more beautiful in religion than he who submits his face to God while he is a beautiful-doer and follows the creed of Abraham, an unswerving man? And God chose Abraham as a bosom friend.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>126</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>126</lastVerse>
      <text>To God belongs everything in the heavens and everything in the earth, and God encompasses everything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>131</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>131</lastVerse>
      <text>To God belongs everything in the heavens and everything in the earth, and We have charged those who were given the Book before you, and you, to be wary of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>132</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>132</lastVerse>
      <text>To God belongs everything in the heavens and everything in the earth, and God is sufficient as a trustee.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>136</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>136</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Have faith in God and His Messenger.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>160</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>160</lastVerse>
      <text>And for the wrongdoing of those who are Jews, We forbade them certain good things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>162</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>162</lastVerse>
      <text>But those who are firmly rooted in knowledge</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>163</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>163</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We have revealed to thee as We revealed to Noah, and the prophets after him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>170</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>170</lastVerse>
      <text>O people, the Messenger has come to you with the truth from your Lord, so have faith; that is better for you. But if you disbelieve, to God belongs all that is in the heavens and the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>174</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>174</lastVerse>
      <text>O people, a proof has come to you from your Lord, and We have sent down to you a clear light.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>175</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>175</lastVerse>
      <text>As for those who have faith in God and hold fast to Him, He will make them enter into mercy from Him, and bounty, and He will guide them to Him on a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="5">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Forbidden to you are carrion and blood, the flesh of swine, that which has been offered up to other than God, the strangled, the beaten down, the fallen, the gored, what has been eaten by predators-except what you slaughter-what is sacrificed on stone alters, and that which you allot by divining arrows-that is ungodliness. Today those who disbelieve have despaired of your religion, so fear them not, and fear Me. Today I have perfected for you your religion and I have completed My blessings upon you, and I have approved for you the submission as a religion.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, when you stand for the prayer, wash your faces and your hands up to your elbows.... If you find no water, have recourse to goodly dust.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Be wary of God, and seek the means of approach to Him. And struggle in His path. Perhaps you will prosper.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>48</lastVerse>
      <text>For every one of you We have appointed an avenue and a method.... So vie in good deeds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>51</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>51</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, take not the Jews and Christians as friends. They are friends of each other. Whoso of you takes them as a friend is one of them. Surely God does not guide the wrongdoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, if any of you turn back on your religion, God will bring a people whom He loves, and who love Him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>Your friend is only God, and His Messenger.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>83</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>And when they hear what has been sent down to the Messenger, thou seest their eyes overflow with tears because of the truth they recognize. They say, "Our Lord, we have faith, so write us down among the witnesses."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>89</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>89</lastVerse>
      <text>God will not take you to task for idle talk in your oaths, but He will take you to task for the oaths you have bound. The expiation thereof is the feeding of ten indigent people with what you usually feed your own family, or clothing them, or freeing a slave.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Wine, arrow-shuffling, idols, and divining arrows are a filth and of the deeds of Satan.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>95</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>95</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, do not slay game when you are ritually consecrated.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>98</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>98</lastVerse>
      <text>Know that God is intense in punishment and that God is forgiving, ever-merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>100</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "The vile and the goodly are not equal, even if the manyness of the vile stirs you to admiration."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>101</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>101</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, do not ask about things which would harm you if they were made to appear to you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>105</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith! Against you are your own souls. Those who are misguided cannot hurt you if you are guided.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="6">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Praise belongs to God who created the heavens and the earth and made the darknesses and the light.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who created you from clay.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>And He is God in the heavens and in the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "To whom belongs what is in the heavens and in the earth?" Say: "To God. He has written mercy against Himself."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>And His is whatsoever dwells in the night and the day, and He is the Hearing, the Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "Shall I take as friend other than God, the Originator of the heavens and earth, who feeds and is not fed?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>And if God touches thee with harm, none can remove it but He.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>And He is the Severe over His servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "What thing is greater in bearing witness?" Say: "God."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>No, what they had been concealing beforehand now appears to them, and even if they were sent back, they would return to what had been prohibited to them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "Do you see: Were God's chastisement to come to you or were the Hour to come to you, would you supplicate other than God, if you are truthful?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>No, He it is whom you will supplicate, so He will remove that for which you supplicate Him if He will, and you will forget what you associated with Him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>42</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>Indeed We sent to nations before thee, and We seized them with misery and hardship that perhaps they would plead.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>52</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>52</lastVerse>
      <text>And drive not away those who supplicate their Lord morning and evening, desiring His face.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>And when those who have faith in Our signs come to thee, say, "Peace be upon you. Your Lord has written mercy against Himself, that whosoever of you does an ugly deed in ignorance, and thereafter repents and makes wholesome, He is forgiving, ever-merciful."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>75</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>So also We were showing Abraham the dominion of the heavens and the earth, that he might be one of those with certainty. When the night darkened over him, he saw a star. He said, "This is my Lord." When it set he said, "I love not those that set."... Then when he saw the sun rising, he said, "This is my Lord, this is greater." When it set he said, "O my people, I am quit of what you associate. Surely I have turned my face toward Him who originated the heavens and the earth, unswerving, and I am not of the associaters."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>91</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>91</lastVerse>
      <text>They measured not God with the rightful due of His measure.... Say "God," then leave them to play in their plunging.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>93</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>93</lastVerse>
      <text>Who does greater wrong than he who forges a lie against God?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>95</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>95</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God is the splitter apart of the grain and the date-stone.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>96</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>96</lastVerse>
      <text>Splitter apart of the dawn; and He has made the night as a stillness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>98</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>98</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who has configured you from one soul.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>99</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>99</lastVerse>
      <text>And He it is who sent down out of heaven water, by which We bring forth the growth of everything.... Gaze at their fruits when they fructify and ripen. Surely in these are signs for a people who have faith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>111</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>111</lastVerse>
      <text>Were We to send down the angels to them, were the dead to speak to them, and were We to muster all things in front of them, they would still not have faith, unless God willed.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>112</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>112</lastVerse>
      <text>Thus have We made for every prophet an enemy, satans of jinn and men.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>114</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>114</lastVerse>
      <text>What, shall I want other than God as a judge?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>116</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>116</lastVerse>
      <text>Wert thou to obey most of those in the earth, they would misguide thee from the path of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>120</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>120</lastVerse>
      <text>Leave aside the outward of sin and its inward.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>122</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>122</lastVerse>
      <text>What, is he who was dead, and We gave him life, making for him a light whereby he walks among the people, like one who is in the darknesses, not coming out from them?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>125</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>125</lastVerse>
      <text>Whomsoever God desires to guide, He expands his breast to the submission.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>126</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>126</lastVerse>
      <text>This is the path of thy Lord, straight.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>134</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>134</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely what you are promised will come.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>160</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>160</lastVerse>
      <text>Whoso brings a beautiful deed shall have ten the like of it, and whoso brings an ugly deed shall be recompensed only with its like.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>161</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>161</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "As for me, my Lord has guided me to a straight path."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>162</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>162</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "My prayer and my sacrifice, my life and my death, belong to God."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="7">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>The weighing that day is true.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>We created you, then We formed you, then We said to the angels, "Prostrate yourselves before Adam."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>O Adam, dwell thou and thy spouse in the Garden, and eat from wheresoever you will, but come not near this tree.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>Then Satan whispered to them to show them their shameful parts that were hidden from them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>And when they tasted the tree, their shameful parts were shown to them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>"Our Lord, we have wronged ourselves. It Thou dost not forgive us and have mercy upon us, we will surely be among the losers."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "My Lord has commanded justice. Set your faces in every place of prostration and supplicate Him, purifying the religion for Him. Just as He began you, so you shall return."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>O children of Adam! Put on your adornment at every place of prostration.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "Who has forbidden the adornment of God?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>We shall strip away all the rancor that is in their breasts.... And it will be called out, "This is your Garden; you have been made to inherit it for what you were doing."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>46</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>And upon the Ramparts are men who recognize everyone by their marks.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely your Lord is God, who created the heavens and the earth in six days, then sat upon the Throne.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>Supplicate your Lord in pleading and secret.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>56</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>56</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God's mercy is near the beautiful-doers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>57</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>57</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who looses the winds as good news before the hands of His mercy so that, when they lift up a heavy cloud, We drive it to a dead land and thereby send down water, bringing forth thereby all the fruits.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>58</lastVerse>
      <text>As for the goodly land, its plants come forth by the leave of its Lord. As for that which is vile, they come forth only scantily.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>80</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>80</lastVerse>
      <text>And Lot, when he said to his people, "What, do you bring an indecency with which none in the worlds has preceded you?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>96</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>96</lastVerse>
      <text>Had the folk of the towns had faith and been godwary, We would have opened up for them blessings from heaven and earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>99</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>99</lastVerse>
      <text>Did they feel secure from God's deception?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>We found nothing of covenant in most of them; indeed, We found most of them ungodly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>142</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>142</lastVerse>
      <text>And We promised Moses thirty nights, and We completed them with ten. So the appointed time of his Lord was completed in forty nights. And Moses said to his brother Aaron, "Take my place among my people."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>143</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>143</lastVerse>
      <text>When Moses came to Our appointed time and his Lord spoke to him, he said, "Show me, that I may gaze upon Thee." He said, "Thou shalt not see Me, but look at the mountain. If it stays firm in its place, thou shalt see me." Then, when his Lord disclosed Himself to the mountain, He made it crumble to dust, and Moses fell down thunderstruck. When he recovered he said, "Glory be to Thee! I repent to Thee!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>144</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>144</lastVerse>
      <text>O Moses, surely I have chosen thee over the people through My messages and My speaking. So take what I have given thee, and be one of the thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>145</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>145</lastVerse>
      <text>And in the tablets We wrote for him of everything an admonition, and a detailing of everything. "So take hold of them with strength, and command thy people to take their most beautiful. I shall show you the abode of the ungodly."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>146</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>146</lastVerse>
      <text>I shall turn away from My signs those who are proud in the earth without the Real. Even were they to see all the signs, they would not have faith in them. Were they to see the way of rectitude, they would not take it as a way.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>148</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>148</lastVerse>
      <text>And the people of Moses, after him, took of their ornaments a calf, a body that lowed. Did they not see that it did not speak to them?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>150</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>151</lastVerse>
      <text>He threw down the Tablets.... He said, "My Lord, forgive me and my brother."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>155</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>155</lastVerse>
      <text>And Moses chose his people, seventy men, for Our appointed time, and when the earthquake took them, he said " "It is naught but Thy trial. Thou misguidest thereby whomsoever Thou wilt and Thou guidest whomsoever Thou wilt. Thou art our Friend, so forgive us and have mercy upon us, and Thou art the best of forgivers!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>156</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>156</lastVerse>
      <text>And write for us in this world the beautiful, and in the next world. We have turned to Thee.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>159</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>159</lastVerse>
      <text>Among the people of Moses is a community that guides by the truth and does justice thereby.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>160</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>160</lastVerse>
      <text>And We cut them up into twelve tribes, communities.... And We revealed to Moses when his people asked him for water, "Strike the stone with thy staff," and twelve springs gushed forth from it. All the people knew their drinking places.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>168</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>168</lastVerse>
      <text>And We cut them up into communities in the earth. Among them are the wholesome and among them other than that. And We tried them with the beautiful things and the ugly things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>172</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>172</lastVerse>
      <text>When your Lord took from the children of Adam, from their loins, their offspring and made them bear witness concerning themselves. "Am I not your Lord?" They said, "Yes indeed."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>180</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>180</lastVerse>
      <text>And to God belong the most beautiful names, so supplicate Him by them, and leave those who deviate concerning His names.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>189</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>189</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who created you from one soul and made of it its spouse so that it may rest in her.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>199</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>199</lastVerse>
      <text>Take to pardoning and command the honorable and turn away from the ignorant.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>204</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>204</lastVerse>
      <text>And when the Qur'an is recited, listen to it and give ear. Perhaps you will be shown mercy.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>205</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>205</lastVerse>
      <text>And remember thy Lord in thyself.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="8">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>The faithful are only those whose hearts quake when God is remembered.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who perform the prayer and expend from what We have provided them, it is they who are the faithful in truth. They have degrees with their Lord and forgiveness and a generous provision.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>And when God promised you one of the two parties would be yours, and you wished that the one not armed would be yours.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>When you sought the aid of your Lord, He responded to you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>Thou didst not throw when thou threwest, but God threw; and that He may try the faithful with a beautiful trial.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, respond to God and the Messenger when he invites you to that which will give you life, and know that God comes between a man and his heart, and unto Him you will be mustered.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, if you are wary of God, He will appoint for you a criterion, acquit you of your ugly deeds, and forgive you. And God is the possessor of a tremendous bounty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>And know that, whatever booty you take, a fifth is for God, and for His Messenger and for kinsfolk, orphans, the indigent, and the son of the road, if you have faith in God".</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>50</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>50</lastVerse>
      <text>Wert thou to see when the angels take those who disbelieve, beating their faces and their backs: "Taste the chastisement of the burning!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>72</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>72</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who have faith, emigrate, and struggle with their possessions and their souls in God's path, and those who give refuge and help, they are friends of one another.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>Those-they are the faithful in truth. Theirs is forgiveness and a generous provision.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="9">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>God has already helped you in many homesteads, and on the Day of Hunain, when you admired your own multitude.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>The freewill offerings are for the poor, and the indigent.... and the son of the road....</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>100</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>And the preceders, the first among the emigrants and the helpers and those who followed them in beautiful doing-God approves of them, and they approve of Him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>And others who acknowledged their sins; they mixed a wholesome deed with another that is ugly. Perhaps God will turn toward them. Surely God is forgiving, ever-merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>106</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>106</lastVerse>
      <text>And others who are made to hope for God's command; either He will chastise them or He will turn toward them. And God is knowing, wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>111</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>111</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God has bought from the faithful their souls and their possessions so that they may have the Garden.... So rejoice in your sale you have made to Him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>112</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>112</lastVerse>
      <text>The repenters, the worshipers, the praisers, the journeyers, the bowers, the prostrators, the commanders to the honorable, the prohibiters of the improper, the keepers of God's bounds-give good news to the faithful!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>119</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>119</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, be wary of God and be among the truthful!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>128</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>128</lastVerse>
      <text>Now there has come to you a Messenger from among yourselves, what troubles you difficult for him; eagerly desirous is he for you, clement and ever-merciful toward the faithful.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="10">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Give good news to those with faith that they have a footing of truthfulness with their Lord.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>To Him is your place of return, all together-God's promise in truth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who made the sun a radiance and the moon a light.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who do not hope for Our encounter, are content with the life of this world and at rest with it, and those who are heedless of Our signs, it is they whose refuge will be the Fire for what they were earning.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who have faith and do wholesome deeds, their Lord will guide them in their faith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>And their greeting therein will be "Peace!," and the last of their supplication will be "Praise belongs to God, the Lord of the Worlds."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who makes you journey on land and sea. Even so, when you are in the ship-it takes them along with a goodly breeze, and they rejoice in it; there comes upon them a raging wind, and waves come from every place and they think that they will be encompassed by them; they supplicate God, purifying the religion for Him: "If Thou savest us from this, we shall surely be among the thankful."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>And God invites to the Abode of Peace, and He guides whomsoever He will to a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>To those who do what is beautiful belong the most beautiful and an increase. Neither dust nor abasement shall overcome their faces. It is they who will be the companions of the Garden, dwelling within it forever.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: Is there any of those whom you associate who guides to the Real?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>42</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>Among them are those who listen to thee.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>58</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: " In the bounty of God and His mercy-in that let them rejoice, for it is better than what they gather. "</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God's friends-no fear shall be upon them, neither shall they sorrow.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>64</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>For them is good news in the life of this world and the next world.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>71</lastVerse>
      <text>And recite to them the story of Noah when he said to his people, "If my station and my reminding you of God's signs are too much for you, then in God I trust, so gather together your affair and those whom you associate, and let not your affair be obscure for you. Then decide about me, and do not leave me waiting."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>105</lastVerse>
      <text>Set thy face to the religion.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="11">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Alif, Lām, RāÌ</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>Perhaps thou art putting aside some of what is revealed to thee, and thy breast is straitened by it, that they say, "Why has a treasure not been sent down upon him or an angel come with him?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>Whoso desires the life of this world and its adornment, We shall pay them in full for their deeds therein, and therein they shall not be defrauded.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>And what of him who is upon a clear sign from his Lord?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who have faith, do wholesome deeds, and are subservient to their Lord-it is they who will be the companions of the Garden, dwelling within it forever.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>The likeness of the two groups is that of the blind and deaf and the seeing and hearing. Are they equal in likeness?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>Make the ship through Our eyes and Our revelation.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>And ask forgiveness from your Lord, then repent to Him. Surely my Lord is ever-merciful, loving.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="12">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>We will tell thee the most beautiful of tales.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>When Joseph said to his father, "O my father, surely I saw eleven stars and the sun and the moon. I saw them prostrating to me."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>So when they went with him and agreed to put him at the bottom of the well, We revealed to him, "Surely thou shalt inform them of this affair of theirs when they are unaware."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>They sold him for a paltry price.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>The king said, "I see seven fat cows that seven lean ones are eating."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>52</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>That, so that he may know that I did not betray him secretly.... But I do not acquit my own soul. Surely the soul commands to ugliness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>76</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>76</lastVerse>
      <text>Thus We schemed for Joseph.... We raise in degree whomsoever We will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>81</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>81</lastVerse>
      <text>Return to your father and say, "O our father! Surely thy son has stolen."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>84</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>84</lastVerse>
      <text>"Oh, my grief for Joseph!" And his eyes turned white because of the sorrow that he was suppressing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>93</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>93</lastVerse>
      <text>Go with this shirt of mine and cast it upon the face of my father so that he may come to seeing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>94</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>94</lastVerse>
      <text>Their father said, "Surely I find Joseph's scent."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>99</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>So, when they entered in upon Joseph, he embraced his parents.... And he lifted his parents to the throne, and they fell prostrate before him.... "He acted beautifully toward me when He brought me out of prison and brought you from the desert after Satan had sowed dissension between me and my brothers. Surely my Lord is gentle toward what He will."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="13">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Alif Lām Mīm RāÌ</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>God is He who lifted up the heavens without pillars that you see.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>And He it is who spread out the earth and placed within it unshaking mountains.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>To God prostrate themselves all in the heavens and the earth, willingly or unwillingly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>He sends down from heaven water, and the wadis flow in their measure, and the flood carries a swelling scum. And from that which they kindle in fire, wanting ornament or ware, arises a scum the like of it. Thus does God strike truth and falsehood. As for the scum, it vanishes as jetsam, and what profits people abides in the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who have faith and whose hearts are serene in the remembrance of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>He effaces whatsoever He will, and He affirms.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="14">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>God is He to whom belongs everything in the heavens and everything in the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>And We sent Moses with our signs: "Bring thy people out from the darknesses into the light and remind them of the days of God." "O My Muḥammad! I commanded Moses exactly as I command you. I said to all: 'Light up the lamp of the invitation, call people from the darknesses of doubt to the light of certainty, bring them from the shadow of ignorance to the brightness of knowledge, leave aside self-governance, see the Real's predetermination, do not set down or approve of innovation, and follow the path of the Sunnah and the congregation.'"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>When your Lord proclaimed, "If you give thanks, I will surely increase you."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who have faith and do wholesome deeds were given entry into the Garden.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>Hast thou not seen how God has struck a similitude? A goodly word is like a goodly tree.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>It gives its fruit every season by the leave of its Lord.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>And when Abraham said, "My Lord, make this land secure, and keep me and my sons away from worshiping idols."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="15">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>And therein We placed for you livelihoods.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>Naught is there but its storehouses are with Us.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>And We sent forth the winds as pollinators.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We give life and We make die.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>We indeed know those of you who go forward and We indeed know those of you who fall behind.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We created man of a dried clay of fetid mud.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="16">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>The command of God is coming, so do not seek to hurry it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>He sends down the angels with the spirit from His command upon whomsoever He will of His servants: "Give warning that there is no god but I, so be wary of Me."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>And in them is beauty for you when you bring home to rest and drive forth to pasture.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>It is for God to point out the path; and some [paths] deviate.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who sends down water from heaven.... Surely in that is a sign for a people who reflect... signs for a people who use intellect... a sign for a people who remember.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who subjected the sea so that you may eat from it fresh flesh.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>Is He who creates like him who does not create?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who emigrate in God after they were wronged-We shall surely build for them something beautiful, and the wage of the next world will be greater.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>Ask the folk of remembrance if you do not know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>51</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>51</lastVerse>
      <text>And God says, "Do not take two gods. Surely He is only one God, so be in awe of Me."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>66</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>66</lastVerse>
      <text>And surely in the cattle there is a lesson for you: We give you to drink of that which is in their bellies, between feces and blood, pure milk, delicious for the drinkers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>71</lastVerse>
      <text>And God has given more bounty in provision to some of you than others.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>83</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>They recognize God's blessings, then they deny them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God commands justice and beautiful doing and giving to kinsmen, and He prohibits indecency, the improper, and rebelliousness. And He admonishes you, that perhaps you may remember.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>96</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>96</lastVerse>
      <text>What is with you runs out, but what is with God subsists.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>97</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>97</lastVerse>
      <text>Whoever does a wholesome deed, male or female, while having faith, We shall surely give him to live a goodly life.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>110</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>110</lastVerse>
      <text>Then surely thy Lord-toward those who emigrated after they were tormented, then struggled and were patient-surely thy Lord after that is forgiving, ever-merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>120</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>121</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely Abraham was a community, devoted to God and unswerving, not among the associaters, grateful for His blessings. He chose him and guided him to a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>123</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>123</lastVerse>
      <text>Then We revealed to thee, "Follow the creed of Abraham, an unswerving man."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>125</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>125</lastVerse>
      <text>Invite to the path of thy Lord with wisdom and beautiful admonition.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="17">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Glory be to Him who took His servant by night from the Holy Mosque to the Farthest Mosque.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>And We gave Moses the Book, and We made it a guidance for the Children of Israel.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>And We decreed for the Children of Israel in the Book: "You will surely work corruption in the earth twice and you will become high with great height."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>If you do the beautiful, you will have done the beautiful for your own souls, and if you do the ugly, it will be against them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>Perhaps your Lord will have mercy upon you. And if you return, We will return.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>Man supplicates for evil just as he supplicates for good.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>And every man, We have fastened his omen to his neck. And We shall bring forth for him, on the Day of Resurrection, a book he will meet wide open.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>Read thy book! Thy soul suffices thee today as a reckoner against thee.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>And your Lord has decreed that you worship none but Him, and beautiful doing toward your parents.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>And say to My servants that they should say what is more beautiful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>And We made some of the prophets more excellent than others.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>70</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>70</lastVerse>
      <text>We indeed honored the children of Adam, and We carried them on land and sea, and We provided them with goodly things, and We made them much more excellent than many of those We created.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>84</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>84</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "Each acts according to his own manner"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>They ask thee about the spirit.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>107</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>107</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: " Have faith in it, or do not have faith. " Surely those who were given knowledge before it, when it is recited to them, fall down on their faces in prostration.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>109</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>109</lastVerse>
      <text>They fall down on their faces weeping.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="18">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Praise belongs to God who sent down the Book to His servant and placed no crookedness therein.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>They shall have a beautiful wage, remaining therein endlessly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>They say nothing but a lie.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>Perhaps thou art consuming thyself with grief in their tracks if they do not have faith in this talk.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We have made all that is on the earth an adornment for it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>When the chevaliers took refuge in the cave and said, "Our Lord, give us mercy from Thee and furnish us with right conduct in our affair."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>We recount to you their story in truth. Surely they were chevaliers who had faith in their Lord, and We increased them in guidance.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>And We placed a tie on their hearts when they stood up and said, "Our Lord is the Lord of the heavens and the earth."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>16</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>16</lastVerse>
      <text>Take refuge in the cave. Your Lord will unfold for you of His mercy and furnish you with kindliness in your affair.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>Thou wouldst have seen the sun, when it rose, turning aside from their cave to the right.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>Thou wouldst have thought them awake, but they were sleeping. And We turned them now to the right, now to the left. And their dog was stretching its paws at the doorstep. Hadst thou looked down upon them, surely thou wouldst have turned away from them fleeing, and thou wouldst have been filled with terror from them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>Now send one of you forth with this silver of yours to the city, and let him look to which of them has the purest food.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>Say not of anything, "I will do it tomorrow," but only, "If God wills." And remember thy Lord when thou forgettest. When someone recognizes God, his free choice drops away before His will, and his decrees are enveloped by the witnessing of his Lord's decree.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>When Moses said to his chevalier, "I will continue on until I reach the meeting place of the two seas."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>And We taught him knowledge from Us.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>67</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>67</lastVerse>
      <text>"Surely thou wilt not be able to bear patiently with me."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="19">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Kāf HāÌ YāÌ ʿAyn Ṣād</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>The mention of thy Lord's mercy to His servant Zachariah.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>When he supplicated his Lord secretly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>Warn them of the day of remorse.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>The Lord of the heavens and the earth and what is between the two. So worship Him, and be patient in His worship.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>The day We shall muster the godwary to the All-Merciful in droves.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="20">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>The All-Merciful sat on the Throne.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>Even if thou speakest aloud, yet surely He knows the secret and the most hidden.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>God, there is no god but He. To Him belong the most beautiful names.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>Hast thou received the story of Moses when he saw a fire?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely I am thy Lord. Take off thy shoes!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>What is that in thy right hand, O Moses?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>Clasp thy hand to thy side. It will come forth white without ugliness, as another sign.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>That We may show thee some of Our greatest signs.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>And We tried thee with trials.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>"I chose thee for Myself."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>From it We created you and to it We shall return you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>75</lastVerse>
      <text>Whoever comes to his Lord as an offender will have Gehenna, wherein he will neither die nor live, and whoever comes to Him faithful, having done wholesome deeds-they will have the highest degrees.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>76</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>76</lastVerse>
      <text>Therein dwelling forever; that is the recompense of those who purify themselves.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>82</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>82</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely I am all-forgiving toward the one who repents and has faith and does wholesome deeds, and then is guided.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>83</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>"And what has made thee hurry from thy people, O Moses!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>84</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>84</lastVerse>
      <text>He said, "They are close upon my footsteps, and I hurried to Thee, my Lord, that Thou mayest approve."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>106</lastVerse>
      <text>They ask thee about the mountains. Say, "My Lord will scatter them as ashes."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>115</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>115</lastVerse>
      <text>And We made covenant with Adam before, but he forgot, and We found in him no resoluteness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>121</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>122</lastVerse>
      <text>And Adam disobeyed his Lord, so went astray. Then his Lord chose him, so He turned toward him and guided.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>124</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>124</lastVerse>
      <text>And whosoever turns away from My remembrance, he shall have a life of narrowness, and on the Day of Resurrection We shall muster him blind.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>131</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>131</lastVerse>
      <text>Extend not thine eyes to what We have given pairs of them to enjoy, the flower of this world's life so that We may entrance them thereby; and thy Lord's provision is better and more subsisting.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>132</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>132</lastVerse>
      <text>And command thy family to the prayer, and have patience therein. We ask no provision of thee, and it is We who shall provide thee.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="21">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>To Him belongs whatsoever is in the heavens and the earth. Those who are with Him are not too proud to worship Him, nor do they become weary.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>He will not be questioned about what He does, but they will be questioned.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>Or have they taken gods apart from Him? Say, "Bring your proof."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>Have not those who disbelieve seen that the heavens and the earth were all sewn up, then We unstitched them, and from water We made every living thing?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>And He it is who created night and day, and the sun and the moon, each swimming in a sphere.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>We have not assigned everlastingness to any mortal before thee. If thou diest, will they be everlasting? Every soul shall taste death.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>Man was created of haste. I shall show you My signs, so seek not to hasten Me.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>69</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>69</lastVerse>
      <text>We said, "O fire, be coolness and safety!"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>78</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>78</lastVerse>
      <text>And David and Solomon, when they gave judgment about the tillage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>79</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>So We made Solomon understand this, and to both We gave judgment and knowledge.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>87</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>88</lastVerse>
      <text>And Dhu'l-Nūn, when he went forth wrathful and thought that We would not have power over him. Then he called out in the darknesses, "There is no god but Thou, glory be to Thee! Surely I am one of the wrongdoers." So We responded to him and delivered him from sorrow.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>89</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>89</lastVerse>
      <text>And Zachariah, when he supplicated his Lord, "My Lord, leave me not solitary."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>They were vying in good works and they were supplicating Us in eagerness and dread, and they were reverent toward Us.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>101</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>101</lastVerse>
      <text>As for those to whom the most beautiful has preceded from Us.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>103</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>103</lastVerse>
      <text>The greatest terror shall not make them sorrow, and the angels shall receive them: "This is the day that you were promised."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>107</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>107</lastVerse>
      <text>We sent thee only as a mercy to the worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="22">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>O people, be wary of your Lord-surely the quaking of the Hour is a tremendous thing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>O people, if you are in doubt about the Uprising, surely We created you of dust, then of a sperm drop, then of a blood clot, then of a lump of flesh, fully created and not fully created, that We might make clear to you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>They will be adorned therein with bracelets of gold and pearls, and their clothes therein will be silk.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>And they will be guided unto the goodly in speech.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>When We built for Abraham the place of the House: "Associate nothing with Me, and make My house pure for those who circumambulate, stand, and bow in prostration."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>That is because God makes the night pass into the day and makes the day pass into the night, and God is hearing, seeing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>That is because God is the Real and what they supplicate other than Him is the unreal, and because God is the high, the great.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>63</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>63</lastVerse>
      <text>Hast thou not seen that God sends down water from heaven, and then the earth becomes green?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>73</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>73</lastVerse>
      <text>Feeble are the seeker and the sought!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>They measured not God with the rightful due of His measure. Surely God is strong, exalted.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>77</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>77</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, bow and prostrate and worship your Lord!</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="23">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>We indeed created above you seven paths and We were not heedless of creation.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>And We sent down from heaven water in a measure and settled it in the earth, and surely We are powerful over taking it away.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>And therewith We made grow up for you gardens of palms and grape vines.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>52</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>52</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely this community of yours is one community, and I am your Lord, so be wary of Me.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>56</lastVerse>
      <text>Do they think that We aid them with possessions and children only that We may hurry good things to them?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>57</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely those who tremble in fear of their Lord" it is they who hurry to good deeds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>We burden no soul save to its capacity</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>96</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>96</lastVerse>
      <text>Repel the ugly with what is more beautiful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>115</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>115</lastVerse>
      <text>What, did you reckon that We created you for play and that you would not be returned to Us?</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="24">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>A surah that We have sent down and made obligatory; and We sent down in it clear signs that perhaps you will remember.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>The fornicatress and the fornicator-flog each of them a hundred lashes, and let no clemency toward them seize you in God's religion, if you have faith in God and the Last Day. And let a group of the faithful witness their chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who came with the slander are a band of you. Do not reckon it evil for you; rather, it is good for you. Against every man of them shall be the sin he has earned. Whosoever of them took upon himself most of it will have a great chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>The goodly women are for the goodly men, and the goodly men for the goodly women-these are innocent of what they say. They will have forgiveness and a generous provision.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>Say to the faithful that they cast down their eyes.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>And say to the faithful women that they cast down their eyes, guard their private parts, and not show their adornment, save what is outward thereof.... And repent all together to God, O you who have faith!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>God is the light of the heavens and the earth. The likeness of His light is a niche, inside the niche a lamp, the lamp inside a glass.... Light upon light. God guides to His light whomsoever He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>36</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>36</lastVerse>
      <text>In houses that God has permitted to be raised up and in which His name is mentioned, glorifying Him therein.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>Men whom neither trade nor buying diverts from the remembrance of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>As for those who disbelieve, their deeds are like a mirage.... Or like darknesses in a deep sea covered with waves, above which are waves, above which are clouds. Darknesses, one on top of another. When he stretches forth his hand, he barely sees it. And he to whom God assigns no light has no light.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>Dost thou not see how God drives the clouds, then combines them, then makes them a heap? Then thou seest the rain coming out from their midst.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>44</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>44</lastVerse>
      <text>God turns about the night and the day. Surely in that is a lesson for the possessors of eyes.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>God promises those of you who have faith and do wholesome deeds that He will surely make you vicegerents in the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="25">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>We shall advance on what deeds they have done and make them scattered dust.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>45</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>45</lastVerse>
      <text>Dost thou not see thy Lord, how He stretched out the shadow? Had He willed, He would have made it still. Then We made the sun an indicator of it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>46</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>Then We contracted it to Us with an easy contracting.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>And He it is who has sent the winds, bearing good news before His mercy. And We sent down from heaven pure water.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who mixed the two oceans, this one sweet, delicious; that one salty, bitter.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>63</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>63</lastVerse>
      <text>The servants of the All-Merciful are those who walk in the earth in lowliness.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="26">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>ṬāÌ Sīn Mīm</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Perhaps thou tormentest thyself because they are not of the faithful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>And the blessing that you have laid on me as a favor is that you have enslaved the Children of Israel.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Pharaoh said, "And what is the Lord of the worlds?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>" The Lord of the heavens and the earth and whatsoever is between the two. "</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>And when the two hosts saw each other, the companions of Moses said, "We have been overtaken."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>"No indeed, surely with me is my Lord; He will guide me."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>77</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>78</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely they are an enemy to me, save the Lord of the Worlds, who created me, so He is guiding me.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>79</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>And who gives me to eat and gives me drink.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>106</lastVerse>
      <text>The people of Noah cried lies to the messengers when their brother Noah said to them, "Will you not be godwary?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>109</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>109</lastVerse>
      <text>I ask from you no wage for this; surely my wage falls on God, the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>217</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>217</lastVerse>
      <text>And trust in the Exalted, the Ever-Merciful!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>218</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>219</lastVerse>
      <text>Who sees thee when thou standest and when thou movest about among those who prostrate themselves.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="27">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>And We gave David and Solomon knowledge.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>59</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>59</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "The praise belongs to God, and peace be upon His servants whom He has chosen."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>Who is it that made the earth a settledness, made rivers in its midst, made for it firm mountains, and made a barrier between the two oceans? Is there a god along with God? No, but most of them know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>80</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>80</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely thou wilt not make the dead to hear.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="28">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>ṬāÌ Sīn Mīm</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>When he turned his face toward Midian, he said, "Perhaps my Lord will guide me on the even way."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>When he entered upon the water of Midian.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>56</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>56</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely thou dost not guide whom thou lovest, but God guides whomsoever He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>83</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>That is the abode of the next world-We appoint it for those who do not desire elevation in the earth, nor corruption.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>He who made the Qur'an obligatory upon thee shall restore thee to a place of return.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="29">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Do the people reckon they will be left to say, "We have faith," and not be tried?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Whoso hopes to encounter God, God's term is coming, and He is the Hearing, the Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>Have they not seen how God originates creation, then makes it return?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>He chastises whom He will and has mercy on whom He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>You will not be disablers in earth or in heaven, and you have no friend or helper apart from God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>And those who disbelieve in the signs of God and the encounter with Him-they have lost hope in My mercy.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="30">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>To God belongs the command, before and after. And on that day the faithful will rejoice in God's help.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>And of His signs is that He created you of dust, and then you were mortal man, spreading about.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>So set thy face to the religion, unswerving.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>50</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>50</lastVerse>
      <text>So gaze on the traces of God's mercy, how He brings the earth to life after its death.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="31">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>And We gave Luqmān wisdom.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="32">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Alif Lām Mīm. The sending down of the Book, wherein is no doubt, from the Lord of the Worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>Who made beautiful everything that He created and who began the creation of man from clay.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "The angel of death, who has been entrusted with you, will make you die."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="33">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>There it was that the faithful were tried and shaken with an intense shaking.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>God desires only to put away from you filth, O Folk of the House, and to make you completely pure.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely submitted men and submitted women, faithful men and faithful women, devout men and devout women, truthful men and truthful women, patient men and patient women, humble men and humble women, charitable men and charitable women, fasting men and fasting women, men who guard their private parts and women who guard, men who remember God much and women who remember-God has prepared for them forgiveness and a tremendous wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>Muḥammad is not the father of any of your men, but rather the messenger of God and the seal of the prophets.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, remember God with much remembrance!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>44</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>44</lastVerse>
      <text>Their greeting on the day they encounter Him will be "Peace."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>45</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>O Prophet! Surely We sent thee as a witness, a good-news bringer, and a warner, inviting to God by His leave, and a light-giving lamp.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>47</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>47</lastVerse>
      <text>And give good news to the faithful that they will have a great bounty from God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>If you show something or hide it, surely God is knower of everything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>70</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>70</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, be wary of God and speak proper words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>72</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>72</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We offered the Trust to the heavens and the earth and the mountains, but they refused to carry it and feared it, and man carried it. Surely he was a great wrongdoer, deeply ignorant.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="34">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>We gave David bounty from Us.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>And the wind was Solomon's, its morning course a month and its evening course a month.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>When We decreed death for him....</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>46</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "I admonish you with but one thing: that you stand up for God."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>49</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "The truth has come, and falsehood does not originate, nor make return."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="35">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Praise belongs to God, the Creator of the heavens and the earth, who appointed the angels as messengers having wings, two, three, and four. He adds to creation as He wills.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Whatever mercy God opens up to the people, none shall hold it back.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>Not equal are the two oceans, this one sweet, satisfying, delicious to drink, that one salty, bitter.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>O people, you are the poor toward God, and God is the Unneedy, the Praiseworthy.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>Then We gave the inheritance of the Book to the ones We chose from among Our servants. Among them are wrongdoers to themselves, among them are moderate, and among them are preceders in good deeds by God's leave. That is the great bounty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>Gardens of Eden that they will enter.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>And they shall say, "Praise belongs to God, who has put away sorrow from us."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="36">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>YāÌ Sīn. By the Wise Qur'an, surely thou art one of the envoys, upon a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>The sending down of the Exalted, the Ever-Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>That thou mayest warn a people whose fathers were not warned, so they are heedless.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>Have they not seen how many generations We destroyed before them?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>36</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>36</lastVerse>
      <text>Glory be to Him who created the pairs, all of them, from what the earth grows and from themselves and from what they do not know!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>A sign for them is the night; We strip from it the day.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>And the moon, We have determined way stations for it, till it returns like the old palm branch.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely the companions of the Garden today are in an occupation, rejoicing.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="37">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>By the row-keepers in rows!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>The Lord of the heavens and the earth and what is between the two, and the Lord of the easts.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>And halt them. Surely they will be questioned.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>They will have a known provision; fruits-and they will be honored.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>For the like of this, then, let the doers do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>83</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>And surely among his party was Abraham.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>84</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>84</lastVerse>
      <text>When he came to his Lord with a sound heart.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>99</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>99</lastVerse>
      <text>He said, " Surely I am going to my Lord; He will guide me. "</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>And when he reached the age of striving with him, he said "O my son! I see in a dream that I will sacrifice thee. Look, what dost thou see?" He said, "O my father! Do as thou art commanded. Thou shalt find me, God willing, one of the patient."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>139</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>139</lastVerse>
      <text>Jonah too was one of the envoys.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>164</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>164</lastVerse>
      <text>None of us there is but has a known station.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>171</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>171</lastVerse>
      <text>Already Our word has preceded to the envoys.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="38">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Ṣād</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>He said, "My Lord, forgive me and give me a kingdom such as no one after me will have."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>71</lastVerse>
      <text>When thy Lord said to the angels, "I am creating a mortal of clay."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>76</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>76</lastVerse>
      <text>I am better than he: Thou hast created me of fire and Thou hast created him of clay.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="39">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We have sent the Book down to thee with the truth, so worship God, purifying the religion for Him.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Does not the pure religion belong to God?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>He created you from one soul and then made from it its mate.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>Is one who does devotions throughout the night, prostrating himself and standing, cautious about the next world and hoping for the mercy of his Lord? Say: "Are they equal, those who know and those who know not?"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>Is he whose breast God has expanded for the submission, so he is upon a light from his Lord? Woe to those whose hearts are hardened against the remembrance of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>And he who brings truthfulness and who assents to it, those are the godwary.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "O My servants who have been immoderate against yourselves, do not despair of God's mercy. Surely God forgives the sins altogether."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>Be penitent toward your Lord and submit to Him before the chastisement comes to you-then you will not be helped.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="40">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>ḤāÌ Mīm ḤāÌ is an allusion to love [maḥabba] and Mīm is an allusion to favor [minna]. He is saying, "O you who have become a friend through the ḤāÌ of My love, not through your own excellence! O you have found Me through the Mīm of My favor, not through your obedience! O you whom I took as My friend when you did not recognize Me! O you whom I wanted when you did not know Me! O you to whom I belonged when you did not belong to Me! A hundred thousand were standing at My threshold wanting Me and making their supplications. I paid no attention to them and I said to you without your asking, 'O community of Aḥmad, I bestowed upon you before you asked from Me, I responded to you before you called upon Me, and I forgave you before you asked Me to forgive you.'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Forgiver of sins and Accepter of repentance and Intense in punishment and Possessor of boons.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>Uplifter of degrees is He, Possessor of the Throne.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>64</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>God is He who made the earth for you a settledness and the heaven a building. And He formed you, so He made your forms beautiful, and He provided you with the goodly things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>He is the Living, there is no god but He.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="41">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>ḤāÌ Mīm</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>A sending down from the All-Merciful, the Ever-Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>He set in it unshakables from above it and He blessed it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>Those who have said, " Our Lord is God, " then gone straight-the angels will descend upon them saying, " Fear not and grieve not, and rejoice in the Garden that you were promised. "</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>We are your friends in this world's life and in the next world.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>And of His signs are the night and the day, the sun and the moon. Do not prostrate yourselves to the sun and the moon, but prostrate yourselves to God, who created them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>We shall show them Our signs on the horizons and in their souls until it is clear to them that He is the Real.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="42">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>The Creator of the heavens and the earth, He made for you from yourselves pairs and from your cattle pairs, thereby multiplying you. Nothing is as His likeness, and He is the Hearing, the Seeing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>God is gentle to His servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>And He responds to those who have faith and do wholesome deeds, and He increases them in His bounty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who sends down the rain after they have despaired and spreads out His mercy.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="43">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Shall We turn the remembrance away from you because you are an immoderate people?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>How many a prophet We sent among the ancients, but a prophet never came to them except that they mocked him</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>So We destroyed those stronger than they in seizing, and the example of the first ones passed away.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>67</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>67</lastVerse>
      <text>Bosom friends on that day will be enemies of one another, except for the godwary.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>68</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>68</lastVerse>
      <text>O My servants, no fear is upon you today, neither will you sorrow.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>71</lastVerse>
      <text>For them will be brought around platters and cups of gold. Therein will be whatever the souls hunger for and gives pleasure to the eyes.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="44">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>We chose them, with a knowledge, above the worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="45">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely in the heavens and the earth are signs for the faithful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>And in your creation and in the beasts He has scattered are signs for a people who have certainty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>And the difference of night and day, and the provision that God sends down from heaven whereby He brings the earth to life after its death, and the turning about of the winds, are signs for a people who use intelligence.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>Then We set thee on a wide road of the command, so follow it, and do not follow the caprices of those who know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely they will not make thee unneedy of God in anything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>Or do those who commit ugly deeds reckon that We will make them like those who have faith and do wholesome deeds, that their living and their dying will be equal? Ugly is what they reckon!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Who then will guide them after God?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>Today We forget you just as you forgot the encounter of this day of yours; your refuge is the Fire.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="46">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>The sending down of the book is from God, the Exalted, the Wise. These words are sent down by the Lord. They are His book and message, His sweet talk and blessed speaking. They are from a Lord whose name is Exalted, which means "exalter." The name means that He exalted the faithful by making them the object of His address and worthy of His book and message. He made their hearts the quarries of the lights of His secrets.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>We did not create the heavens and the earth and what is between the two except with the rightful due.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="47" />
  <chapter index="48">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We opened up for thee a clear opening.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="49">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>The faithful indeed are siblings.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="50">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Qāf! By the splendorous Qur'an!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>When the two receivers receive, sitting on the right and on the left.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>Not a word he utters, but by him is an observer ready.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>And the agony of death comes with the truth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely in that is a reminder for him who has a heart.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="51">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>By the scatterers scattering.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>49</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>Of everything We created a pair.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="52">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>And an inscribed book.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>By the Inhabited House.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>The day they are driven with a driving to the fire of hell._@_ This verse demands fear.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely the godwary will be in gardens and bliss, rejoicing in what their Lord has given them.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="53">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>By the star when it fell.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>Then He drew close, so He came down until he was two-bows' length away, or closer.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>He revealed to His servant what He revealed.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="54">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>49</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We created everything according to a measure.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely the godwary will be amidst gardens and a river.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="55">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>The All-Merciful-He taught the Qur'an.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>He created man. He taught him the explication.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>He mixed the two oceans that meet together.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>27</lastVerse>
      <text>All that is upon it undergoes annihilation, and there subsists the face of thy Lord, Possessor of Majesty and Generous Giving.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>Whatever is in the heavens and the earth asks of Him. Each day He is upon some task.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="56">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>As recompense for what they were doing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>59</lastVerse>
      <text>Have you seen the seed that you spill? Do you create it, or are We its creators?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>Do you create it, or are We its creators?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>We have determined death among you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>Glorify the name of your Lord the Tremendous!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>88</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>89</lastVerse>
      <text>If he is one of those brought near, then repose and ease and a garden of bliss.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>91</lastVerse>
      <text>If he be one of the companions of the right hand, then " Peace to you from the companions of the right hand. "</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="57">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Whatsoever is in the heavens and the earth glorifies God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>To Him belongs the kingdom of the heavens and the earth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>He is the First, the Last, the Outward, and the Inward, and He is knower of everything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>And He is with you wherever you are.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely God is to you clement, ever-merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>Their light running before them, and on their right hands.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>And a wall will be set up between them, inside of which is mercy and outside of which is chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="58">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>God has heard the words of her who disputes with thee concerning her husband and complains to God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, when you whisper with the Messenger, offer charity before you whisper.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="59">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>Whatever the Messenger gives you, take. Whatever he prohibits you, forgo.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>Those-they are the truthful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, be wary of God and let each soul consider what it has sent on ahead for tomorrow, and be wary of God.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="60">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, take not My enemy and your enemy as friends.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="61">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Everything in the heavens and the earth glorifies God, and He is the Exalted, the Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, why do you say what you do not do?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>Greatly hateful to God is it that you say what you do not do.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="62">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Everything in the heavens and the earth glorifies God, the King, the Holy, the Exalted, the Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="63">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>When the hypocrites come to thee they say, "We bear witness that thou art indeed the Messenger of God."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="64">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Everything in the heavens and everything in the earth glorifies Him. His is the kingdom and His is the praise, and He is powerful over everything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is who created you. Among you are unbelievers and among you are faithful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>16</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>16</lastVerse>
      <text>So be wary of God as much as you are able.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="65">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>O Prophet, when you divorce women, divorce them for the set period.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="66">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>O you who have faith, repent to God with true repentance.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="67">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Blessed is He in whose hand is the kingdom, and He is powerful over everything.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="68">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Nūn. By the Pen and what they inscribe.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="69">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>The Realizing! What is the Realizing?</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="70" />
  <chapter index="71">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>What is it with you that you do not hope for God with dignity? And He created you in stages.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="72" />
  <chapter index="73">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>O enwrapped in thy robe, stand at night save for a little.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>And recite the Qur'an with measured recitation.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>And remember the name of thy Lord and devote thyself to Him devoutly.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>Lord of the east and the west, there is no god but He, so take Him as a trustee.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>And be patient with what they say, and keep apart from them beautifully.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="74">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>O enwrapped in thy cloak, stand up and warn!</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="75">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>No! I swear by the Day of Resurrection.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>No! I swear by the blaming soul.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>Faces that day will be radiant, gazing upon their Lord.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="76">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Has an era come upon man when he was not a thing remembered?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely the pious shall drink of a cup whose mixture is of camphor.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>A fountain from which drink the servants of God, making it gush forth with a gushing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>And their Lord will pour for them a pure wine.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="77" />
  <chapter index="78" />
  <chapter index="79">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>By those that pluck harshly, by those that draw fiercely.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>On the day when the trembler trembles and the successor follows it, hearts on that day will be quivering, their eyes humbled.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="80">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>As for him who deemed himself without need, to him dost thou attend.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>38</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>There will be faces that day shining, laughing, joyous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>And there will be faces that day dusty, overspread with darkness-those are the unbelievers, the depraved.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="81">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>When the sun is enwrapped, and when the stars become opaque, and when the mountains are set moving...</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="82">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>O Man! What has deluded thee about thy generous Lord?</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="83">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>A book inscribed, witnessed by those given proximity.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="84">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>When heaven is split open.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>"O Man! Thou art toiling to thy Lord with toil, and thou shalt encounter Him."</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>He shall surely be called to account with an easy accounting and he shall return joyful to his folk.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>You shall surely ride stage after stage.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="85" />
  <chapter index="86">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>Over every soul there is a guardian.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>So let man consider of what he was created.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>He was created of gushing water, emerging from between the loins and the chest.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="87" />
  <chapter index="88" />
  <chapter index="89">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>By the even and the odd!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>27</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>O serene soul, return to thy Lord, approving, approved!</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="90" />
  <chapter index="91">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>By the soul and that which proportioned it and inspired it with its depravity and godwariness.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="92" />
  <chapter index="93" />
  <chapter index="94">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>Did We not expand for thee thy breast, and lift from thee thy burden that weighed down upon thy back, and raise up for thee thy mention?</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="95">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>By the fig, by the olive, by Mount Sinai, and by this secure land!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>Surely We created man in the most beautiful stature.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Then We shall restore him to the lowest of the low.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>They shall have a wage unfailing.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="96" />
  <chapter index="97" />
  <chapter index="98">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>They were commanded only to worship God, purifying the religion for Him as unswerving ones, and to perform the prayer and pay the alms tax; that is the enduring religion.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="99" />
  <chapter index="100" />
  <chapter index="101" />
  <chapter index="102">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Vying for increase distracts you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>But no, you will know. Then but no, you will know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>But no. Did you but know with the knowledge of certainty.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>You shall surely see the Blaze, then you shall see it with the eye of certainty.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="103">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>By the era! Surely man is in loss.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="104">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>He reckons that his wealth will make him last forever.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>But no, he will be thrown into the Crusher.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>And what will let thee know what is the Crusher?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>The lit-up fire of God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>Roaring over the hearts, coming down on them in outstretched columns.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="105" />
  <chapter index="106" />
  <chapter index="107" />
  <chapter index="108" />
  <chapter index="109">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "O unbelievers!"</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="110" />
  <chapter index="111">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Perish the hands of Abū Lahab, and perish he!</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="112">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: "He is God, One; God, the Self-Sufficient...."</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="113">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>Say: I seek refuge in the Lord of the daybreak.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="114" />
</tafsir>