<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<tafsir>
  <code>Kashani</code>
  <mufassir>Kashani</mufassir>
  <isTafsir>Y</isTafsir>
  <copyright>Content reproduced with permission of www.AlTafsir.com</copyright>
  <chapter index="1">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>In the Name of God: the name of a thing is that by which it can be known. The Names of God, exalted be He, are the [arche]typal forms (ṣuwar nawʿiyya) whose specificities and ipseities (hūwiyya) indicate the attributes of God and His essence, and [which indicate] by their very existence His countenance, and by their individuation His oneness. For, these are the outward manifestations through which He can be known; Allāh is a name for the divine essence qua essence absolutely, without taking into consideration that it may be qualified by the attributes or indeed taking into consideration that it may not be [so] qualified; the Compassionate, is the one who causes existence and perfection to flow upon all [things] in the measure that [divine] wisdom requires and to the capacity of the receiving entities (qawābil) from the outset [of their creation]; the Merciful: (al-Raḥīm) is the one who bestows the spiritual perfection (kamāl maʿnawī) that has been earmarked for the human species in the end [sc. in the Hereafter]. It is for this reason that they say O [You Who are the] Compassionate One of this world and of the Hereafter (yā raḥmān al-dunyā wa'l-ākhira), but [say] O Merciful One of the Hereafter (raḥīm al-ākhira): the meaning then is, in the perfect human all-encompassing form, general and specific mercy, which is the locus of manifestation of the divine essence and the greatest truth with the totality of attributes, I commence and I recite. It [Allāh] is the Greatest Name [of God]. It is to this meaning that the Prophet's (ṣlʿm) alluded when he said, 'I have been given the sum of all [excellent] speech [sc. The QurÌān] and have been sent to complete the noble character traits (makārim al-akhlāq). For words constitute the realities (ḥaqāÌiq) of existents (mawjūdāt) and their concrete substances (aʿyān), just as Jesus, peace be upon him, was called a Word from God [cf. 3:39,45]. The noble character traits are the perfections [of these existents] and [represent] their specifities, constituting the sources of their [the existents'] actions in their entirety, contained as they are in the comprehensive human microcosm (kawn insānī). Herein lies a subtlety (la?īfa), namely that the prophets, peace be upon them, have made the letters of the alphabet analogous to the ranks of existents (marātib al-mawjūdāt).</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Praise be to God; Lord of all Worlds, to the end of the sūra: 'praise' in actions and utterances of the moment (lisān al-ḥāl) is the manifestation (ẓuhūr) of perfections and the actualisation (ḥuṣūl) of the ends (ghāyāt) of things, since these are opening laudations and marvelous eulogies by the one granting them in accordance with what is due to that [object of eulogy]. For all existents, on account of their specificity and specific qualities and orientation towards their end-goals, and by the bringing forth of their perfections [sc. perfected states] from the space of potentiality into actuality, are proclaimers of [His] glory and praisers, as God, exalted be He, says: and there is not a thing but proclaims His praise [Q. 17:44]. Their proclamation of His glory is the declaration that He is above the need for any associate, [exalted above] the attributes of deficiency (naqṣ) and incapacity, [and this] by their very dependence on Him and their being indicators of His Oneness and His power. As for their praise [of Him], this is the manifesting of their derivative perfections and their being the loci of the manifestation of those attributes of majesty and beauty. His Essence is singled out [for praise] on account of His being the principle (mabdaÌ) of all things, and [on account of] His preservation and management of these, which constitute the very signification of [His] lordship of all worlds. In other words [praise be] to every knowable of the knowledge of God [being that] by which He is known, as in the case of the seal and what it seals and the mould and what is moulded in it. The construction [of ʿālam] is in the sound plural [ʿālamīn] because it subsumes the signification of 'knowledge' (ʿilm), or on account of the prevalence [of cognizant beings in these worlds]. In the face of [His] bestowing of good generally and specifically, that is, outward graces such as health and provision, and inner [graces] such as gnosis (maʿrifa) and knowledge (ʿilm); and on account of His being the ultimate end [of all things], which is the [true] signification of [His being] master of [all] things on the Day of Judgement, since in reality the only one who will requite will be the worshipped One, to whom all mastership returns at the time of requital either through the rewarding of everlasting grace in place of ephemeral [grace] upon the disengagement from this [latter] by means of renunciation and the self-disclosures of actions upon the servant's wrenching himself away from his actions and the replacement of his attributes with His attributes upon effacement (maḥw) and his subsistence (baqāÌ) through His Essence, and His gift to him of veridical [divine] existence (wujūd ḥaqqānī), upon his annihilation (fanāÌ).</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>Guide us to the straight path, in other words, fix us upon [the path of] guidance and empower us to remain upright along the path of oneness, that is, the path of those favoured [by You] with the special favour pertaining to [Your] Mercifulness (raḥīmiyya), which is gnosis, love and guidance, such as the prophets, the martyrs, the truthful and the friends (awliyāÌ) who have witnessed Him as the First and the Last, and as the Manifest and the Hidden, and who through the witnessing of the rise of His abiding countenance, became absent from the existence of ephemeral shadow.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="2">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>Alif lām mīm. That Book: these three letters constitute an allusion to the entirety of existence qua totality, because alif alludes to the essence of the one who is the first of existence, as has been mentioned; lām [alludes] to the active intellect, called Gabriel, who is the middle of existence receiving emanation from the principle [of existence] and overflowing upon the end [of existence]; mīm [alludes] to Muḥammad who is the last of existence with whom the cycle [of existence] comes full circle and [its last] is joined to its first, which is why he [Muḥammad] is the seal. He said, 'Verily time has come full circle back to its form on the day when God created the heavens and the earth'. According to one of the [pious] predecessors, 'The lām is made up of two alifs', in other words, analogous to the Essence together with its attribute of knowledge, which together constitute two of the three divine realms we have alluded to. It is thus one of God's Names, for each Name is made up of the Essence together with some [particular] attribute. As for mīm, this is an allusion to the Essence together with all of the attributes and the acts that have been veiled therein in the Muḥammadan form, which is God's Greatest Name, so that none knows this [Name] except the one who knows it. Do you not know how mīm, which is the form of the Essence, is veiled by It? Mīm has a yāÌ and the yāÌ has an alif. The mysterious aspect of the letters of the alphabet is that there is no letter that does not contain an alif. This [explanation] is similar to the statement that the meaning [of these letters] constitutes an oath by God, the Knowing, the Wise. For Gabriel is the locus of manifestation of knowledge and is thus His Name the Knowing, while Muḥammad is the locus of manifestation of wisdom and is thus His Name the Wise. From this becomes manifest the meaning of the statement, 'In every one of His Names there are an infinite number of names. In the realm of wisdom, which is the realm of cause and effect, knowledge is not complete and is not perfected unless it is combined with the act whereupon it becomes a wisdom.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>[those] who believe in the Unseen, and maintain the prayer: that is, [they believe] in what is absent to them in terms of the faith of following authority (taqlīdī), or that [faith] of the verification of knowledge. For faith is in two parts, that of following authority and that of verification. That of verification is [itself] divided into two, [verification] by reasoning (istidlāl) or by unveiling (kashfī), both of which [are] either [of the type that] stand at the limit of knowledge and of the unseen, or [of the type that] do not stand there. The former is to know [something] for certain, what is called the knowledge of certainty (ʿilm al-yaqīn); the second is either of the eye, namely, the witnessing (mushāhada) called the eye of certainty (ʿayn al-yaqīn), or of the reality, namely, the vision of self-disclosure, called the reality of certainty (ḥaqq al-yaqīn). The last two types do not belong to [the category of] belief in the Unseen. For belief in the Unseen requires works of the heart, namely, [self-]purification (tazkiya), which is the purification of the heart against becoming inclined to the exterior bodily fortunes that distract [one] from attaining abiding happiness. For happiness is of three kinds: that of the heart, that of the body and that which surrounds it. That [happiness] of the heart consists of gnostic sciences (maʿārif) and wisdoms, perfections of knowledge and practical perfections of character. As for [the happiness of] the body, this consists of physical well-being and strength, corporeal pleasures and natural passions. As for that [happiness] which surrounds [the body], this consists of wealth and means, just as the commander of the believers [ʿAlī b. Abī Ṭālib], peace be upon him: 'Verily, ample wealth is a grace, but more excellent than ample wealth is the well-being of the body and a God-mindful heart'. It is necessary to guard against [concerning oneself with] these former two in order to obtain this desired last by means of renunciation and worship. For to perform prayers is to abandon the comforts of the body and to tire the physical limbs, [prayer] being the mother of all [acts of] worship which when it is forthcoming the remainder follow, truly prayer prohibits lewd acts and indecency [Q. 45:29], since it is a burden and a great hardship upon both body and soul; while to expend of [one's] wealth [in charity] is to turn away from outward happiness beloved to the soul, what is called renunciation (zuhd).</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>and who believe in what has been revealed to you; and what was revealed before you, that is to say, the faith of verification that comprehends the three divisions [of faith], required for the works of the heart which constitute the adornment (taḥliya) and that is when the heart acquires perspicacity through the wisdoms and gnostic sciences revealed in the divine scriptures and [through] knowledge concerning the states [of creatures] in the final return (maʿād) and the matters of the Hereafter and the realities of holy knowledge, which is why He says: and of the Hereafter, they are certain. The people of the Hereafter are the ones who have not traversed the limit of purification and have not arrived at the [stage of] adornment which is the legacy (mīrāth) of that [traverse], on the basis of his [the imam ʿAlī's] saying, peace be upon him: 'Whoso acts in accordance with what he has been taught, God grants (warratha) him the knowledge of what he knows not'. The people of God, those of certainty, who comprehend [that legacy], they are all upon guidance from their Lord, [being] either [guided] to Him, or to His abode, the abode of safety (salāma), merit, reward and gentleness (lu?f): these are none other than the people of prosperity (falāḥ), [prosperous] by [having escaped] punishment or veiling, which is why He says</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>Those, namely, the ones enjoying the above-mentioned attributes relating to purification and adornment, are upon guidance from their Lord; those are the ones that will prosper, because of these [attributes]. Thus alladhīna yuÌminūna ('who believe') is the subject, the second alladhīna yuÌminūna is coordinated to it and ūlāÌika ('those are the ones') constitutes the predicate; but if it were construed as an adjectival qualification (ṣifa) of al-muttaqīn ('the God-fearing') [of verse 2], then what is meant is that they are the ones whose God-consciousness after the guidance [given to them] is perfect; this is [grammatically] feasible on the basis of [the feasibility] of referring to a thing by that to which it is about to allude.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>[From] As for the disbelievers, to where He says mighty [alike it is for them whether you have warned them or have not warned them, they do not believe.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>God has set a seal on their hearts, and on their hearing; and on their eyes is a covering; and for them there will be a mighty chastisement], [all of this] refers to the foremost group of the wretched ones who are subject to the overwhelming divine power (qahr ilāhī) for whom no warning is of any use and who have no means to being saved from the Fire: 'those are the ones against whom the word of your Lord was fulfilled: that they shall not believe' [cf. Q. 10:33] and thus was the word of your Lord fulfilled against those who disbelieve: that they shall be the inhabitants of the Fire [Q. 40:6] all paths shall be closed to them and the gates [of hell] shall be sealed shut upon them. For the heart is the divine waymark of the senses, the locus of inspiration from which they are veiled by its [the heart's] being sealed; while the hearing and the sight are the human waymarks of the senses, the pure ones which constitute the two gates of understanding and the capacity to take heed. These [wretched ones] are thus denied the use of these two [waymarks] because meaning is unable to penetrate from them into the heart. Thus they have no access inwardly to the unveiling knowledge of experiential taste, nor outwardly to taught and acquired knowledge and so they are interned in the prisons of darkness: how mighty therefore is their chastisement!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>And some people there are who say, 'We believe, these being the second group of the wretched who are deprived of [true] belief even as they claim [to have] it when they say 'we believe' in God, because the locus of belief is the heart and not the tongue: [as in the case of where] the bedouins say, 'We believe'. Say: 'You do not believe; but rather say, " We have submitted ", for faith has not yet entered into your hearts [Q. 49:14]. The meaning of their statement 'we believe in God and [in] the Last Day', is that they are claiming possession of the two [branches of] knowledge, that of God's oneness and that of the final return (maʿād), both of which constitute the principles of religion and its foundation. In other words, [they are saying] 'we are not like the polytheists who are veiled from the Truth nor like the People of the Scripture who are barred from [true knowledge of] religion and the final return - for, the teachings of the People of the Scripture concerning the final return does not accord with the truth. Know that to disbelieve is to be veiled and where one is veiled from the truth, as in the case of the polytheists, or from religion, as in the case of the People of the Scripture; and the one who is veiled from the truth is necessarily veiled from religion the very means by which one arrives at the truth. But the one who is veiled from religion may not necessarily be veiled from the truth. These, however, claim to be free of both veils at once. Thus they are shown to be liars by having their selves deprived of faith. In other words, so long as they are such they cannot be believers; [but they are not believers.]</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>[They would deceive God and the believers; and only themselves they deceive; and they are not aware.] Deception (mukhādaʿa) is the act of deceit from two parties. It is to manifest good [intentions] while concealing evil [ones]. To deceive God is to deceive His Messenger, on account of God's saying whoever obeys the Messenger, verily obeys God [Q. 4:80] and His saying and you threw not when you threw but God threw [Q. 8:17]; and because he [the Prophet] is His beloved. A ḥadīth has it that: 'And My servant does not cease to approach me through supererogatory acts until I love him. And when I love him, I become his hearing with which he hears and his sight with which he sees and his tongue with which he speaks and his hand with which he strikes and his foot with which he walks'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>In their hearts is a sickness, in other words, doubt and hypocrisy. The use of the indefinite form of mara? (sickness) and the adverbial clause is an indication of the fact that [such a] sickness has befallen them and has established itself and taken root in these [hearts of theirs, as we have mentioned in the above structure, for otherwise He would have said: 'Their hearts are sick or [that they are] dead'; and God has increased them in sickness, that is, [with] another [sickness]: [God increases their] spite, envy and rancour by exalting the word of religion and the granting of assistance to the Messenger and the believers. All despicable acts are sicknesses of the heart as they are cause of its weakening and the evil of its private actions and its ruin in the final issue. He distinguishes between the two chastisements by [stipulating] pain for the hypocrites and an awesome [chastisement] for disbelievers, because the chastisement for those who have been banished from pre-eternity is greater. Thus they do not experience the intensity of its painfulness because of the impurity of their hearts' perception, similar to the state of a dead or hemiplegic or numbed limb [that senses nothing] when it undergoes severing or cauterisation and other kinds of pain. As for the hypocrites, they sense the extreme pain because of their established preparedness [for belief] at the outset and the permanence of their [faculties of] perception. Inevitably then their chastisement is painful, caused as it is by the chronic sickness that occurs [in their hearts], namely, mendacity and its [evil] concomitants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>When it is said to them, 'Do not work corruption on earth', they say, 'We are only putting things right'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>Truly, they are the agents of corruption, but they perceive not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>When it is said to them, 'Believe as the people believe', they say, 'Shall we believe as fools believe?' Truly, they are the foolish ones, but they know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>When they meet those who believe: a literal quotation of their hypocrisy that is a concomitant of the presence of two [kinds of] preparedness within them, a primordial luminous one that is weak, vanquished and close to being extinguished, and by which they correspond to the believers; and an acquired dark one that is strong and vanquishing by which they are in harmony with the disbelievers. For if they did not possess a minimum of light they would not be able to mix with and befriend believers in the first place as is the case with others like the disbelievers, because of the self-evident mutual incompatibility between light and darkness in all aspects. [The word] shay?ān is constructed to the paradigm fayʿāl from [the infinitive] al-shu?ūn which means 'to go far away', their devils being profoundly removed [from the divine], banished, while their leaders have attained the utmost degree of hypocrisy. Their mocking of the believers is proof of the weakness of the light aspect within them and the strength of the dark aspect, for the one who belittles something is one for whom that thing is slight, of little weight or worth. Thus they belittle those luminous individuals because of the littleness of light within them, since it is [only] by light that the value of light can be known. Given the preponderance of darkness within them, they resort to the disbelievers and become friendly with them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>God [Himself] mocks them, that is, He belittles them because from the aspect in which they find themselves their relationship to the Divine Presence is slight and weak, and so in the same measure that the Divine aspect is diminished in them, they become more firmly attached to their souls, whereas for the believers the more that their ego-centric (nafsānī) make-up is diminished the more that they find themselves by God's side: what a difference between the two [states]! reinforcing them, in their bestial and predatorial darknesses, which are satanic and ego-centric attributes, by setting up [for them] the substrata and causes [of these resultant attributes], namely their passions, sensual delights, property and livelihood in this world, all of which they have chosen on account of their caprice in their state of bewilderment, in their insolence, bewildered (yaʿmahūn): ʿamah is blindness of the heart, while their insolence is their transgressing of the [divinely stipulated] limit which they are supposed to respect. That limit is the breast (ṣadr), that is, the aspect of the heart that is adjacent to the soul (nafs), whereas the inner heart (fuÌād) is that aspect [of the heart] that is adjacent to the spirit (rūḥ), and so it sits in the middle [between the two] with aspects towards both of these: to adhere to that limit is to worship by [adhering to] the commands of God, exalted be He, and [to] His prohibitions, simultaneously turning to Him in order to seek illumination so that this aspect may be illumined and thereby the soul is illuminated. To adhere to the other limit is to receive gnosis, sciences, realities, wisdoms and divine prescriptions so that these might become etched upon the breast and the soul be adorned thereby. Insolence is to be engrossed in the ego-centric, bestial, predatorial and satanic attributes that overcome the heart, blackening it and blinding it, and sullying the spirit [as a result].</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>16</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>16</lastVerse>
      <text>Those are they who have bought in exchange for guidance error, that is, darkness and being veiled from the path of truth, namely, religion, or from the truth [itself], for error is dispersed in the face of guidance through the original light of preparedness; so their commerce brings no profit [for them], because their capital derives from the world of light and subsistence so that they might acquire by this [capital] what resembles it in the way of effusive, perfecting light through the sciences, deeds, wisdoms, gnosis, character traits and virtuous dispositions becoming thereby rich in reality, deserving of proximity, dignity, exaltation and esteem before God, but they have not profited by acquiring [all of] that; [nor are they guided] and thus the original guidance that had been their commodity and capital is lost by the disappearance of their preparedness and the sullying of their hearts by the rust that necessarily leads to eternal veiling and deprivation and so their loss is an eternal one without beginning or end.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>Their likeness, that is, to describe them in terms of their hypocrisy is like describing the one seeking to kindle [a fire] and the resultant light which no sooner than it illumines things nearby around him his fire subsides, leaving him bewildered. For the light of their preparedness can be compared to a kindled fire and its illumining of things around them is their being guided to what is in their best interest in terms of their livelihood in the here and now, as opposed to what is in their best interest in terms of the final return that is [seemingly] far away for them, and [their being guided to] companionship of the believers and being in accord with them outwardly; its [his fire's] being extinguished swiftly is the dying out of their light of preparedness and the rapid evanescence of what they had been content with of their world and its imminent termination; [is as the likeness of one who kindled a fire, and when it illumined all about him]</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>deaf, dumb, blind, in reality because of their hearts being veiled from the light of the intellect by which they hear the truth, utter it and see it. Outwardly, because of their not being beneficial, given that the paths from those sense to the heart are blocked and given the locus of the veil, the light of the heart does not reach them so that they might have preserved their benefits; nor do its perceptions touch the heart so that they might understand and take heed; they shall not return, to God because of the two barriers set upon their hearts, [the two barriers] mentioned in His statement and We have set before them a barrier and behind them a barrier [Q. 36:9]. The use of the simile lies in depicting what is intellectual in tangible form that it might find visible expression in the souls of the common folk. He then likens them to a people who are struck by rain amidst darkness, thunder and lightning: rain is the descent of the divine revelation and the arrival of [divine] mercy as assistance to them through the blessedness of the companionship of the believers and the remainder of their preparedness that might benefit their hearts even minimally; and [the rain] is also the materialisation for them of outward graces consistent with their wishes outwardly. The darknesses are the ego-centric attributes and the imaginal and illusory doubts and the satanic whisperings that bewilder them and fill them with anxiety. Thunder is the divine fulmination and the overwhelmingly powerful threat [of chastisement] mentioned in the QurÌān, its verses and the aurally and visually received reports, that which frightens them and results in the smallest breaking of their insolent hearts and a defeat of their rejecting souls. Lightning is the luminous flashes and the spiritual alerts upon hearing the promise [of reward] and being reminded of the favours and blessings that which entices them and gives them hope [of salvation] and thus profits them with a small yearning and sways them to [hope for] the granting [of their supplications].</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>Or as a cloudburst out of the heaven in which is darkness, and thunder, and lightning -</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>The lightning, namely, the luminous flash, well-nigh snatches away their sight, that is, their intellects veiled as they are by slumber from the light of guidance and unveiling, for the intellect is the eye of the heart; whensoever it gives them light, they walk in it, that is, they rise [in status] and come closer to accepting the truth and guidance; and when the darkness is over them, they stop, that is, they remain fixed in their [state of] bewilderment in that darkness of theirs; had God willed, He would have taken away their hearing and their sight, He would have obliterated their understanding and intellect and effaced the light of their preparedness as in the case of the former group, and so they are not even affected upon hearing the revelation in the first place. Truly, God has power over all things, [be it] an externally existent thing, necessary or contingent, as well as a mentally existent thing, contingent or impossible. For a non-thing is purely a non-existent, neither in the mind nor externally [sc. in the created universe]; but His power specifically relates to that which is contingent and not to what is necessary or what is impossible, this [is clear] by rational proof. This concludes the discussion of the seven categories in undifferentiated form and a separation between the two groups of wretched ones. The mention of the first group is brief and kept to a minimum because discussion of them is of no use and is fully gleaned from the mention of the second group. Thus the criticism, reviling and censure entailed in the depiction of their status, as well as their being threatened and promised punishment and the condemnation of their conduct and their habits is on account of the possibility of their accepting guidance and the disappearance of the sickness that afflicts them and the kindling of the light of their innate dispositions by the aid of the divine granting of success, that perhaps such rebuke might break the strength of their obstinacy and that such scolding might extirpate the roots of their despicable acts so that their inner aspects might then be purified, their hearts illumined by the light of the will whereafter they follow the path of truth. Perhaps their friendly and gentle attitude towards the believers and their keeping company with them might incline them towards their [the believers'] good nature awakening some love and desire within them by which their hearts then soften to the remembrace of God [cf.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>O people [worship your Lord Who created you and those that were before you, so that you may be fearful], having concluded His mention of the fortunate and the damned, He calls them to [declaration of] the Oneness of God. The first stage of [declaring] the Oneness of God, is to declare the unity of [His] acts, which is why servanthood is tied to lordship, that they might feel the intimacy when they see the graces [given to them] and love Him, like when He said: 'I made creatures and sought their love through the graces [that I grant them]'. They then thank Him for these, for worship is gratitude and is only forthcoming in return for graces. He singles out His lordship for them so that they might single out their worship for Him. He seeks to lift the first of the three veils which are the veils of the acts, the attributes and [the veil of His] essence by means of the presentation of the self-disclosure of the acts because creatures in terms of the three [veils] are all, as engendered things, veiled from the truth absolutely. Thus the origin of their configuration (inshāÌ) and the configuration of their existence is dependent upon in terms of principles, causes and conditions, is the same as that of their mothers and fathers before them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>[He Who assigned to you the earth for a couch and heaven for an edifice; and sent down from the heaven water, wherewith He brought forth fruits for your provision] He has assigned the earth to them for a couch so that it might be their resting place and their domicile, and He has assigned [to them] the heaven for an edifice so that it might shelter them, and He has sent down water from the heaven and therewith brought forth plants from the earth so that this might be provision for them [drawing them thereby] to Himself, that they might beware of attributing the act to other than Him and thus rise above associating acts [with any other than Him] when they witness that these are all from God. That is why He mentions what results from these anteceding [graces] using [the coordinating particle] fāÌ, saying: so set not up compeers to God, while you know, what we have mentioned in the way of things given, as though He were saying that He was the one who has performed these acts and so worship can only be truly for Him and should not be assigned to any other than Him. Do not therefore set up a compeer to Him by attributing the act to this [compeer] that this [latter] would then deserve to be worshipped by you and that you then worship this [compeer] even as you are aware of [the transgression involved in] that. Their worship should only be for the Maker. Their Lord is the one who discloses Himself in the form of maker, since every servant only worships what he knows and he can only know God in the measure that he finds divinity in himself. They can only find the Doer, freely chosen [by them] and so they worship Him. The ultimate goal of such worship is to arrive at Paradise, which is the perfection of the world of acts. God has made smooth the earths of their souls and constructed upon them the heavens of their spirits, sending down from these heavens the water of the science of declaring the unity of [His] acts, therewith bringing forth from that earth the plants of submission as well as works, acts of obedience, and virtuous character traits so that from these He might provide for their hearts the fruits of certainty, as well as the states and the stations such as patience, gratitude and reliance.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>And if you are in doubt concerning what We have revealed, that is, [doubt concerning] Our revelation to Muḥammad and thus doubt the truthfulness of his prophethood, then weigh up your human forces and summon your analogy-strong minds, veiled [as they are] from the light of guidance, and your thoughts, skilful [as they are] in putting together speech and arranging meanings, being as you are of your own, children of your species: would you be able to produce a sūra, that is, a segment of speech like it? [to Our servant, then bring a sūra like it; and call your witnesses besides God] if you are truthful, in attributing it to Muḥammad.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>And if you do not, then be pliant, submit, believe and abandon obstinacy that will eventually lead you to the Fire. The requisite, that is either faith or submission, has been omitted, while the concomitant, which is to guard against the Fire, has replaced it, so that the proof that denial necessarily leads to entering the Fire and the eventuality of chastisement for them is stronger. As for His saying and you will not, is a parenthetical statement informing [them] of the unseen in the knowledge that the intellects of those who are veiled are barred from such [knowledge]; [then fear the Fire] what is meant by the Fire is their being consumed by the upheaval of their souls and the evil of their natures, [natures] which are turned away from the spiritual holy spirit and the breeze of the tasting of the Compassionate, and deprived from the pleasure of the coolness of certainty and the safety of the abode of permanence, severed [as their natures are] by the habits of the senses and corporeal pleasures, prohibited by what they have become addicted and accustomed to, while there remain [within them] the yearning for that [spirit] and the rapture [felt for it], [but] the deeply rooted conditions of attachment to the lower affairs in them and their love of earthly bodies are the causes of the igniting of their fires, which is why He says: whose fuel is men, and stones, that is, the silent sensory lower matters to which they are attached out of love so that the forms of these [matters] have become deeply-rooted in their souls while their souls have become imprisoned by having inclined to these very [forms]. As the Messenger, peace and blessings be upon him, said: 'Every person is gathered [at the resurrection] with the one that he loves, so that if one of you loved a stone he will be gathered with it'. How can it be otherwise when his own form has fixed itself within him through love so that the form of his heart has become his own form. Know that the [intensity of the] heat of the fire follows from its [arche-]typal form that constitutes its spirituality and its kingdom, for otherwise it would be equal in its specific qualities to all bodies; that spirituality are sparks of the fire of God's overwhelming supra-sensory power after its descent into several ranks, such as its descent into the rank of the soul upon the upheaval of rage, for the upheaval of rage might have the effect of consuming the character traits in a way that not even fire might have on firewood.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>And give good tidings to those who believe, in the Maker and who have performed deeds that make them good for Paradise in accordance with their knowledge of the unity of [God's] acts, [give them good tidings] that they shall have what they want and desire over and above what they imagined and longed for, because of the indefinite form of 'Gardens'. Gardens underneath which rivers run are the most splendid and delightful that a place can be and the most pleasurable and sweetest that a desired thing can be for the people of this world, for these [gardens] for their souls are of the same kind as the gardens of this world but purer than them, commensurate with the physicality of the final return, which is real as you shall see;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>God is not ashamed, He is not prohibited by what would [normally] prohibit the one who experiences shame, to strike a similitude even of a gnat, or anything above it, for in the eyes of God the disbeliever is lowlier than a gnat and this world [lowlier] than its wings, as stated by the ḥadīth.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>27</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>27</lastVerse>
      <text>Those such as break the covenant of God after its solemn binding: this is what is alluded to in His statement: And when your Lord took from the Children of Adam, from their loins, their seed and made them testify against themselves, 'Am I not your Lord?', they said, 'Yea, indeed "' [Q. 7:172]. It is mentioned in a ḥadīth that God, exalted be He, stroked Adam's back with His hand and brought forth his seed from him like particles, [to the end of] the ḥadīth. God's hand is the holiest intellect and the first spirit which is the spirit of the world that is referred to as the right-hand of the Compassionate; Adam is the universal reasoning soul which is itself the heart of the world; His stroking of his back constitutes the effect of the intellect upon it [the soul] and its illuminating of it by His light through the spiritual joining; His bringing forth of his seed from him constitutes the bringing into existence of the individual partial souls that had been inside it in potentiality and bringing them out in actuality; God's covenant with them where He says, 'Am I not your Lord?', is the depositing of the knowledge of [His] Oneness in their essences; the binding of that covenant is the propping up of the proofs of His Oneness in their intellects and His obligating them to that knowledge, making it a binding aspect of their essences, so that upon their disengagement from the attributes of the soul and the coverings of the body such [knowledge] would [immediately] become clear to them and the most manifest and obvious of things would be disclosed to them, namely, their having been made to testify against themselves, since such knowledge would at that instance become necessary. Their response to that [question] with 'Yea, indeed', constitutes their essential acceptance of that [truth]. Their breaking of that covenant is their total engrossment in the carnal pleasures and the trappings of the physical world and their enslavement by their desires and lusts such that they become veiled by these from [the knowledge of] God's Oneness and His worship. [and such as cut what God has commanded should be joined]: their 'cutting of what God has commanded should be joined' is their turning away from the joining with the Holy Spirit, the highest points of origin [of motion] and the heavenly spirits who are the High Council [cf.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>How do you disbelieve in God, that is, in which state are you veiled from Him, when your state is that of, when you were dead, drops of sperm in the loins of your forefathers, and He gave you life, in other words, why do you not see the proof of the Creator in [His] creation, then He shall make you dead, through natural death, then He shall give you life, through resurrection, for the former is known by means of the witnessing while the latter [is known] by deduction from the original creation, then to Him you shall be returned!, for requital, or [it means] that He makes you dead [separated] from your souls through voluntary death which is annihilation in the Oneness, whereafter He gives you life through true life which is subsistence after annihilation through that existence which is the bestowal of the Truth, after which you are returned to Him for the witnessing (mushāhada), if the unity is the unity of [His] attributes, or for the presential vision (shuhūd), if the unity is the unity of His Essence.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>He it is Who created for you all that is in the earth, in other words, the lower aspect which is the world of the elements in its entirety since it constitutes the origin points of your creation and the substrata of your existence and subsistence; then He presided over [the heaven], that is, He turned evenly to the upper aspect - thumma ('then') is used to indicate a separation between the two aspects and the two moments of existentiation, the originational (ibdāʿī) and the creational (takwīnī), and not a lapse between the two time periods, so that the creation of the earth necessarily precedes that of the heavens; [and He levelled them seven heavens and He has knowledge of all things]: He then proportioned them as seven heavens according to what the generality thinks, for the eighth and the ninth [heavens] are [respectively] the seat (kursī) and the throne (ʿarsh) in their manifest dimension. In reality the lower aspect is the corporeal world, like the body and its limbs given its inferior rank in relation to the spiritual world which is the upper aspect referred to by the expression 'heaven'; thumma is used to indicate a separation between [the act of] creation and the command; 'and He levelled them seven heavens' is an allusion to the ranks of the world of spiritual beings: the first is the angelic earthly realm and the forces of the soul and the jinn; the second is the world of the soul; the third is the world of the heart; the fourth is the world of the intellect; the fifth is the world of the mysteries; the sixth is the world of the spirit while the seventh is the world of concealment, which is the spiritual mystery distinct from the mystery of the heart. It is to this that the Commander of the Believers [ʿAlī b. Abī Ṭālib], peace be upon him, alluded when he said: 'Ask me about the paths of the heavens, for I know them better than the paths of the earth'. Its paths are the states and the stations such as renunciation, reliance, satisfaction and the like. Know that the intellect when referred to by the term wisdom is the spirit in the terminology of the Sufis. And what we have referred to as the intellect in the terminology of the Sufis is the rational faculty that belongs to the speaking soul according to the philosophers. That is why the Sufis say that the intellect is the polished part of the heart illumined by the light of the spirit, while the heart is the speaking soul. Remember this lest [your] understanding become confused by the different terms [used].</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>And when your Lord said to the angels: idh ('when') refers to an endless duration that is from pre-eternity to sempiternity; the 'saying' is the casting of the meaning of the connectedness of God's will to the existentiation of Adam onto the holy essences of the realm of divine power, namely the angels brought near and the disengaged spirits and those [spirits] of the angelic realm constituting the heavenly souls. For everything that occurs in the world of engendered things has a form before becoming engendered in the world of the spirit which is the world of the pre-decree, followed by the world of the heart which is the heart of the world known as the Preserved Tablet, followed by the world of the soul, namely, the soul of the world that is the Tablet of 'effacement and fixing' [cf. Q. 13:39] expressed as the heaven of this world (samāÌ al-dunyā) in the revelation, as God says: And there is not a thing but that the stores thereof are with Us, and We do not send it down except in a known measure [Q. 15:21]. That then is His saying to the angels: 'I am appointing on earth a vicegerent': consider in yourself your state, for all that manifests itself upon your limbs, which constitute your engendered world and the world of your witnessing, in the way of words and deeds exists within your spirit which is hidden beyond your unseen and in the unseen of your unseen then in your soul which is the closest unseen to you and your heaven of this world before it becomes manifest upon your limbs; 'to appoint' is more general than origination and engenderment. He did not say 'I am creating' because man is a composite of both worlds. A viceregent that will assume My character traits and My descriptions and execute My command and rule My creatures and manage their affair, keeping their laws in check, summoning them to obedience of Me. The disapproval of the angels when they said: 'What, will You appoint therein one who will do corruption therein and shed blood, and their intimation of the priority that they enjoy by saying: while we glorify You with praise and sanctify You?', is their being veiled from the manifestation of the inner meaning of divinity and the lordly descriptions in him [sc.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>And He taught Adam the names, all of them, that is, He cast upon his heart the specific qualities of things, [the qualities] by which they, their benefits and their harmfulness, can be known. Then He presented them, that is, He presented those named things, to the angels, through their witnessing of the human structure and their accompaniment of Adam in the revelation. The meaning of His words: and He said, 'Now tell Me the names of these if you speak truly', [is] His will that they be revitalised by some of the objects of man's knowledge, as required by the human composition and the conveying of the objects of his senses and his diverse knowledge, temporally originated in him through the specificity of [his] composition and his social condition, to their essences after not having been [there], since their knowledge ensues from his knowledge and that is the sense in which they are dumbfounded [by God] and the connection between that and His will is reflected in the command given to Adam to 'tell', since all of the human faculties and the angels that are in His presence are revitalised by what in a different locus they would not be revitalised; that is the meaning of Adam's telling them [of the names].</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>As for the meaning of: They said, 'Glory be to You! We know not except what You have taught us. Surely You are the Knower, Wise', [that is] the testimony of their being through evidence and of the tongues of their state that they fall short of the human perfections and their inability to outdo them; and [testimony] of God's being above an act that would entail corruption in general and their awareness of their inability to rise to their levels by the acquisition of knowledge, since their perfections go hand in hand with their being and that His knowledge, exalted be He, is above their knowledge, for He is the absolute Knower and the Wise that does only what ought to be done, which is why He says:</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>He said, 'Adam, tell them their names', and He did not say 'teach them' because acquired knowledge that entails [spiritual] ascension is of the specific qualities of the all-comprehensiveness of humankind. Thus each [quality] accepts only what accords with its nature of that genus of perceptibles and not any other. Just as, for example, vision [exists in humans] because of the many visible things, so it does not increase knowledge or level and accepts only what belongs to the genus of visibles even if these be manifold. Such is the state of every inner faculty. [And when he had told them their names He said] As for the meaning of: 'Did I not tell [you that I know the Unseen in the heavens and the earth?] [that is] an affirmation by Him concerning the natures of the angels, that He, exalted be He, knows what they know not of the Unseen in the heavens and the earth, that which is the mystery of spiritual knowledge and [divine] love, deposited in man whose knowledge God has taken unto Himself.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>And when We said to the angels, 'Prostrate yourselves to Adam: their prostrating to Adam represents their pliancy and their submissiveness to him and their being rendered obedient to him and at his disposal; so they prostrated themselves, except Iblīs, he refused and disdained: Iblīs is the illusory power because it does not belong to the [class of] purely earthly angels that are veiled from the ability to perceive meanings by perceiving forms so that it would [like these angels] yield to the overwhelming power of God out of obedience to His command; nor does it belong to the [class of] heavenly rational [angels] so that it would [like these] become aware of the noble status of Adam and in harmony with his intellect and thus yield out of love seeking divine approval. He [Iblīs] was of the jinn, that is, from among those of the lower angelic realm and the earthly power. He was reared and raised behind the backs of the heavenly angels because of his capacity to perceive meanings of particulars and his ascension to the horizon of reason; that is why compared to the intellect in man, he [Iblīs] was like the animals that are incapable of speech. His refusal is his non-submission to reason and his refraining from accepting its wisdoms; his disdain is his attempt to be superior to that which was created from clay and to the heavenly and earthly angels by not adhering to the limits of his ability to perceive those meanings of particulars that are attached to the impressions of the senses; [his disdain is also] his transgressing his condition by delving into rational meanings and universal rules; and so he became one of the disbelievers, who are pre-eternally veiled from the lights of the intellect and the coupled [lights] in addition to the light of unity.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>And We said, 'Adam, dwell and your partner in the Garden, his partner is the soul and is named ḤawwāÌ (Eve) because of her constant clinging to the body of darkness, since life (ḥayāt) is the colour that is preponderantly black, while the heart is named Adam because of its attachment to the body though not constantly, for adama is a tanned colour, that is, the colour which is close to black. Were it not for his attachment, he would not have been named Adam. The 'Garden' in which the two [Adam and Eve] were commanded to remain is the heaven of the world of spirits that is the holy garden. In other words, [the command to them is] 'Remain in the heaven of the spirit'; and eat thereof easefully where you desire, that is, embrace and walk amply across it to receive the meanings, knowledge and wisdoms in it, that are the nourishments of the heart and the spiritual fruits, as amply as you wish, and in any direction, level, state or station that you desire. For it is everlasting, unceasing and unprohibited; [but do not come near this tree] lest you be evildoers (ẓālimīn)', who place light in the place of darkness which is not its place, and who diminish the light of their preparedness and their share of the world of light; for [the meaning of] ẓulm is traditionally understood as [meaning] to place something where it does not belong; lexically [it means] to take away from an obligatory right or share.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="3" />
  <chapter index="4" />
  <chapter index="5" />
  <chapter index="6" />
  <chapter index="7" />
  <chapter index="8" />
  <chapter index="9" />
  <chapter index="10" />
  <chapter index="11" />
  <chapter index="12" />
  <chapter index="13" />
  <chapter index="14" />
  <chapter index="15" />
  <chapter index="16" />
  <chapter index="17" />
  <chapter index="18" />
  <chapter index="19" />
  <chapter index="20" />
  <chapter index="21" />
  <chapter index="22" />
  <chapter index="23" />
  <chapter index="24" />
  <chapter index="25" />
  <chapter index="26" />
  <chapter index="27" />
  <chapter index="28" />
  <chapter index="29" />
  <chapter index="30" />
  <chapter index="31" />
  <chapter index="32" />
  <chapter index="33" />
  <chapter index="34" />
  <chapter index="35" />
  <chapter index="36" />
  <chapter index="37" />
  <chapter index="38" />
  <chapter index="39" />
  <chapter index="40" />
  <chapter index="41" />
  <chapter index="42" />
  <chapter index="43" />
  <chapter index="44" />
  <chapter index="45" />
  <chapter index="46" />
  <chapter index="47" />
  <chapter index="48" />
  <chapter index="49" />
  <chapter index="50" />
  <chapter index="51" />
  <chapter index="52" />
  <chapter index="53" />
  <chapter index="54" />
  <chapter index="55" />
  <chapter index="56" />
  <chapter index="57" />
  <chapter index="58" />
  <chapter index="59" />
  <chapter index="60" />
  <chapter index="61" />
  <chapter index="62" />
  <chapter index="63" />
  <chapter index="64" />
  <chapter index="65" />
  <chapter index="66" />
  <chapter index="67" />
  <chapter index="68" />
  <chapter index="69" />
  <chapter index="70" />
  <chapter index="71" />
  <chapter index="72" />
  <chapter index="73" />
  <chapter index="74" />
  <chapter index="75" />
  <chapter index="76" />
  <chapter index="77" />
  <chapter index="78" />
  <chapter index="79" />
  <chapter index="80" />
  <chapter index="81" />
  <chapter index="82" />
  <chapter index="83" />
  <chapter index="84" />
  <chapter index="85" />
  <chapter index="86" />
  <chapter index="87" />
  <chapter index="88" />
  <chapter index="89" />
  <chapter index="90" />
  <chapter index="91" />
  <chapter index="92" />
  <chapter index="93" />
  <chapter index="94" />
  <chapter index="95" />
  <chapter index="96" />
  <chapter index="97" />
  <chapter index="98" />
  <chapter index="99" />
  <chapter index="100" />
  <chapter index="101" />
  <chapter index="102" />
  <chapter index="103" />
  <chapter index="104" />
  <chapter index="105" />
  <chapter index="106" />
  <chapter index="107" />
  <chapter index="108" />
  <chapter index="109" />
  <chapter index="110" />
  <chapter index="111" />
  <chapter index="112" />
  <chapter index="113" />
  <chapter index="114" />
</tafsir>