<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<tafsir>
  <code>Qushairi</code>
  <mufassir>Al-Qushairi</mufassir>
  <isTafsir>Y</isTafsir>
  <copyright>Content reproduced with permission of www.AlTafsir.com</copyright>
  <chapter index="1">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>1:1 In the Name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>[1:2] Praise be to God;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>[1:3] The Compassionate, the Merciful</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>[1:4] Master of the day of Judgement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>[1:5] You [alone] we worship, and You [alone] we ask for help.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>[1:6] Guide us to the straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="2">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:1] Alif lām mīm.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:2] That Book, in it there is no doubt.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>3</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:3] Who believe in the Unseen, and maintain the prayer</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>4</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:4] and who believe in what has been revealed to you; and what was revealed before you; and of the Hereafter, they are certain.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:5] Those are upon guidance from their Lord; those are the ones that will prosper</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:6] As for the disbelievers, alike it is for them whether you have warned them or have not warned them, they do not believe.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:7] God has set a seal on their hearts, and on their hearing; and on their eyes is a covering; and for them will be a mighty chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:8] And some people there are who say, 'We believe in God and the Last Day'; but they are not believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:9] They would deceive God and the believers; and only themselves they deceive; and they are not aware.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:10] In their hearts is a sickness; and God has increased their sickness; and there awaits them a painful chastisement because they used to lie.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:11-12] When it is said to them, 'Do not corruption in the land', they say, 'We are only putting things right'. * Truly, they are the agents of corruption, but they perceive not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:13] When it is said to them, 'Believe as the people believe', they say, 'Shall we believe as fools believe?' Truly, they are the foolish ones, but they know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:14-15] When they meet those who believe, they say, 'We believe'; but when they go apart to their devils they say, 'We are with you; we were only mocking'. * God [Himself] mocks them, leaving them in their insolence, bewildered.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>16</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>16</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:16] Those are they who have bought error for guidance; so their commerce has not profited them; nor are they guided.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:17] Their likeness is as the likeness of one who kindled a fire, and when it illumined all about him God took away their light and left them in darkness, unable to see,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:18] deaf, dumb, blind, they shall not return</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:19] Or as a cloudburst out of the heaven in which is darkness, and thunder, and lightening - they put their fingers in their ears against the thunderclaps, cautious of death; and God encompasses the disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:20] The lightening well-nigh snatches away their sight; whensoever it gives them light, they walk in it; and when the darkness is over them; they stop; had God willed, He would have taken away their hearing and sight; Truly, God has power over all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:21] O people, worship your Lord Who created you and those that were before you, so that you may be fearful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:22] He Who assigned to you the earth for a couch and heaven for an edifice; and sent down from the heaven water, wherewith He brought forth fruits for your provision; so set not up compeers to God, while you know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:23-24] And if you are in doubt concerning what We have revealed to Our servant, then bring a sūra like it; and call your witnesses besides God if you are truthful. * And if you do not and you will not, then fear the Fire, whose fuel is men, and stones, prepared for disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:25] And give glad tidings to those who believe and perform righteous deeds that theirs shall be Gardens underneath which rivers run</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:26] God is not ashamed to strike a similitude even of a gnat, or anything above it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>27</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>27</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:27] Those such as break the covenant with God after its solemn binding, and such as cut what God has commanded to be joined; and such as do corruption in the land - they shall be the losers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:28] How do you disbelieve in God, when you were dead, and He gave you life; then He shall make you dead, then He shall give you life, then to Him you shall be returned!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:29] He it is who created for you all that is in the earth;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:30] And when your Lord said to the angels, 'I am appointing on earth a viceregent', they said, 'What, will You appoint therein one who will do corruption therein and shed blood, while we glorify You with praise and sanctify You?'; He said, 'Assuredly, I know what you know not'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:31] And He taught Adam the names, all of them; then He presented them to the angels and said, 'Now tell Me the names of these if you speak truly'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:32] They said, 'Glory be to You! We know not except what You have taught us. Surely You are the Knower, Wise'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:33] He said, 'Adam, tell them their names'; And when he had told them their names He said, 'Did I not tell you that I know the Unseen in the heavens and the earth?, And I know what you reveal and what you were hiding.'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:34] And when We said to the angels, 'Prostrate yourselves to Adam; so they prostrated themselves, except Iblīs, who refused and disdained; and so he became one of the disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:35] And We said, 'Adam dwell and your wife in the Garden and eat thereof easefully where you desire; but do not come near this tree lest you be evildoers'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>36</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>36</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:36] Then Satan caused them to slip therefrom and brought them out of what they were in</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:37] Thereafter Adam received certain words from his Lord and He relented to him; truly He is the Relenting, the Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>38</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>38</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:38] We said, 'Go down from it all together, yet there shall come to you from Me guidance, and whoever follows My guidance, no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:39] As for the disbelievers who deny Our signs, those shall be the inhabitants of the Fire, abiding therein'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:40] O Children of Israel, remember My favor wherewith I favored you;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:41] And believe in what I have revealed, confirming that which is with you; and be not the first to disbelieve in it. And do not sell My signs for a small price; and fear Me.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>42</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:42] And do not obscure the truth with falsehood; and do not conceal the truth while you know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:43] And establish prayer, and pay the alms, and bow with those that bow. 'Keep in mind the good manners of presence (ḥa?ra), for the preservation of good manners is the most perfect type of service'. The allusion in giving alms is to the almsgiving of aspirations, just as you fulfill the almsgiving of wealth. The one who spoke for them said:</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>44</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>44</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:44] Will you bid others to piety and forget yourselves, while you recite the Book? Do you not understand?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>45</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>45</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:45] Seek help in patience and prayer. For it is grievous, except to the humble,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>46</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:46] who reckon (yaẓunnūna) that they shall meet their Lord, and that to Him they are returning.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>47</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>47</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:47] O Children of Israel, remember My favor wherewith I favored you, and that I have preferred you above all the worlds;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>48</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:48] and fear the day when no soul for another shall give satisfaction, and no intercession shall be accepted from it; nor any compensation (ʿadl) be taken, neither shall they be helped.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>49</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:49] And when We delivered you from the folk of Pharaoh who were visiting you with evil chastisement, slaughtering your sons, and sparing your women; and for you therein was a tremendous trial from your Lord.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>50</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>50</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:50] When We divided for you the sea, and We delivered you, and drowned Pharaoh's folk, while you were beholding.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>51</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>51</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:51] And when We appointed for Moses forty nights, then you took to yourselves the Calf after him, and you were evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>52</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>52</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:52] Then We pardoned you after that so that you might be thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>53</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:53] And when We gave to Moses the Scripture and the Criterion, so that you might be guided.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>54</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:54] And when Moses said to his people, 'My people you have done wrong against yourselves by your taking the [golden] calf;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:55] And when you said, 'O Moses, we will not believe you till we see God openly'; and the thunderbolt took you, while you were beholding.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>56</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>56</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:56] Then We raised you up after you were dead, so that you might be thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>57</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>57</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:57] And We made the cloud overshadow you; and We sent down upon you manna and quails: 'Eat of the good things We have provided for you'; And they did not wrong Us, but themselves they wronged.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>58</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:58] And when We said, 'Enter this city, and eat freely therein wherever you will, and enter it at the gate prostrating, and say, 'exoneration', and We shall forgive you your transgressions and We shall give more to those who are virtuous'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>59</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>59</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:59] Then the evildoers substituted a saying other than that which had been said to them; so We sent down upon the evildoers wrath from the heaven for their wickedness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:60] And when Moses sought water for his people, We said, 'Strike with your staff the rock,' and there exploded from it twelve fountains, each people came to know their drinking-place, 'Eat and drink of that which God has provided, and do not be degenerate in the earth, seeking corruption'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:61] And when you said, 'Moses, we will not endure one sort of food; pray to your Lord for us, that He may bring forth for us of what the earth produces - green herbs, cucumbers, garlic, lentils, onions'; He said, 'Would you exchange what is better with what is lowlier?' 'Go down to a city, you shall have what you demanded'; And abasement, and wretchedness were cast upon them, and they incurred God's wrath; that was because they used to disbelieve the signs of God and slay prophets without right; that was because they disobeyed, and they were transgressors.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:62] Surely those who believe, and those of Jewry, and the Christians, and the Sabaeans, whoever believes in God and the Last Day, and performs righteous deeds - their wage is with their Lord, and no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>63</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:63-4] And when We made a covenant for you, and We raised above you the Mount, 'Take forcefully what We have given you, and remember what is in it so that you might preserve yourselves'. * Then you turned away thereafter, and but for God's bounty and His mercy towards you, you would have been among the losers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:65] And verily you know that there were those among you who transgressed the Sabbath, and We said to them, 'Be apes, despised!'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>66</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>66</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:66] And We made it an exemplary punishment for all the former times and for the latter, and an admonition to such as who fear.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>67</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>68</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:67] And when Moses said to his people, 'God commands you to sacrifice a cow'...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>69</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>70</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:69-70] '...a golden cow, bright in color, gladdening to beholders'. * They said, 'Pray to your Lord for us, that He make clear to us what she may be; the cows are all alike to us; and if God wills, we shall then be guided'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>71</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:71] He said, 'He says she shall be a cow not broken to plough the earth, or to water the tillage, with no blemish on her'. They said, 'Now you have brought the truth'; and so they sacrificed her, even though they very nearly did not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>72</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>72</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:72] And when you killed a living soul, and disputed thereon - and God disclosed what you were hiding,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>73</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>73</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:73] so We said, 'Smite him with part of it'; God brings to life the dead, and He shows you His signs so that you might understand.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:74] Then your hearts became hardened thereafter, or even yet harder; for there are stones from which rivers come gushing, and others split so that water issues from them; and others come down in fear of God; And God is not heedless of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>75</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>75</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:75] Are you then so eager that they should believe you, seeing there is a party of them that heard God's word, and then tampered with it (yuḥarrifūnahu), and that, after they had comprehended it knowingly?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>76</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>77</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:76-7] And when they meet those who believe, they say, 'We believe'; but when they go in private one to another, they say: 'Do you speak to them of what God has disclosed to you, so that they may thereby dispute with you before your Lord? Have you no understanding?' * Know they not that God knows what they keep secret and what they proclaim?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>78</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:78-9] And there are some of them that are illiterate, not knowing the Scripture, but only desires and mere conjectures. * So woe to those who write the Scripture with their hands then say, 'This is from God' that they may sell it for a small price.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>80</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>80</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:80] And they say, 'the Fire shall not touch us, save a number of days'. Say: 'Have you taken with God a covenant? God will not fail in His covenant, or say you against God what you do not know?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>81</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>81</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:81] Not so; whoever earns evil and is encompassed by his transgression - those are the inhabitants of the Fire, therein abiding (khālidūn).</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>82</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>82</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:82] And those who believe and perform righteous deeds - those are the inhabitants of Paradise, therein abiding.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:85] Then there you are killing one another, and expelling a party of you from their habitations, conspiring against them in sin and enmity, and if they come to you as captives, you ransom them; yet their expulsion was forbidden you. What, do you believe in part of the Book, and disbelieve in part?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>86</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>86</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:86] Those are the ones who have purchased the life of this world at the price of the Hereafter - for them the punishment shall not be lightened, neither shall they be helped.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>87</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>87</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:87] And We gave Moses the Scripture, and after him We sent successive messengers, and We gave Jesus son of Mary the clear proofs, and We confirmed him with the Holy Spirit, and whenever there came to you a messenger, with what your souls did not desire, you became arrogant; and some, you called liars, and some you slay?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>88</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>88</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:88] And they say: 'Our hearts are encased'. Nay, but God has cursed them for their unbelief; and little will they believe.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>89</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>89</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:89] When there came to them a Book from God, confirming what was with them - and they formerly prayed for victory over the disbelievers; but when there came to them what they recognized, they disbelieved in it; and the curse of God is on the disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:90] Evil is that for which they sell their souls; that they disbelieve in that which God has revealed, grudging that God should reveal of His bounty to whomever He will of His servants; and they were laden with anger upon anger; and for the disbelievers there shall be a humiliating chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>91</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>91</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:91] And when it was said to them, 'Believe in what God has revealed', they said, 'We believe in what was revealed to us', and they disbelieve in what is beyond that; yet it is the truth, confirming what is with them. Say: 'Why then were you slaying the prophets of God formerly, if you were believers?'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>92</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>92</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:92] And Moses came to you with clear proofs; then you took to yourselves the calf after him, and you were evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>93</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>93</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:93] And when We made a covenant with you, and raised over you the Mount, 'Take forcefully what We have given you, and listen', they said, 'We hear and disobey'; and they were made to drink the calf in their hearts on account of their unbelief. Say: 'Evil is that which your belief enjoins on you, if you are believers'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>94</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>95</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:94-5] Say: 'If the Abode of the Hereafter with God is purely yours, and not for other people, then long for death - if you speak truly'. * But they will never long for it, because of that which their own hands have sent before them. God knows the evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>96</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>96</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:96] And you shall find them the people most covetous of life, and the idolaters; any one of them would love that he might be given life for a thousand years; yet, his being given life shall not budge him from the chastisement. God sees what they do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>97</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>98</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:97-8] Say: 'Whoever is an enemy to Gabriel - he it was that brought it down upon your heart by the leave of God, confirming what was before it, a guidance, and good tidings for the believers. * Whoever is an enemy to God and His angels and His messengers, and Gabriel and Michael - then surely God is an enemy to the disbelievers'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>99</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:99-100] And We have revealed to you clear proofs; and none disbelieves in them except the wicked. * Why, whenever they make a covenant, does a party of them reject it? Nay, but most of them are disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>101</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>101</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:101] When there came to them a messenger from God, confirming what was with them, a party of them who were given the Scripture have cast away the Scripture of God behind their backs, as though they did not know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:102] And they follow what the devils used to relate Solomon's kingdom: Solomon disbelieved not, but the devils disbelieved, teaching the people sorcery; and that which was revealed to the two angels in Babylon - Hārūt and Mārūt. They taught not any man, without them saying, 'We are but a temptation; do not disbelieve'. From them they learned how they might cause division between a man and his wife, yet they did not hurt any man thereby save by the leave of God; and they learned what hurt them, and did not profit them. And surely they knew well that whoever buys it, he shall have no share in the Hereafter;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>103</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>103</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:103] Yet if only they had believed, and been fearful, verily, a reward from God would have been better, if they had but known.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>104</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>104</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:104] O you who believe, do not say, 'Observe us'; but say, 'Regard us', and give ear; and for disbelievers awaits a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>105</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:105] Those disbelievers of the People of the Scripture and the idolaters, do not wish that any good should be revealed to you from your Lord, but God singles out for His mercy, whom He will; God is of bounty abounding.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>106</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>106</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:106] And whatever verse We abrogate or postpone, We bring [in place] a better, or the like of it; do you not know that God has power over all things?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>107</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>107</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:107] Do you not know that to God belongs the kingdom of the heavens and the earth, and that you have none, besides God, neither protector, nor helper?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>108</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>108</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:108] Or do you desire to question your Messenger as Moses was questioned, aforetime? Whoever exchanges belief for unbelief, has surely strayed from the even way.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>109</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>109</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:109] Many of the People of the Scripture long that they might make you disbelievers, after you have believed, from the envy of their own souls, after the truth has become clear to them; yet pardon and be forgiving till God brings His command; truly God has power over all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>110</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>110</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:110] And perform the prayer, and pay the alms; whatever good you shall offer for your own souls, you shall find it with God; assuredly God sees what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>111</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>111</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:111] And they say, 'None shall enter Paradise except those who are Jews or Christians'. Such are their desires. Say, 'Produce your proof if you speak truly'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>112</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>112</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:112] Nay, but, whoever submits his purpose to God, being virtuous, his reward is with his Lord, and no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>113</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>113</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:113] The Jews say, 'The Christians stand on nothing'; and the Christians say, 'The Jews stand on nothing'; yet they recite the Scripture. Thus, the ignorant say the like of what these say; God shall decide between them on the Day of Resurrection regarding their differences.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>114</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>114</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:114] And who does greater evil than he who bars God's places of worship, so that His Name be not invoked in them, and strives to ruin them?; such men might never enter them, save in fear; for them in this world is degradation; and in the Hereafter a mighty chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>115</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>115</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:115] To God belong the East and the West; whithersoever you turn, there is the Face of God. Lo! God is Embracing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>116</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>116</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:116] And they say, 'God has taken to Himself a son'; Glory be to Him!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>117</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>117</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:117] Creator of the heavens and the earth; and when He decrees a thing, He but says to it 'Be', and it is.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>118</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>118</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:118] And they, who do not know, say, 'Why does God not speak to us?; Why does a sign not come to us?' So, spoke those before them, the like of what they say; their hearts are much alike. Yet We have made clear the signs to a people who are certain.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>119</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>119</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:119] We have sent you with the truth, a bearer of good tidings, and warner. You shall not be asked about the inhabitants of Hell-fire.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>120</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>120</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:120] Never will the Jews be pleased with you, neither the Christians, not until you follow their creed, Say: 'God's guidance is the true guidance'. And if you were to follow their whims, after the knowledge that has come to you, you shall have against God neither friend, nor helper.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>121</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>121</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:121] Those to whom We have given the Scripture, and who recite it with true recitation, they believe in it; and whoever disbelieves in it, they shall be the losers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>122</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>122</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:122] O Children of Israel, remember My favor wherewith I favored you, and that I have preferred you over all the worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>123</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>123</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:123] And beware of a day when no soul shall for another be requited, and no compensation shall be accepted from it, nor any intercession shall benefit it, neither shall they be helped.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>124</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>124</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:124] And when his Lord tested Abraham with certain words, and he fulfilled them,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>125</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>125</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:125] And when We appointed the House to be a place of visitation for the people, and a sanctuary:</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>126</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>126</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:126] And when Abraham said, 'My Lord, make this a land secure and provide its people with fruits; such of them as believe in God and the Last Day', He said, 'And whoever disbelieves, to him I shall give enjoyment, a little, then I shall compel him to the chastisement of the Fire - how evil a journey's end!'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>127</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>127</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:127] And when Abraham raised up the foundations of the House, and Ishmael with him: 'Our Lord! Receive this from us. Truly You are the Hearing, the Knowing. The success of the request is in the sincerity of the supplication. When the two of them humbly sought aid in prayer, he gave them help and fulfilled the request.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>128</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>128</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:128] Our Lord! And make us submissive to You and, of our seed, a community submissive to You; and show us our holy rites, and relent to us. Surely You are the Relenting, the Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>129</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>129</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:129] Our Lord! And send among them a messenger, one of them, who shall recite to them Your signs, and teach them the Book and Wisdom, and purify them; You are the Mighty, the Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>130</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>130</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:130] Who therefore shrinks from the religion of Abraham, except he who fools himself? Indeed We chose him in this world, and in the Hereafter he shall be among the righteous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>131</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>131</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:131] When his Lord said to him, 'Submit', he said, 'I have submitted to the Lord of the Worlds'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>132</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>132</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:132] And Abraham enjoined upon his sons this, and [so did] Jacob, 'My sons, God has chosen for you the [true] religion, see that you die not save in submission.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>133</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>133</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:133] Or, were you witnesses when death came to Jacob? When he said to his sons, 'What will you worship after me?' They said, 'We will worship your God</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>134</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>134</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:134] That is a community that has passed away; theirs is what they have earned, and yours is what you have earned; you shall not be asked about what they did.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>135</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>135</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:135] And they say, 'Be Jews or Christians, and you shall be guided'. Say, 'Nay, rather the creed of Abraham, a ḥanīf; and he was not of the idolaters'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>136</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>136</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:136] Say: 'We believe in God, and in that which has been revealed to us, and revealed to Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac, Jacob, and the Tribes, and that which was given to Moses, and Jesus, and the prophets, from their Lord, we make no division between any of them, and to Him we submit'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>137</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>137</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:137] And if they believe in the like of what you believe in, then they are truly guided; but if they turn away, then they are clearly in schism; God will suffice you against them; He is the Hearer, the Knower.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>138</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>138</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:138] The mark of God; and who has a better mark than God? And Him we worship.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>139</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>139</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:139] Say: 'Would you then dispute with us concerning God, and He is our Lord and your Lord? Our deeds belong to us, and to you belong your deeds, and to Him we are sincerely devoted'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>140</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>140</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:140] Or do you say: 'Abraham, Ishmael, Isaac and Jacob, and the Tribes - they were Jews, or they were Christians?' Say: 'Have you then greater knowledge, or has God? And who does greater injustice than he who conceals a testimony received from God? And God is not heedless of what you do'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>141</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>141</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:141] That is a community that has passed away; theirs is what they have earned, and yours is what you have earned; you shall not be asked about what they did.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>142</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>142</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:142] The fools among the people will say, 'What has turned them from the direction they were facing in their prayers formerly?'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>143</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>143</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:143] Thus, We appointed you a midmost community that you might be witnesses to the people; and that the Messenger might be a witness to you,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>144</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>144</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:144] We have indeed seen you turning your face about in the heaven; now We will surely turn you to a direction (qibla) that shall satisfy you. Turn your face towards the Sacred Mosque, and wherever you are turn your faces towards it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>145</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>145</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:145] Yet if you should bring to those who have been given the Scripture every sign, they will not follow your direction, and you are not a follower of their direction; neither are they followers of one another's direction. If you were to follow their whims after the knowledge that has come to you, then you will surely be among the evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>146</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>146</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:146] Those to whom We have given the Scripture, they recognize him, as they recognize their sons; even though there is a party of them that conceal the truth, while they know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>147</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>147</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:147] The truth comes from your Lord; then be not among the doubters.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>148</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>148</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:148] Every person has his direction to which he turns, so vie with one another in good works. Wherever you may be, God will bring you all together; surely God has power over all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>149</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>149</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:149] From whatever place you issue, turn your face towards the Sacred Mosque; it is the truth from your Lord. God is not heedless of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>150</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>150</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:150] From whatever place you issue, turn your face towards the Sacred Mosque; and wherever you may be, turn your faces towards it, so that there be not any argument from the people against you; excepting the evildoers among them;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>151</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>151</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:151] As also We have sent among you, of yourselves, a messenger, to recite Our verses to you and to purify you, and to teach you the Book, and wisdom, and to teach you what you knew not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>152</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>152</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:152] So remember Me, I will remember you; and be thankful to Me, and be not ungrateful towards Me.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>153</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>153</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:153] O you who believe, seek help through patience and prayer; surely God is with the patient.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>154</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>154</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:154] And say not of those slain in God's way: 'They are dead'; rather they are living; but you are not aware.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>155</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>156</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:155-6] Surely We will try you with something of fear and hunger, and diminution of goods and lives and fruits; yet give good tidings to the patient; * those who, when they are struck by an affliction, say, 'Surely we belong to God, and to Him we will return'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>157</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>157</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:157] Upon those rest blessings and mercy from their Lord, and those - they are the truly guided.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>158</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>158</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:158] Truly Ṣafā and Marwa are among the waymarks of God,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>159</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>159</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:159] Those who conceal the clear proofs and the guidance that We have revealed after We have shown them clearly in the Scripture - they shall be cursed by God and by the cursers,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>160</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>160</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:160] Except those that repent, and make amends, and show clearly - them I shall turn [relenting]; I am the Relenting, the Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>161</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>162</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:161-2] But those who disbelieve, and die disbelieving - upon them shall be the curse of God and the angels, and of people altogether. * Abiding therein: the chastisement shall not be lightened for them, no respite shall be given them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>163</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>163</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:163] Your God is One God; there is no god except Him, the Compassionate, the Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>164</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>164</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:164] Surely in the creation of the heavens and the earth, and the alternation of the night and day, and the ships that run in the sea with what profits men, and the water, God sends down from the heaven with which He revives the earth after it is dead, and He scatters abroad in it all manner of crawling thing; and the disposition of the winds, and the clouds compelled between heaven and the earth - surely there are signs for a people who comprehend.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>165</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>165</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:165] Yet there be people who take to themselves compeers besides God, loving them as God is loved;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>166</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>166</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:166] When those who were followed disown their followers, and they have seen the chastisement, and the cords are cut away before them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>167</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>167</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:167] And those who followed say, 'O, if only we might return again and disown them, as they have disowned us!' So, God shall show them their works, anguish for them! Never shall they exit from the Fire.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>168</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>168</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:168] O people, eat of what is in the earth, lawful and wholesome; and follow not the steps of Satan; he is a manifest foe to you;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>169</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>169</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:169] he only commands you to evil and indecency, and that you should speak against God what you do not know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>170</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>170</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:170] And when it is said to them, 'Follow what God has revealed', they say, 'No; but we follow what we found our fathers doing'. What? Even if their fathers do not understand anything, and they were not guided?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>171</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>171</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:171] The likeness of those who disbelieve is as the likeness of one who shouts to that which hears nothing, save a call and a cry; deaf, dumb, blind - they do not comprehend.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>172</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>172</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:172] O you who believe, eat of the good things (?ayyibāt) wherewith We have provided you, and give thanks to God if it be Him that you worship.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>173</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>173</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:173] He has only forbidden you: carrion, blood, the flesh of swine; what has been hallowed to other than God. Yet whoever is constrained, not desiring, nor transgressing, no sin shall be on him. God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>174</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>174</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:174] Those who conceal what God has revealed of the Scripture, and sell it for a little price - they shall consume nothing in their bellies but the Fire; God shall not speak to them on the Day of Resurrection, neither purify them; and theirs is a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>175</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>176</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:175-6] Those are they that have bought error at the price of guidance, and chastisement at the price of pardon; what makes them so patient for the Fire? * That is because God has revealed the Book with the truth; and those that are at variance regarding the Book are in schism, far removed.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>177</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>177</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:177] It is not piety, that you turn your faces to the East and to the West. True piety is [that of] the one who believes in God and the Last Day and the angels and the Book and the prophets, and who gives of his substance, however cherished to kinsmen and orphans and the needy and the traveller and beggars, and for slaves, and who observes prayer and pays the alms, and those who fulfill their covenant when they have engaged in a covenant, those who endure with fortitude misfortune, hardship, and peril are the ones who are truthful, and these are the ones who are fearful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>178</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>178</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:178] O you who believe, prescribed for you is retaliation, regarding the slain; a free man, for a free man, and a slave for a slave, and a female for a female. But if anything is pardoned any one in relation to his brother, let the pursuing be honorable. And let the payment to him be with kindliness; that is an alleviation given by your Lord, and a mercy; and for him who commits aggression after that - his is a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>179</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>179</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:179] In retaliation there is life for you, O people of pith, so that you might fear.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>180</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>180</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:180] Prescribed for you, when any of you is approached by death and leaves behind some good, is to make testament in favor of his parents and kinsmen honorably - an obligation on those that fear.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>181</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>181</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:181] Then if anyone changes it after hearing it, the sin shall rest upon those who change it; surely God is Hearing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>182</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>182</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:182] But if any one fears injustice or sin from one making testament, and so makes things right between them, then no sin shall be upon him; surely God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>183</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>183</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:183] O you who believe, prescribed for you is the Fast, just as it was prescribed for those that were before you so that you might guard yourselves.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>184</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>184</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:184] For days numbered; and if any of you be sick, or be on a journey, then a number of other days;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>185</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>185</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:185] The month of Rama?ān, wherein the QurÌān was revealed, a guidance for the people, and as clear proofs of the Guidance and the Criterion; So let those of you, who are present at the month, fast it and if any of you be sick, or if he be on a journey, then a number of other days.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>186</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>186</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:186] And when My servants question you concerning Me, I am near; I answer the call of the caller when he calls to Me; so let them respond to Me, and let them believe in Me that they might go aright.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>187</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>187</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:187] Permitted to you, upon the night of the Fast, is to go in to your wives; they are a vestment for you, and you are a vestment for them; God knows that you have been betraying yourselves, and so He has turned to you [relenting], and He has pardoned you. So now, lie with them and seek what God has prescribed for you, and eat and drink until the white thread is distinct to you from the black thread at daybreak; then complete the fast to the night;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>188</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>188</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:188] Consume not your goods between you in deception, and proffer them to the judges, that you may consume a portion of other people's goods in sin while you are aware.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>189</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>189</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:189] They will ask you about the new moons. Say, 'They are appointed times for the people and the Pilgrimage'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>190</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>190</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:190] And fight in the way of God with those who fight against you, but aggress not; God loves not the aggressors.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>191</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>191</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:191] And slay them wherever you come upon them,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>192</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>192</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:192] But if they desist, surely God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>193</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>193</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:193] Fight them till there is no sedition, and the religion is for God; then if they desist, there shall be no enmity, save against evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>194</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>194</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:194] The sacred month for the sacred month; holy things demand retaliation; whoever commits aggression against you, then commit aggression against him in the manner that he committed against you; and fear God, and know that God is with the God-fearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>195</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>195</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:195] And spend in the way of God; and cast not your own hands into destruction; but be virtuous; God loves the virtuous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>196</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>196</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:196] Fulfill the Pilgrimage and the Visitation to God;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>197</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>197</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:197] The Pilgrimage is in months well-known;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>198</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>198</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:198] You would not be at fault if you should seek bounty from your Lord;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>199</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>199</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:199] Then press on from where the people press on, and seek God's forgiveness; God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>200</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>200</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:200] And when you have performed your holy rites, remember God as you remember your fathers, or yet more intensely.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>201</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>201</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:201] And there are others who say, 'Our Lord, give to us in this world good, and good in the Hereafter, and guard us against the chastisement of the Fire'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>202</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>202</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:202] Those - they shall have a portion from what they have earned;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>203</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>203</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:203] And remember God, during certain days numbered. If any man hastens on in two days, that is no sin for him; and if he delays, it is not a sin for him; if he fears; and fear God, and know that to Him you shall be gathered.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>204</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>204</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:204] And among people there is he whose speech in the life of this world pleases you; and who calls on God to witness what is in his heart; yet he is most stubborn in dispute.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>205</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>205</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:205] And when he turns his back, he hastens about the earth to do corruption there and to destroy the tillage and the stock; and God loves not corruption.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>206</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>206</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:206] And when it is said to him, 'Fear God', he is seized by vainglory in his sin. So Hell shall be enough for him - how evil a cradling!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>207</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>207</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:207] But there are other men who sell themselves, desiring God's pleasure; and God is Gentle with His servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>208</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>208</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:208] O you who believe, come, all of you, into submission; and follow not the steps of Satan; he is a manifest foe to you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>209</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>209</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:209] But if you slip after the clear proofs have come to you, know then that God is Mighty, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>210</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>210</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:210] What do they wait for that God shall come to them in the shadows of clouds, and the angels? The matter is determined, and to God all matters are returned.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>211</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>211</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:211] Ask the Children of Israel how many a clear proof did We give them; whoever changes God's grace after it has come to him, God is severe in retribution.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>212</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>212</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:212] Decked out fair to the disbelievers is the life of this world; and they deride the believers; but those who fear shall be above them on the Day of Resurrection; and God sustains whomever He will without reckoning.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>213</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>213</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:213] People were one community; then God sent forth the prophets as bearers of good tidings and warners; and He revealed with them the Scripture with the truth that He might decide between people regarding their differences; and only those who had been given it, differed about it after the clear proofs had come to them out of insolence, one to another; then God guided those who believed to the truth, regarding which they were at variance, by His leave; and God guides whomever He will to a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>214</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>214</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:214] Or did you suppose that you should enter Paradise without there having come upon you the like of those who passed away before you? They were afflicted by misery and hardship and were so convulsed that the Messenger and those who believed with him said, 'When will God's help come?' Ah, but surely God's help is nigh.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>215</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>215</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:215] They will ask you about what they should expend. Say, 'Whatever you expend of good it is for parents and kinsmen, orphans, the needy, and the traveler; and whatever good you may do, God has knowledge of it'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>216</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>216</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:216] Prescribed for you is fighting, though it be hateful to you. Yet it may happen that you hate a thing which is good for you; and it may happen that you love a thing which is bad for you; God knows, and you know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>217</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>217</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:217] They ask you about the sacred month, and fighting in it. Say, 'Fighting in it is a grave thing; but to bar from God's way, and disbelief in Him, and the Sacred Mosque, and to expel its people from it - that is graver in God's sight; and sedition</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>218</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>218</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:218] Verily the believers, and those who emigrate, and struggle in God's way - those have hope of God's compassion; and God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>219</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>220</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:219] They ask you about wine (khamr), and divinatory arrows. Say: 'In both is great sin and profit for men; but the sin in them is greater than the usefulness'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>221</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>221</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:221] Do not marry idolatresses until they believe; a believing slavegirl is better than an idolatress, though you may admire her. And do not marry idolaters, until they believe. A believing slave is better than an idolater, though you may admire him. Those call to the Fire; and God calls to Paradise and pardon by His leave; and He makes clear His signs to the people so that they might remember.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>222</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>222</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:222] They will ask you about the monthly period. Say: 'It is an ailment; so part with women in the monthly period, and do not approach them until they are pure; when they have cleansed themselves, then come to them, as God has commanded you'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>223</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>223</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:223] Your women are a tillage for you; so come to your tillage as you wish; and offer for your souls; and fear God; and know that you shall meet Him; and give good tidings to the believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>224</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>224</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:224] Do not make God a hindrance in your oaths, to be pious and Godfearing; and to put things right between people; surely God is All-Hearing, Knower.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>225</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>225</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:225] God will not take you to task for a slip in your oaths; but He will take you to task for what your hearts have earned; and God is Forgiving, Forbearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>226</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>226</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:226] For those who forswear their women, a wait of four months; if they revert, God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>227</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>227</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:227] But if they resolve upon divorce; surely God is Hearing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>228</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>228</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:228] Divorced women shall wait by themselves for three periods.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>229</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>229</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:229] Divorce is twice;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>230</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>230</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:230] If he divorces her, she shall not be lawful to him after that, until she marries another husband. If he divorces her, then neither of them would be at fault to return to each other,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>231</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>231</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:231] When you divorce women, and they have reached their term, then retain them honorably, or set them free honorably; do not retain them in harm to transgress; whoever does that has wronged his soul; take not God's verses in mockery, and remember God's grace upon you, and the Book, and the wisdom He has revealed to you, to exhort you therewith; and fear God, and know that God has knowledge of all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>232</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>232</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:232] When you divorce women, and they have reached their term, do not debar them from marrying their husbands when they have agreed together honorably. That is an admonition for whoever of you believe in God and the Last Day; that is purer for you, and cleaner. God knows, and you know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>233</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>233</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:233] Mothers suckle their children for two full years for such as desire to fulfill the suckling.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>234</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>234</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:234] And those of you who pass away, leaving wives, they shall wait by themselves for four months and ten. When they have reached their term, then you would not be at fault regarding what they may do with themselves, honorably; God is aware of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>235</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>235</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:235] You would not be at fault regarding the proposal you present or hide in your hearts to women. God knows that you will be mindful of them; but do not make arrangements with them secretly, unless you speak honorable words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>236</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>236</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:236] You would not be at fault if you divorce women while you have not touched them, nor appointed any obligation for them; yet make provision of comforts for them honorably, the one of ample means, according to his means, and the needy man, according to his means - an obligation on the virtuous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>237</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>237</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:237] And if you divorce them before you have touched them, and you have already appointed for them an obligation, then one-half of what you have appointed, unless it be that they make remission, or he makes remission, the one in whose hand is the knot of marriage; yet that you should remit is nearer to piety.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>238</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>238</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:238] Maintain (ḥāfiẓū) the prayers and the middle prayer, and stand submissive to God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>239</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>239</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:239] And if you are in fear, then standing, or mounted. But when you are secure, then remember God, as He taught you what you knew not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>240</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>240</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:240] And those of you who die, leaving wives, make testament for their wives, provision for a year; but if they go forth, you would not be at fault regarding what they may do with themselves honorably; God is Mighty, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>241</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>241</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:241] There shall be provision for divorced women, honorably - an obligation on those who fear.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>242</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>242</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:242] So, God makes clear His signs for you, so that you might understand.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>243</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>243</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:243] Have you not seen those thousands, who went forth from their habitations fearful of death? God said to them, 'Die!' Then He gave them life. Truly God is bounteous to people, but most people are not thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>244</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>244</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:244] So fight in God's way, and know that God is Hearing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>245</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>245</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:245] Who is he that will lend God a loan that is good, and He will multiply it for him manifold?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>246</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>246</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:246] Have you not seen the council of the Children of Israel after Moses, when they said to a prophet of theirs, 'Send for us a king, and we will fight in God's way'. He said, 'Might it be that if fighting is prescribed for you, you will not fight?'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>247</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>247</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:247] Then their prophet said to them, 'Verily God has raised up Saul for you as king'. They said, 'How can he be king over us when we have better right than he to kingship, seeing he has not been given amplitude of wealth?' He said, 'God has chosen him over you and has increased him broadly in knowledge and body (jism). God gives the kingship to whom He will; and God is Embracing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>248</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>248</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:248] And their prophet said to them, 'The sign of his kingship is that there will come to you the Ark. Therein is a Spirit of Peace from your Lord, and a remnant of what the folk of Moses and the folk of Aaron left behind, the angels bearing it. Surely in that shall be a sign for you if you are believers'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>249</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>249</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:249] And when Saul went forth with the hosts, he said, 'God will try you with a river; whoever drinks of it, is not of me, and whoever tastes it not, he is of me, except for him who scoops up with his hand.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>250</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>250</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:250] So, when they went forth against Goliath and his troops, they said, 'Our Lord, pour out upon us patience, and make firm our feet, and grant us victory over the disbelieving folk!'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>251</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>251</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:251] And they routed them, by the leave of God, and David slew Goliath; and God gave him the kingship and Wisdom, and He taught him such as He willed.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>252</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>252</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:252] These are the verses of God We recite to you in truth, and assuredly you are one of the Messengers [of God].</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>253</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>253</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:253] Those messengers some We have preferred above others; some there are to whom God spoke, and some He raised in rank. And We gave Jesus son of Mary the clear proofs, and confirmed him with the Holy Spirit.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>254</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>254</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:254] O you who believe, expend of what We have provided you with before there comes a day in which there shall be neither commerce, nor friendship, nor intercession. And the disbelievers - they are the evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>255</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>255</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:255] God, there is no god, except Him, the Living, the Eternal Sustainer.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>256</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>256</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:256] There is no compulsion in religion.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>257</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>257</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:257] God is the Protector (walī) of the believers;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>258</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>258</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:258] Have you not seen him who disputed with Abraham concerning his Lord, that God had given him the kingship? When Abraham said, 'My Lord is He who gives life, and makes to die', he said, 'I give life and make to die'. Abraham said: 'God brings the sun from the east; so bring it from the west.' Then the disbeliever was confused; and God guides not the folk who do evil.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>259</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>259</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:259] Or such as he who passed by a city that was fallen down upon its turrets, he said, 'How shall God give life to this now that it is dead?'. So God made him die a hundred years, then he raised him up; He, said, 'How long have you tarried?'; he said, 'I have tarried a day, or part of a day'; He said, 'Nay; you have tarried a hundred years. Look at your food and drink, it has not spoiled; and look at your ass so that We would make you a sign for the people. And look at the bones, how We shall set them up, and then clothe them with flesh'. So, when it was made clear to him, he said, 'I know that God has power over all things'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>260</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>260</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:260] And when Abraham said, 'My Lord show me how You give life to the dead'. He said, 'Why, do you not believe?' 'Yes', he said, 'but so that my heart may be re-assured'. Said He, 'Take four birds, and twist them to you, then set a part of them on every hill, then summon them, and they will come to you in haste. And know that God is Mighty, Wise'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>261</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>261</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:261] The likeness of those who expend their wealth in the way of God is as the likeness of a grain of corn that sprouts seven ears, in every ear a hundred grains; so God multiplies for whom He will; God is Embracing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>262</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>262</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:262] Those who expend their wealth in the way of God then do not follow up their expenditure with reminder of their generosity and injury, their wage is with their Lord, and no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>263</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>263</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:263] Honorable words and forgiveness are better than a voluntary almsgiving followed by injury; and God is Independent, Forbearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>264</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>264</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:264] O you who believe, annul not your voluntary almsgivings with reproach and injury, as one who expends of his substance to show off to men and believes not in God and the Last Day. The likeness of him is as the likeness of a smooth rock on which is soil, and a torrent smites it, and leaves it barren. They have no power over anything that they have earned. God guides not the disbelieving folk.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>265</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>266</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:265-266] But the likeness of those who expend their wealth, seeking God's good pleasure, and to confirm themselves is as the likeness of a garden upon a hill; a torrent smites it and it yields its produce twofold; if no torrent smites it, then dew, and God sees what you do. * Would any of you wish to have a garden of date-palms and vines, with rivers flowing beneath it, for him there is in it all manner of fruit, then old age smites him, and he has seed, but they are weak; then a whirlwind with fire smites it, and it is consumed. So, God makes clear the signs to you, so that you might reflect.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>267</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>267</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:267] O you who believe, expend of the good things you have earned, and of what We have produced for you from the earth, and seek not the corrupt of it for your expending; for you would never take it yourselves without closing your eyes to it; and know that God is Independent, Laudable.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>268</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>268</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:268] Satan promises you poverty and enjoins you to indecency, but God promises you His pardon, and His bounty; and God is Embracing, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>269</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>269</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:269] He gives wisdom to whomever He will, and he who is given wisdom, has been given much good; yet none remembers, but the people of pith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>270</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>270</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:270] And whatever expenditure you expend, and whatever vow you make, surely God knows it. For the evildoers, they have no helpers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>271</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>271</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:271] If you proclaim your voluntary almsgivings, it is a fine thing; but if you conceal them, and give them to the poor, that is even better for you; and it will absolve you of your evil deeds. God is aware of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>272</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>272</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:272] You are not responsible for guiding them; but God guides whomever He will. And whatever good you expend is for yourselves; for then you are expending, desiring only God's Face, and whatever good you expend, shall be repaid to you in full, and you will not be wronged.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>273</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>273</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:273] For the poor (fuqarāÌ), who are constrained in the way of God; and they are unable to journey in the land; the ignorant man supposes them rich because of their abstinence; but you shall know them by their mark; they do not beg of men importunately. And whatever good you expend, surely God has knowledge of it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>274</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>274</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:274] Those who expend their wealth night and day, secretly and openly, their wage awaits them with their Lord, and no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>275</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>275</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:275] Those who devour usury shall not rise again, except as one whom Satan has made prostrate from touch; that is because they say, 'Trade is like usury': God has permitted trade, and forbidden usury. Whoever receives an admonition from his Lord and desists, he shall have his past gains, and his affair is committed to God; but whoever reverts - those are the inhabitants of the Fire, abiding therein.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>276</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>276</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:276] God effaces usury, but He augments voluntary almsgivings with interest. God loves not any guilty ingrate.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>277</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>277</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:277] Those who believe and perform righteous deeds, and establish the prayer, and pay the alms - their wage awaits them with their Lord, and no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>278</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>278</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:278] O you who believe, fear God, and give up the usury that is outstanding, if you are believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>279</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>279</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:279] But if you do not, then be warned of war from God, and His Messenger. Yet if you repent, you shall have your principal sums, not being unjust, and no injustice being done to you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>280</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>280</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:280] And if any man should be in difficulties, then respite, till things are easier; but that you should give a voluntary almsgiving is better for you, did you but know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>281</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>281</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:281] And fear a day wherein you shall be returned to God, and every soul shall be paid in full what it has earned; and they shall not be wronged.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>282</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>283</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:282-283] O you who believe, when you contract a debt, one upon another for a stated term, write it down; and let a writer write it down between you justly; and let not any writer refuse to write it down, as God has taught him; so let him write, and let the debtor dictate; and let him fear God his Lord, and not diminish anything of it. And if the debtor be a fool, or weak, or unable to dictate himself, then let his guardian dictate justly. And summon to bear witness, two witnesses, men; or if the two be not men, then one man and two women, such witnesses as you approve of, so that if one of the two women errs; the other will remind her; and let the witnesses not refuse, whenever they are summoned; and be not disdainful to write it down, small or great, with its term; that is more equitable in God's sight, more upright for testimony, and nearer, that you will not be in doubt, unless it be trade carried out there and then that you give and take between you, then you will not be at fault if you do not write it down. And take witnesses when you are trading with one another. And let not either writer or witness be pressed; and if you do, that is sinfulness in you. And fear God. God teaches you and God knows all things. * And if you are upon a journey, and you do not find a writer, then a pledge in hand. But if one of you trusts another, let him who is trusted, deliver his trust, and let him fear God his Lord. And do not conceal the testimony; whoever conceals it, his heart is sinful; and God knows what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>284</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>284</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:284] To God belongs all that is in the heavens and the earth. Whether you disclose what is in your hearts or hide it, God shall take you to account for it. Then He will forgive whom He wishes, and chastise whom He wishes. And God has power over all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>285</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>285</lastVerse>
      <text>[2:285] The Messenger believes in what was revealed to him from his Lord, and the believers; each one believes in God and His angels, and in His Books, and His messengers, 'we make no distinction between any of His messengers'. And they say, 'We hear and obey; Your forgiveness, our Lord; to You is the homecoming'.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="3">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>3:1 Alif Lām Mīm</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:2] God! There is no god except Him, the Living, the Eternal.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:3] He has revealed to you the Book, by the truth</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:5] Nothing whatever is hidden in heaven and earth from God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:6] He it is Who forms you in the wombs as He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:7] He it is Who revealed to you the Book, wherein are verses [that are] clear, forming the Mother Book, and others allegorical. As for those in whose hearts is deviation, they follow the allegorical part, desiring sedition, and desiring its interpretation, and none knows its interpretation, save God. And for those firmly rooted in knowledge (al-rāsikhūn fī'l-ʿilm), say, 'We believe in it; all is from our Lord'; yet none remembers [yatadhakkaru], but people of pith.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:8] Our Lord, do not cause our hearts to deviate after You have guided us; and give us mercy from You; You are the Bestower.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:9] Our Lord, You shall gather mankind for a day of which there is no doubt; verily God will not fail the tryst.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:10] As for the disbelievers, neither their riches nor their children will avail them against God; those - they shall be fuel for the Fire.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:11] As the way of Pharoah's folk, and the people before them, who denied Our signs; God seized them for their sins; God is severe in retribution.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:12] Say to the disbelievers: 'You shall be vanquished and mustered to Hell - an evil cradling!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:13] There has already been a sign for you in two hosts that met; one company fighting in the way of God; and another unbelieving; they saw them, twice the like of them; for God confirms with His help whom He will. Surely in that is a lesson for people of vision.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:14] Beautified for mankind is love of lusts - of women, children, stored-up heaps of gold and silver, horses of mark, cattle, and tillage. That is the comfort of the life of this world; but God - with Him is the more excellent abode.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:15] Say: 'Shall I tell you of something better than that? For those that are fearful with their Lord are Gardens underneath which rivers flow, abiding therein, and spouses purified, and beatitude from God; and God is Seer, of His servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>16</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>16</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:16] Those who say: "O, Our Lord, we believe; so forgive us our sins, and guard us from the chastisement of the Fire",</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:17] the patient, sincere, obedient, expenders, imploring God's pardon at daybreak'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:18] God bears witness that there is no god, except Him,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:19] Lo, the religion (dīn) with God is submission (islām) (to the One God).</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:20] So if they dispute with you, say: 'I have surrendered my countenance to God and whoever follows me': and say to those who have been given the Scripture, and to the uninstructed: 'Have you submitted?' And so if they have submitted, they have been guided, but if they turn their backs, your duty is only to deliver; and God sees His servants.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:21] Those who disbelieve in the signs of God and slay the prophets without right, and slay those who enjoin to equity. So give them good tidings of a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:22] Those are the ones whose works have failed in this world and the Hereafter; they have no helpers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:23] Have you not seen those who were given a portion of the Book, being called to the Book of God, that it might decide between them, and then a party of them turned away (yatawallā), opposed?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:24] That, because they said, 'the Fire shall not touch us, except for a number of days'; and the lies they used to invent have deluded them in their religion.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:25] But how will it be when We gather them for a day of which there is no doubt, and every soul shall be paid in full what it has earned, and they shall not be wronged?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:26] Say: 'O God (Allāhumma), Master of the Kingdom,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>27</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>27</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:27] You make the night pass into the day and You make the day to pass into the night; You bring forth the living from the dead, and You bring forth the dead from the living, You provide whom You will without reckoning'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>28</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:28] Let not the believers take the disbelievers as patrons, rather than the believers -</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>29</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:29] Say: 'Whether you hide what is in your breasts, or disclose it, God knows it and knows what is in the heavens and what is in the earth; and God is Able to do all things.'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>30</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:30] The day every soul shall find what it has done of good present before it, and what it has done of evil, it will wish that between it and that there were a great distance.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:31] Say: 'If you love God, follow me, and God will love you, and forgive you your sins; God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:32] Say: 'Obey God, and the Messenger'. But if they turn their backs, God loves not the disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:33-34] Lo! God preferred Adam and Noah and the House of Abraham and the House of ʿImrān above the worlds, * the seed of one another; God is Hearer, Knower.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>36</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:35-36] When the wife of ʿImrān said, 'Lord, I have vowed to You what is within my womb as a consecration. Accept this from me. Lo! It is You Who are the Hearer, Knower. * And when she gave birth to her, she said, 'Lord, I have given birth to a female' - and God knew very well what she had given birth to the male is not as the female. 'And I have named her Mary, and commend her to You with her seed to protect them from the accursed Satan'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>37</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:37] Her Lord accepted the child with gracious acceptance, and made her grow excellently, and Zachariah took charge of her.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>38</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>38</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:38] Then Zachariah prayed to his Lord, saying, 'Lord, bestow upon me from You a goodly offspring, verily You are the Hearer of supplication'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:39] And the angels called to him as he stood praying in the sanctuary at worship</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:40] He said, 'My Lord! How shall I have a boy when old age has overtaken me, and my wife is barren?' He said, 'So it will be'. 'God does what He will'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>41</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:41] He said, 'My Lord! Appoint for me a sign'. He said, 'Your sign is that you shall not speak to men, save by tokens for three days.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>42</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:42] And when the angels said, 'O Mary, God has preferred you, and made you pure; He has preferred you above all women of the worlds.'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:43] 'O Mary, be obedient to your Lord, prostrating and bowing with those who bow'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>44</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>44</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:44] That is of the tidings of the Unseen. We reveal it to you for you were not with them, when they were casting quills, which of them should have charge of Mary; nor were you with them, when they were disputing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>45</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:45-46] When the angels said, 'O Mary, God gives you good tidings of a Word from Him, whose name is the Messiah, Jesus, son of Mary, honored shall he be in this world, and the Hereafter, and of those brought close. * He shall speak to mankind in the cradle, and in his manhood, and he is of the righteous.'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>47</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>47</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:47] She said, 'Lord, how shall I have a child when no mortal has touched me?' He said, 'It is such. God creates what He will.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>49</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:48-9] And He will teach him the Book, wisdom, and the Torah, and the Gospel. * To be a messenger to the Children of Israel, 'I have come to you with a sign from your Lord, I will create for you out of clay like the shape of a bird then I will breathe into it, and it will be a bird by the leave of God. I will also heal the blind and the leper; and I bring to life the dead, by the leave of God. I will inform you too of what things you eat, and what you treasure up in your houses. Surely in that is a sign for you, if you are believers.' (3:48-9)</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>52</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>52</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:52] And when Jesus sensed their disbelief, he said, 'Who will be my helpers unto God?' The disciples said, 'We will be helpers of God; we believe in God; witness that we have submitted.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>54</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:53] Lord, we believe in what You have revealed, and we follow the Messenger; inscribe us therefore with those who bear witness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>55</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:55] When God said, 'O Jesus, I am gathering you'...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>58</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:58] This We recite to you of verses and wise remembrance.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>59</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>59</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:59] Truly the likeness of Jesus in God's sight, is as Adam's likeness"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:60] The truth is from your Lord"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:61] And whoever disputes with you concerning him"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:62] This is the true story...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>63</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>63</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:63] And if they turn their backs, God knows the agents of corruption.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>64</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:64] 'O People of the Scripture! Come now to a word agreed upon between us and you,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:65] 'O People of the Scripture Why do you argue about Abraham'"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>66</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>66</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:66] Lo! You are those who dispute about what you know; why do you then dispute concerning that of which you have no knowledge?; and God knows, and you know not.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>67</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>67</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:67] No; Abraham in truth was not a Jew, neither a Christian, but he was a Muslim and a ḥanīf...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>68</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>68</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:68] Surely the people with the best claim, Abraham, are those who followed him, and this Prophet, and those who believe; and God is the Protector of the believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>69</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>69</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:69] There is a party of the People of the Scripture who yearn to make you go astray; yet they cause none to stray, except themselves...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>70</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>70</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:70] O People of the Scripture! Why do you disbelieve in God's verses, when you yourselves bear witness?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>71</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:71] O People of the Scripture! Why do you confound truth with falsehood, and conceal the truth while you know?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>72</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>72</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:72] A party of the People of Scripture say, 'Believe in what has been revealed to those who believe at the beginning of the day, and disbelieve at the end of it, so that they might then turn back.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>73</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>73</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:73] And do not believe except in one who follows your religion'...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:74] He singles out for His mercy whom He will; God is of bounty abounding'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>75</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>75</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:75] And of the People of the Scriptures is he who, if you trust him with a hundredweight, he will return it to you; and of them is he who, if you trust him with one dinar, will not return it to you"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>76</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>76</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:76] Nay, but whoever fulfils his covenant, and has fear...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>77</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>77</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:77] Those that sell God's covenant and their own oaths for a small price, there shall be no share for them in the Hereafter; and God shall not speak to them, nor look upon them on the Day of Resurrection, nor will He purify them and theirs will be a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>78</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>78</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:78] And there is a group of them who twist their tongues with the Book, so that you may suppose it as part of the Book; yet it is not part of the Book; and they say, 'It is from God', yet it is not from God, and they speak falsehood against God, while they know.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>79</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:79] It belongs not to any mortal that God should given him the Book, the Judgment, prophethood, then that he should say to men, 'Be servants to me instead of God'. Rather, 'Be masters, by virtue of what you know of the Book and in what you study'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>80</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>80</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:80] He would never order you to take the angels and the prophets as lords. Would He order you to disbelieve, after you have submitted?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>81</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>81</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:81] And when God made a covenant with the prophets"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>82</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>82</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:82] Then whoever turns his back after that, they are the wicked.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>83</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:83] What! Do they desire other than God's religion, when to Him has submitted, whoever is in the heavens and the earth, willing, or unwillingly"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>84</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>84</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:84] Say: 'We believe in God, and that which has been revealed to us, and that which has been revealed to Abraham and Ismael, and Isaac and Jacob, and the Tribes; and in that which was given to Moses and Jesus, and the prophets, from their Lord; we make no division between any of them; and to Him we submit'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:85] Whoever desires a religion other than Islam, it shall not be accepted from him and in the Hereafter he shall be among the losers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>86</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>86</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:86] How shall God guide a people who have disbelieved after their belief, and bore witness that the Messenger is true"</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>87</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>87</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:87] Those - their requital is that there shall rest on them the curse of God and of the angels and of men altogether.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>88</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>88</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:88] Abiding therein, the chastisement shall not be lightened for them and they shall not be reprieved.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>89</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>89</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:89] But those who repent thereafter, and make amends, then truly God is forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>90</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:90] Surely those who disbelieve after they have believed, and then increase in unbelief, their repentance shall not be accepted; those are the ones who go astray.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>91</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>91</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:91] Surely those who disbelieve, and die disbelieving, the whole earth full of gold shall not be accepted from any one of them if he would ransom himself thereby; for them awaits a painful chastisement, and they shall have no helpers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>92</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>92</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:92] You will not attain piety (birr) until you expend of what you love; and whatever thing you expend, God knows of it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>93</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>94</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:93-94] All food was lawful to the Children of Israel save what Israel forbade for himself before the Torah was revealed. Say: 'Bring the Torah now, and recite it, if you are truthful'. * Whoever invents falsehood against God after that, those are the evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>95</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>95</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:95] Say: 'God has spoken the truth, therefore follow the creed of Abraham, a ḥanīf, and he was not an idolater'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>96</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>97</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:96-97] The first house established for the people was that at Bakka, a blessed place, and a guidance to all worlds. * Therein are clear signs, the station of Abraham; and whoever enters it is in security. It is the duty of people towards God to make the pilgrimage to the House, if he is able to make his way there. As for the one who disbelieves, God is Independent of all worlds.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>98</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>98</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:98] Say: 'O People of the Scripture, why do you disbelieve in God's verses, when God is Witness of what you do?'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>99</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>99</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:99] Say: 'O People of the Scripture, why do you bar believers from God's way, desiring to make it crooked, while you yourselves are witnesses. God is not heedless of what you do'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>100</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:100] O you who believe, if you obey a party of those who have been given the Scripture, they will turn you, after you have believed, into disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>101</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>101</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:101] How can you disbelieve while you have God's verses recited to you, and His Messenger is in your midst? Whoever holds fast to God, he is guided to a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:102] O you who believe, fear God as He should be feared (ḥaqqa tuqātihi)</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>103</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>103</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:103] And hold fast to God's bond, together, and do not scatter; remember God's grace upon you when you were enemies, and He brought your hearts together so that by His grace you became brothers; and you were upon the brink of a pit of fire; but He delivered you from it. So God makes clear to you His signs that you might be guided.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>104</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>104</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:104] Let there be one community of you calling to good, and enjoining decency, and forbidding indecency; those are the successful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>105</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:105] Be not as those who scattered and disputed after the clear proofs came to them, those there awaits a mighty chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>106</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>107</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:106-107] The day when some faces are blackened, and some faces whitened. As for those whose faces are blackened, 'Did you disbelieve after you had believed? Then taste the chastisement for what you disbelieved!' * But for those whose faces are whitened, they shall be in God's mercy, abiding therein.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>108</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>109</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:108-109] Those are the verses of God which We recite to you in truth, and God desires not any injustice for the worlds. * To God belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth, and to Him all matters are returned.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>110</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>110</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:110] You are the best community brought forth to men, enjoining decency, and forbidding indecency, and believing in God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>111</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>111</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:111] They will not harm you, except a little hurt; and if they fight against you, they will turn their backs to you, then they will not be helped.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>112</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>112</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:112] Abasement shall be cast upon them, wherever they are found, save a rope of God, and a rope of the people; they have incurred with anger from God, and poverty shall be cast upon them; that because they disbelieved in God's signs, and slew the prophets without right; that because they disobeyed and used to transgress.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>113</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>114</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:113-114) Yet they are not all alike; some of the People of the Scripture are a community upright, who recite God's verses in the watches of the night, prostrating themselves. * They believe in God and in the Last Day, enjoining decency and forbidding indecency, vying with one another in good works; those are of the righteous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>115</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>115</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:115] And whatever good they do, they shall not be denied it, and God knows the God-fearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>116</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>116</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:116] As for the disbelievers, their riches shall not avail them, neither their children, against God; those are the inhabitants of the Fire, abiding therein.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>117</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>117</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:117] The likeness of what they expend in the life of this world is as the likeness of a wind wherein is a blast that smote the tillage of a people who have wronged themselves and destroyed it. God did not wrong them, but they wronged themselves.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>118</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>118</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:118] O you who believe, do not take as intimates anyone apart from yourselves; such men spare nothing to ruin you; they would love for you to suffer. Hatred is revealed by their mouths; and what their breasts conceal is yet greater. Now We have made clear to you the signs; if you understand.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>119</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>119</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:119] Lo, there you are, you love them, but they love you not; you believe in the Book, all of it, and when they meet you they say, 'We believe', but when they are alone, they bite at you their fingertips, in rage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>120</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>120</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:120] If good fortunate befalls you, it is evil for them; but if evil befalls you, they rejoice thereat. Yet if you endure and fear, their guile will not hurt you at all; God encompasses what they do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>121</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>121</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:121] And when you went forth at dawn from your family to assign the believers their places for battle, and God hears, knows.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>122</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>122</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:122] When two parties of you were about to lose heart; and God was their Protector, and let the believers rely on God.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>123</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>123</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:123] God already gave you victory at Badr, when you were contemptible. So fear God, in order that you might be thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>124</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>125</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:124-5] When you were saying to the believers, 'Is it not sufficient for you that</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>126</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>126</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:126] What God ordained was only as a good tiding to you and that your hearts might be at peace. Victory comes only from God, the Mighty, the Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>127</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>127</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:127] And that He might cut off a party of the disbelievers, or suppress them, so that they fall back, frustrated.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>128</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>129</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:128-129] No part of the command is yours [Muḥammad], whether He relents to them or chastises them; for they are indeed evildoers. * To God belongs all that is in the heavens and the earth; He forgives whom He wills and chastises whom He wills. And God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>130</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>131</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:130-131] O you who believe, do not exact usury, twofold and severalfold. And fear God, so that you may prosper. * And fear the Fire that has been prepared for the disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>132</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>132</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:132] And obey God and the Messenger, so that you may find mercy.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>133</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>134</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:133-134] And vie with one another hastening to forgiveness from your Lord, and to a garden as wide as the heavens and the earth that has been prepared for those who fear. * Who expend in prosperity and adversity, and restrain their rage, and pardon their fellow-men; and God loves those who are virtuous.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>135</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>136</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:135-136] And who when they commit an indecency or wrong themselves, remember God, and pray forgiveness for their sins - and who shall forgive sins but God? - and who do not persist in what they did, knowing. * Those - their requital is forgiveness from their Lord, and Gardens beneath which rivers flow, abiding therein; excellent is the wage of those workers!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>137</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>138</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:137-138] Ways of life have passed away before you; so travel in the land and behold how was the end of those who denied. * This is an exposition for mankind, and a guidance, and an admonition for such as are God-fearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>139</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>139</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:139] Faint not, neither grieve, for you shall prevail if you are believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>140</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>140</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:140] If a wound touches you, a like wound already has touched the other people. Such days We deal out in turn among mankind, and that God may know those who believe; and that He may take witnesses from among you, and God loves not the evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>141</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>141</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:141] And that God may prove the believers, and efface the disbelievers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>142</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>142</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:142] Or did you suppose that you should enter Paradise without God knowing, who among you have struggled and who are patient.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>143</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>143</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:143] You were longing for death before you met it. Now you have seen it, looking on.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>144</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>144</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:144] Muhammad is only a messenger: messengers have passed away before him. Why, if he should die or is slain, will you turn back on your heels. If any man should turn back on his heels, he will not harm God in any way, and God will requite those that are thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>145</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>145</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:145] It is not for any soul to die, save by the leave of God, a prescribed term. And whoever desires the reward of this world, We will give him of it; and whoever desires the reward of the Hereafter, We will give him of it; and We will requite the thankful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>146</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>146</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:146] How many a prophet has been killed and with him thousands manifold [fought], but they fainted not in the face of what afflicted them in God's way; they neither weakened, nor did they humble themselves. And God loves the patient.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>147</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>147</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:147] All that they said was, 'Our Lord, forgive us our sins and our excesses in our affairs and make firm our feet and help us against the unbelieving folk'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>148</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>148</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:148] And God gave them the reward of this world,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>149</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>150</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:149-150] O you who believe, if you obey the disbelievers, they will make you turn back on your heels, and you will revert as losers. * Nay, but God is your Protector, and He is the best of helpers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>151</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>151</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:151] We will cast terror into the hearts of the disbelievers; for what they have associated with God that for which He has revealed no warrant; their abode shall be the Fire; evil is the abode of the evildoers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>152</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>152</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:152] God has been true to His promise, when you slew them by His leave, until you lost heart, and quarreled over the command; and you disobeyed after he had shown you what you longed for.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>153</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>154</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:153-154] When you were ascending, not turning around for anyone and the Messenger was calling you from your rear, so he rewarded you with grief for grief so that you might not grieve for what escaped you, neither for what befell you; and God is aware of what you do. * Then He sent down upon you, after grief, security - a slumber overcoming a party of you, and a party whose own souls distressed them, thinking wrongly of God, thoughts of age of ignorance, saying, 'Have we any part whatever in the affair?' Say: 'The affair belongs entirely to God'. They conceal within their hearts what they do not disclose to you, saying, 'Had we had any part in the affair, we would not have been slain here'. Say: 'Even if you had been in your houses, those for whom it had been appointed that they be slain would have sallied forth to the places where they were to lie' that God might try what was in your breasts and that He might prove what was in your hearts; and God knows what is in the breasts.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>155</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>155</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:155] Truly, those of you who turned away the day the two hosts encountered each other - truly, Satan made them slip through some of what they had earned; but God pardoned them; God is Forgiving, Forbearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>156</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>156</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:156] O you who believe, be not as the disbelievers, who say of their brothers, when they travel in the land, or are on raiding campaigns, 'Had they been with us, they would not have died and would not have been slain' - so that God may make that anguish in their hearts. For God gives life, and He gives death and God sees what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>157</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>158</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:157-158] And if you are slain in God's way, or die, forgiveness from God and mercy are better than what they amass. * And if you die or are slain, it is to God you shall be mustered.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>159</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>159</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:159] It was by the mercy of God that you were lenient with them; had you been harsh and fierce of heart, they would have dispersed from about you. So pardon them, and ask forgiveness for them, and consult them in the matter. And when you are resolved, rely on God; for God loves those who rely.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>160</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>160</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:160] If God helps you, then none can overcome you; but if He forsakes you, then who is there who can help you after Him? Therefore on God let the believers rely.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>161</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>161</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:161] It is not for a prophet to be fraudulent; whoever defrauds shall bring what he has defrauded on the Day of Resurrection; then every soul shall be paid in full what it has earned, and they shall not be wronged.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>162</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>163</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:162-3] Is he who follows God's beatitude like him who is laden with God's anger, whose abode is hell? An evil journey's end! * They are of degrees before God; and God sees what they do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>164</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>164</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:164] Truly God was gracious to the believers when He sent to them a messenger from among their own to recite to them His verses, and to purify them, and to teach them the Book, wisdom, though before, they were in clear error.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>165</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>165</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:165] And why, when distress befell you, and you had afflicted twice the like of it, did you say, 'How is this?' Say: 'It is from yourselves. Surely God has power over everything.'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>166</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>167</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:166-167] And what afflicted you, the day the two hosts encountered, was by God's leave, and that He might know the believers. * And that He might also know the hypocrites when it was said to them, 'Come now, fight in the way of God or defend', they said, 'If we knew how to fight we would follow you'. They that day were nearer to unbelief than to belief, saying with their mouths that which was not in their hearts. And God knows best what they hide.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>168</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>168</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:168] Those who said to their brothers, whilst they themselves stayed put, 'Had they obeyed us, they would not have been slain'. Say: 'Then avert death from yourselves, if you speak the truth'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>169</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>170</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:169-170] Count not those who were slain in God's way, as dead, but rather, living with their Lord, provided for [by Him]. * Rejoicing in what God has given them of His bounty, and rejoicing, for the sake of those who have not joined them but are left behind, that no fear shall befall them, neither shall they grieve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>171</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>171</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:171] Joyful in grace and bounty from God, and that God does not let the wage of believers go to waste.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>172</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>172</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:172] [For] those who responded to God and the Messenger after the wounds had afflicted them, those who did good among them and feared, shall be a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>173</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>173</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:173] Those to whom people said, 'The people have gathered against you, therefore fear them'; but that increased them in faith, and they said, 'God is sufficient for us, an excellent Guardian is He'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>174</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>174</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:174] So they returned with grace and bounty from God, and no evil touched them, and they followed the beatitude of God; and God is of bounty abounding.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>175</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>175</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:175] That is only Satan making fear his friends, therefore do not fear them; but fear Me, if you are believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>176</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>176</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:176] Let them not grieve you those that vie with one another in unbelief; they will not hurt God at all. God desires not to assign them any portion in the Hereafter, and theirs is a mighty chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>177</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>177</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:177] Those who purchase unbelief at the price of faith, they will not hurt God at all, and there awaits them a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>178</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>178</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:178] And let not the disbelievers suppose that what We indulge them in is better for their souls. We grant them indulgence only that they may increase in sinfulness, and theirs is a humbling chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>179</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>179</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:179] It is not God's purpose to leave the believers in the state in which you are till He shall distinguish the evil one from the good. And it is not God's purpose to apprise you of the Unseen, but God chooses of His messengers whom He will. So believe in God and His messengers; and if you believe and guard [against evil], then yours shall be a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>180</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>180</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:180] Let them not suppose those who are niggardly with what God has given them of His bounty, that it is better for them; nay, it is worse for them; what they were niggardly with, they shall have hung around their necks on the Day of Resurrection; and to God belongs the inheritance of the heavens and the earth. And God is aware of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>181</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>182</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:181-182] Verily God has heard the saying of those who said, 'Indeed God is poor, and we are rich'. We shall write down what they have said and their slaying the prophets without right, and We shall say, 'Taste the chastisement of the Burning. * That is for what your hands have sent before; for God is never unjust towards His servants'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>183</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>183</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:183] Those same who said, 'God has already made covenant with us that we should not believe in any messenger until he bring us an offering to be devoured by fire'. Say: 'Messengers have come to you before me with clear proofs, and with that which you said. Why did you slay them, then, if you are truthful?'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>184</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>184</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:184] But if they deny you, so were denied messengers before you who came bearing clear proofs, and the Scriptures, and the Illuminating Book.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>185</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>185</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:185] Every soul shall taste of death; you shall surely be paid in full your wages on the Day of Resurrection. Whoever is moved away from the Fire and admitted to Paradise, will have triumphed, the life of this world is but the comfort of delusion.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>186</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>186</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:186] You shall surely be tried in your property; and in your selves, and you shall bear from those who were given the Scripture before you, and from those who are idolaters, much hurt, but if you are patient, and fear - surely that is true resolve.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>187</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>187</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:187] And when God made covenant with those who had been given the Scripture, 'You shall expound it to people, and not conceal it'. But they rejected it behind their backs, and bought it with a small price; how evil is what they have bought!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>188</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>188</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:188] Do not reckon that those who rejoice in what they have brought, and who love to be praised for what they have not done - do not reckon them secure from the chastisement; there shall be a painful chastisement for them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>189</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>189</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:189] To God belongs the kingdom of the heavens and the earth, and God has power over all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>190</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>191</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:190-3:191] Surely in the creation of the heavens and the earth, and in the alternation of night and day, there are signs for people of pith. * Those who remember God, standing and sitting and on their sides,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>192</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>192</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:192] Our Lord, whomever You admit into the Fire, You will have abased, and the evildoers shall have no helpers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>193</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>193</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:193] 'Our Lord, we have heard a caller calling to belief, saying, " Believe in your Lord! " And we believed. So, our Lord, forgive us our sins and absolve us of our evil deeds, and take us [in death] with the pious.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>194</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>194</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:194] 'Our Lord, grant us what You have promised us through Your messengers, and abase us not on the Day of Resurrection. You will not fail the tryst'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>195</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>195</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:195] And their Lord answers them, 'I do not let the labor of any laborer among you go to waste, be you male or female - the one of you is as the other: and those who emigrated, and were expelled from their habitations, those who suffered hurt in My way, and fought, and were slain - them I shall surely absolve of their evil deeds, and I shall admit them to Gardens underneath which river flow'. A reward from God! And God - with Him is the fairest reward.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>196</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>197</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:196-3:197] Let it not delude you, that the disbelievers go to and fro in the land, * a little enjoyment; then their abode is Hell - an evil cradling!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>198</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>198</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:198] But those who fear their Lord - for them shall be Gardens underneath which rivers flow, abiding therein; a hospitality from God Himself. That which is with God is better for the pious.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>199</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>199</lastVerse>
      <text>[3:199] Verily, there are some among the People of the Scripture who believe in God, and what has been revealed to you, and what has been revealed to them, humble before God, not purchasing with the verses of God a small price. Those - their wage is with their Lord. God is swift at reckoning.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="4">
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>1</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>1</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:1] O people, fear your Lord, Who created you of a single soul, and from it created its mate, and from the pair of them scattered many men and women; and fear God by whom you claim [your rights] from one another and kinship ties. Surely God has been watchful over you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>2</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>2</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:2] Give the orphans their property and do not exchange the evil for the good,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>3</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>4</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:3-4:4] If you fear that you will not act justly towards the orphans, marry such women as seem good to you, two or three or four, but if you fear you will not be equitable, then only one, or what your right hands own; thus, it is likelier that you will not be unjust. * And give women their dowries as a free gift;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>5</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>5</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:5] But do not give to the foolish your property, which God has assigned to you as maintenance; provide for them thereof, and clothe them, and speak to them decent words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>6</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>6</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:6] Try well the orphans until they reach the age of marrying; then, if you perceive in them maturity, deliver their property to them; consume it not wastefully and in haste, lest they should grow up. If any man is rich, let him be abstinent; if he is poor, let him consume honorably. And when you deliver to them their property, take witnesses over them. God suffices as a reckoner.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>7</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>7</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:7] To the men belongs a share of what parents and kinsmen leave, and to the women belongs a share of what parents and kinsmen leave, whether it be little or much - an obligatory share.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>8</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>8</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:8] And when the division is attended by kinsmen, and orphans, and the poor, grant them out of it; and speak to them honorable words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>9</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>9</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:9] And let them fear those who, if they leave behind them weak offspring would be afraid for them; let them fear God and speak pertinent words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>10</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>10</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:10] Those who consume the property of orphans unjustly, are only consuming fire in their bellies and they shall be exposed a blaze.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>11</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>11</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:11] God charges you concerning your children, to the male the equivalent of the portion of two females; and if they be women more than two, then for them two-thirds of what he leaves; but if she be one then to her a half; and to his parents, to each one of the two the sixth of what he leaves, if he has a child; but if he has no child, and his heirs are his parents, then to his mother a third; or, if he has siblings, to his mother a sixth after any bequest that he may bequeath, or any debt.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>12</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>12</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:12] And for you a half of what your wives leave, if they have no children; but if they have children, then for you a fourth of what they leave, after any bequest they may bequeath, or any debt: a fourth of what you leave, if you have no children; but if you have children, then for them an eighth of what you leave, after any bequest you may bequeath, or any debt. If it be a man leaving an inheritance and not having a direct heir, or it be a woman, but it be that such, has a brother or a sister, then to each of the two a sixth; but if they be more than that, then they share a third after any bequest to be bequeathed or any debt without prejudice; a charge from God. God is Knowing, Forbearing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>13</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>13</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:13] Those are God's bounds. Whoever obeys God and His Messenger, He will admit him to Gardens underneath which rivers flow, abiding therein; that is the great triumph.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>14</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>14</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:14] But whoever disobeys God, and His Messenger; and transgresses His bounds, him He will admit to a Fire, abiding therein, and for him there shall be a humbling chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>15</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>15</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:15] As for those of your women who commit lewdness, call four of you to witness against them; and if they witness, then detain them in their houses until death take them or God appoints for them a way.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>16</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>16</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:16] And when two of you commit it, punish them both; but if they repent and make amends, then leave them be. God ever turns [relenting] and is Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>17</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>17</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:17] The repentance that God accepts is only of those who do evil in ignorance; then repent shortly thereafter; God will relent to those. And God is ever Knowing, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>18</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>18</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:18] Repentance is not for those who do evil deeds until, when death approaches one of them, he says, 'Indeed now I repent'; neither for those who die disbelieving. Those - We have prepared for them a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>19</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>19</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:19] O you who believe, it is not lawful for you to inherit women against their will; neither debar them, so that you may go off with part of what you have given them, except when they commit flagrant lewdness. Consort with them in kindness; for if you hate them, it may happen that you hate a thing wherein God has set much good.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>20</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>20</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:20] And if you desire to exchange a wife in place of another, and you have given to one a hundredweight, take of it nothing. Would you take it by way of calumny and manifest sin?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>21</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>21</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:21] How shall you take it...</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>22</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>22</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:22] And do not marry women whom your fathers married, unless it be a thing of the past; surely that is obscene and abominable, an evil way.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>23</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>23</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:23] Forbidden to you are your mothers, and daughters, your sisters, your paternal aunts, and maternal aunts, your brother's daughters, your sister's daughters, your foster mothers who have given you milk, your foster sisters, your mothers-in-law, your step-daughters, who are in your care being born of your wives you have been in to - but if you have not yet been in to them you are not at fault - and the spouses of your sons who are of your loins, and that you should take to you two sisters together unless it be a thing of the past. God is ever Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>24</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>24</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:24] And wedded women, save what your right hands own, this is what God has prescribed for you. Lawful for you beyond all that is that you seek using your wealth, in wedlock and not in illicitly. Such wives as you enjoy thereby, give them their wages as an obligation; you are not at fault in agreeing together, after the obligation. God is ever Knowing,Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>25</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>25</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:25] And whoever has not the means wherewith to be able to marry believing women in wedlock, let him take believing maids whom your right hands own. God knows very well your faith; the one of you is as the other. So marry them, with the permission of their folk, and give them their wages, honorably, as women in wedlock, not illicitly, or taking lovers. But when they are given in wedlock, if they commit lewdness, they shall be liable to half the chastisement, of married women. That is for those of you who fear the distress of sin, yet it is better for you to be patient. God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>26</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>26</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:26] God desires to make clear to you and to guide you in the ways of those before you, and to turn [in forgiveness] towards you; God is Knowing, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>27</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>28</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:27-28] And God desires to turn [forgivingly] towards you, but those who follow their passions, desire that you deviate with a terrible deviation. * God desires to lighten things for you; for man was created weak.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>29</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>30</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:29-4:30] O you who believe, consume not your goods between you wrongly, except it be trading through mutual agreement. And kill not yourselves. Surely God is ever Merciful to you. * And whoever does that through aggression and injustice, him We shall certainly expose to a fire; and that for God is an easy matter.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>31</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>31</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:31] If you avoid the grave sins that are forbidden you, We will absolve you of your evil deeds and admit you by an honorable gate.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>32</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>32</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:32] Do not covet that in which God has preferred some of you above others. To men a share from what they have earned and to women a share from what they have earned. And ask God of His bounty; God is ever Knower of all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>33</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>33</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:33] To each We have appointed heirs (mawālī) of that which parents and kinsmen leave and to those to whom your right hands were pledged. So give them their share. God is ever Witness over everything.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>34</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>34</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:34] Men are in charge of women because of that with which God has preferred the one over the other, and because of what they expend of their property. Therefore righteous women are obedient, guarding in the unseen because of what God has guarded. And those you fear may be rebellious, admonish them, and share not beds with them, and strike them. If they then obey you, do not seek a way against them. God is ever High, Great.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>35</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>35</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:35] And if you fear a breach between the two, send forth an arbiter from his folk, and an arbiter from her folk, if they desire to set things right, God will grant them success. Surely God is ever Knower, Aware.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>36</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>37</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:36-4:37] And worship God, and associate nothing with Him. Be kind to parents, and near kindred, and to orphans, and to the needy, and to the neighbor who is near, and to the neighbor who is a stranger, and to the friend at your side, and to the wayfarer, and to what your right hands own. Surely God loves not the conceited, and the boastful. * Those who are niggardly, and bid other people to be niggardly, and conceal what God has bestowed upon them of His bounty. And We have prepared for those that disbelieve a humbling chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>38</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>38</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:38] And those who expend of their substance to show off to people, and believe not in God and the Last Day. Whoever has Satan for a comrade, then an evil comrade has he.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>39</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>39</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:39] And what burden is on them if they were to believe in God and the Last Day, and expend of what God has provided them? God is ever Aware of them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>40</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>40</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:40] Surely God shall not wrong so much as the weight of an atom; and if it be a good deed, He will double it and give from Himself a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>41</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>42</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:41-4:42] So how shall it be when We bring forward from every community a witness; and We bring you as witness against these? * Upon that day, the disbelievers, those who have disobeyed the Messenger, will wish that the earth might be leveled with them. And they will not hide from God any talk.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>43</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>43</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:43] O you who believe, draw not near to prayer, whilst you are inebriated, until you know what you are saying, nor whilst you are defiled, unless you are traversing a way, until you have washed yourselves. But if you are sick, or on a journey, or if any of you comes from the privy, or you have touched women; and you can find no water, wholesome soil, and wipe your faces and your hands. God is ever Pardoning, Forgiving.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>44</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>46</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:44-4:46] Have you not seen those who were given a share of the Book, purchasing error and desiring that you should err from the way? * God has better knowledge of your enemies. God suffices as a Protector, God suffices as a Helper. * Some from among the Jews distort the words from their contexts and they say, 'We have heard, and we disobey, and hear as one who does not hear' and, 'Mind us', twisting with their tongues and slandering religion. If they had said, 'We have heard and obey', and 'Hear', and 'Consider us,', it would have been better for them and more upright, but God has cursed them for their unbelief, so they believe not except a few.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>47</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>47</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:47] O you who have been given the Scripture, believe in what We have revealed, confirming what is with you before We obliterate faces, and turn them inside out or curse them as We cursed those of the Sabbath, and God's command is done.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>48</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>48</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:48] God forgives not that anything should be associated with Him. But He forgives other than that to whomever He wills. Whoever associates anything with God, then he has indeed invented a tremendous sin.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>49</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>50</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:49-4:50] Have you not seen those who praise themselves for purity? Nay, God purifies whom He will, and they shall not be wronged, a single date-thread. * Consider how they invent falsehood against God, and that suffices for a clear sin.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>51</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>52</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:51-4:52] Have you not seen those who were given a share of the Book, how they believe in al-Jibt and al-Ṭāghūt, and say to the disbelievers, 'These are more rightly guided than the believers'? * Those are the ones whom God has cursed; and he whom God has cursed, you will never find for him any helper.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>53</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>55</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:53-4:55] Or have they a share in the Kingdom?, then they would not give the people a single date-spot. * Or, are they jealous of people for the bounty that God has bestowed upon them. For We gave the House of Abraham the Book and wisdom, and We gave them a mighty kingdom. * And there are some of them who believe in him and some of them who bar from him. Hell suffices for a blaze.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>56</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>56</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:56] Surely those who disbelieve in Our signs - We shall expose them to a Fire; as often as their skins are consumed, We shall replace them with other skins, that they may taste the chastisement. Surely God is ever Mighty, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>57</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>57</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:57] And those that believe, and perform righteous deeds, We shall admit them to Gardens underneath which rivers flow, wherein they abide: they shall have therein spouses purified, and We shall admit them to plenteous shade.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>58</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>58</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:58] Verily, God commands you to restore trusts. And when you judge between people, that you judge with justice. Excellent is the admonition God gives you. God is ever Hearer, Seer.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>59</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>59</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:59] O you who believe, obey God, and obey the Messenger and those in authority among you. If you should quarrel about anything, refer it to God and the Messenger, if you believe in God and the Last Day; that is better and more excellent in interpretation.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>60</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>60</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:60] Have you not seen those who claim that they believe in what has been revealed to you, and what was revealed before you, desiring to take their disputes to a false deity when they have been commanded to renounce him? But Satan desires to mislead them, far astray.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>61</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>61</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:61] And when it is said to them, 'Come to what God has revealed and the Messenger', you see the hypocrites turn away from you vehemently.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>62</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>62</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:62] How would it be when an affliction befalls them for what their own hands have sent before them! They then come to you, swearing by God that, 'We sought only virtue and harmony'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>63</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>63</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:63] Those - God knows what is in their hearts; so turn away from them, and admonish them, and say to them regarding their souls penetrating words.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>64</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>64</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:64] We never sent any Messenger, but that he should be obeyed by the leave of God. If, when they had wronged themselves, they had come to you, and asked forgiveness from God, and the Messenger had asked forgiveness for them, they would have found God Relenting, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>65</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>65</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:65] But no, by your Lord! They will not believe until they make you judge over what has broken out between them and find in themselves no inhibition regarding what you decide, but submit in full submission.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>66</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>68</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:66-4:68] And had We prescribed for them: 'Slay yourselves' or 'Leave your habitations', they would not have done it, save a few of them; yet if they had done what they were admonished to do, it would have been better for them, and stronger in establishing. * And then, We would have surely given them from Us a great wage. * And We would have guided them to a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>69</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>70</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:69-4:70] Whoever obeys God and the Messenger, they are with those whom God has blessed of the prophets and the truthful, and the martyrs, and the righteous. What fine companions they are! * That is bounty from God. God suffices as Knower.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>71</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>73</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:71-4:73] O you who believe, take your precautions, then move forward in companies, or move forward all together. * Verily, there are some of you who tarry; then, if an affliction befalls you, he says, 'God has been gracious to me, for I was not a witness with them'. * But if a bounty from God befalls you, he will surely cry as if there had never been any affection between you and him: 'Oh, would that I had been with them, so that I might have won a great triumph!'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>74</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>74</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:74] So let them fight in the way of God those who sell the life of this world for the Hereafter; and whoever fights in the way of God and is slain or conquers, We shall give him a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>75</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>75</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:75] What is wrong with you, that you do not fight in the way of God, and for the oppressed men, women, and children who say, 'Our Lord, bring us forth from this town whose people are evildoers and appoint for us a protector from You, and appoint for us from You a helper'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>76</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>76</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:76] Those who believe fight in the way of God, and those who disbelieve fight in the way of a false deity. Fight therefore against the friends of Satan; surely the plotting of Satan is ever feeble.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>77</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>77</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:77] Have you not seen those to whom it was said, 'Restrain your hands, and establish the prayer, and pay the alms'? Then, as soon as fighting was prescribed for them, lo, a party of them fear people as they would fear God, or with more fear and they said, 'Our Lord, why have You prescribed fighting for us? Why not defer us to a near term?'</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>78</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>78</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:78] Wherever you may be, death will overtake you, though you should be in raised-up towers'. And if a good thing befalls them, they say, 'This is from God'; but if an evil thing befalls them, they say, 'This is from you'. Say, 'Everything is from God'. What is wrong with this people that they do not understand?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>79</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>79</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:79] Whatever good befalls you it is from God; whatever evil befalls you is from yourself. We have sent you to people as a messenger and God suffices as Witness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>80</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>80</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:80] Whoever obeys the Messenger, verily obeys God; and whoever turns his back, We have not sent you as a watcher over them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>81</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>81</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:81] They say, Obedience; but when they sally forth from you, a party of them harbor other than what they say. God writes down what they harbor. So turn away from them, rely on God, and God suffices as a Guardian.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>82</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>83</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:82-4:83] What, do they not ponder the QurÌān? If it had been from other than God surely they would have found therein much inconsistency. * And when there comes to them an issue, be it of security, or of fear, they broadcast it. If they had referred it to the Messenger and to those in authority among them; those among them who are able to think it out (yastanbi?ūnahu), would have known it from them. And but for the bounty of God to you and His mercy, you would surely have followed Satan, except a few [of you].</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>84</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>84</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:84] So fight in the way of God; you are charged only with yourself. And urge on the believers; maybe God will restrain the might of the disbelievers; God is mightier and more severe in castigation.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>85</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>85</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:85] Whoever intercedes with a good intercession shall receive a share of it; and whoever intercedes with an evil intercession, shall receive the like from it. God conserves all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>86</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>86</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:86] And when you are greeted with a greeting, greet with better than it, or return it. Surely God keeps count of all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>87</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>87</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:87] God - there is no god except Him, He will surely gather you to the Day of Resurrection whereof there is no doubt. And who is truer in statement than God?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>88</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>88</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:88] What is wrong with you that you have become two parties, regarding the hypocrites, when God has overthrown them for what they earned? What, do you desire to guide him whom God has sent astray? And he whom God sends astray, you will never find for him a way.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>89</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>90</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:89-4:90] They long that you should disbelieve as they disbelieve, so then you would be equal; therefore do not take friends from among them until they emigrate in the way of God; then, if they turn away, take them and slay them wherever you find them; and do not take any of them as a patron, or as a helper. * Except those who attach themselves to a people between whom and you there is a covenant, or come to you with their breasts constricted about the prospect of fighting you, or fighting their people. Had God willed, He would have given them sway over you, so that assuredly they would have fought you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>91</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>91</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:91] You will find others desiring to have security from you and security from their own people; yet whenever they are returned to sedition, they are overwhelmed by it. So, if they do not stay away from you, and offer you peace, and restrain their hands, then take them and slay them wherever you come upon them; against them We have given you clear warrant.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>92</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>92</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:92] It is not for a believer to slay a believer, except by mistake. He who slays a believer by mistake, then let him set free a believing slave, and blood-money is to be submitted to his family, unless they remit it as a charity. If he belongs to a people at enmity with you and is a believer, then the setting free of a believing slave. If he belongs to a people between whom and you there is a covenant, then the blood-money must be paid to his family, and the setting free of a believing slave. But if he has not the wherewithal, then the fasting of two successive months, a relenting from God. And God is ever Knowing, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>93</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>93</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:93] And whoever slays a believer deliberately, his requital is Hell, abiding therein, and God is wroth with him and has cursed him, and has prepared for him a mighty chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>94</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>94</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:94] O you who believe, when you are going forth in the way of God, be discriminating and do not say to him who offers you peace: 'You are not a believer, desiring the transient goods of the life of this world. With God are plenteous spoils. So you were formerly, but God has been gracious to you. So be discriminating. Surely God is ever Aware of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>95</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>96</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:95-4:96] The believers who sit at home, other than those who have an injury are not the equals of those who struggle in the way of God with their possessions and their lives. God has preferred those who struggle with their possessions and their lives over the ones who sit at home by a degree; yet to each God has promised the goodly reward, and God has preferred those who struggle over the ones who sit at home with a great reward, * degrees from Him, and forgiveness and mercy. Surely God is ever Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>97</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>97</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:97] And those whom the angels take [in death], while they are wronging their souls, the angels will say, 'What was your predicament?' They will say, 'We were oppressed in the land'. The angels will say, 'But was not God's earth spacious that you might have emigrated therein?' As for such, their abode shall be Hell - an evil journey's end!</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>98</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>99</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:98-4:99] Except the oppressed among the men, women, and children who are unable to devise a plan and are not guided to a way. *As for such, perhaps God will pardon them, for God is ever Pardoning,Forgiving.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>100</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>100</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:100] Whoever emigrates in the way of God will find in the earth many refuges and abundance; whoever goes forth from his house as an emigrant to God and His Messenger, and then death overtakes him, his wage is then incumbent upon God; surely God is ever Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>101</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>101</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:101] And when you are going forth in the land you would not be at fault if you shorten the prayer if you fear that you may be afflicted by those who do not believe; the disbelievers are a manifest foe to you.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>102</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>102</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:102] When you are among them, and you stand to lead them in prayer, let a party of them stand with you, and let them take their weapons. Then when they have performed their prostrations, let them be behind you, and let another party who have not prayed come and pray with you, taking their precautions and their weapons. The disbelievers wish that you should be heedless of your weapons and your baggage that they may descend upon you all at once. You are not at fault, if rain bothers you, or if you are sick, to lay aside your weapons. But take your precautions; God has prepared for the disbelievers a humiliating chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>103</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>103</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:103] When you have performed the prayer, remember God, standing and sitting and on your sides. Then, when you are reassured, observe the prayer, surely the prayer is for believers a prescription at specific times.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>104</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>104</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:104] Be not faint in seeking the enemy; if you are suffering, they are also suffering as you are suffering; and you hope from God that for which they cannot hope. God is ever Knower, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>105</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>106</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:105-4:106] Surely We have revealed to you the Book with the truth so that you may judge between people by that which God has shown you. And do not be a disputant for traitors. * And pray for forgiveness from God; surely God is ever Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>107</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>108</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:107-4:108] And do not dispute on behalf of those who betray themselves; surely God loves not one who is treacherous and sinful. * They hide themselves from people, but they do not hide themselves from God; for He is with them while they plot at night with discourse displeasing to Him. God is ever Encompassing of what they do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>109</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>109</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:109] Ah! There you are you have contested on their behalf in the life of this world; but who will contest against God on their behalf on the Day of Resurrection, or who will be a guardian for them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>110</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>110</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:110] Whoever does evil, or wrongs himself, and then prays for God's forgiveness, he shall find God is Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>111</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>111</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:111] And whoever commits a sin commits it against himself only; and God is ever Knower, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>112</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>112</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:112] And whoever commits a mistake or a sin, and then casts it upon the innocent, he has thereby burdened himself with calumny and a manifest sin.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>113</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>113</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:113] Were it not for God's bounty to you and His mercy, a party of them would have intended to lead you astray; but they lead only themselves astray; they will not hurt you at all. God has revealed to you the Book and wisdom, and He has taught you what you did not know; and God's bounty to you is ever great.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>114</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>114</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:114] There is no good in much of their secret conversations, except for he who enjoins to voluntary almsgiving, or kindness, or setting things right between people. And whoever does that, desiring God's good pleasure, We shall surely give him a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>115</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>115</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:115] But whoever makes a breach with the Messenger after guidance has become clear to him, and follows other than the way of the believers, We shall turn him over to what he has turned to, and We shall expose him in Hell - an evil journey's end.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>116</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>119</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:116-4:119] God does not forgive that anything should be associated with Him; He forgives all except that, to whomever He will. Whoever associates anything with God, verily he has strayed far away. * What they pray to instead of Him are but females, and they only pray to a rebellious satan. * God has cursed him. And he said, 'Assuredly I will take to myself an appointed portion of Your servants. * And I will surely lead them astray, and surely I will fill them with desires; and surely I will command them and they will cut up the cattle's ears. And surely I will command them and they will change God's creation'. And whoever takes Satan for a patron, instead of God, has surely suffered a manifest loss.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>120</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>121</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:120-4:121] He promises them, and fills them with desires; but what Satan promises them is only delusion. * For such - their abode shall be Hell, and they shall find no refuge from it.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>122</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>122</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:122] But those who believe and perform righteous deeds, We shall admit them to Gardens underneath which rivers flow, abiding therein for ever; God's promise in truth; and who, is truer in utterance than God?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>123</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>124</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:123-124] It is not your desires nor the desires of the People of the Scripture. Whoever does evil shall be requited for it; and he will not find besides God any friend or helper. * And whoever does righteous deeds, whether male or female, and is a believer - such shall be admitted into Paradise, and not be wronged, the dint in a date-stone.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>125</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>126</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:125-4:126] And who is fairer in religion than he who submits his purpose to God and is virtuous, and who follows the creed of Abraham as a ḥanīf? And God took Abraham for a close friend. * To God belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth; and God is ever the Encompasser of all things.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>127</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>127</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:127] They will ask you for a pronouncement concerning women. Say: 'God pronounces to you concerning them, and what is recited to you in the Book, concerning the orphan women to whom you do not give what is prescribed for them for you desire to marry them, and the oppressed children and that you deal justly with orphans. Whatever good you do, God is ever Knower of it'.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>128</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>128</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:128] And if a woman fears from her husband ill-treatment or rejection (iʿrā?), they are not at fault if they are reconciled through some agreement; reconciliation is better. But greed has been made present in the souls. If you are virtuous and fear, surely God is ever aware of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>129</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>129</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:129] You will never be able to be just to your wives, even if you be eager; yet do not turn altogether away, so that you leave her like one suspended. If you set things right, and fear, surely God is ever Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>130</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>130</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:130] But if they separate, God will compensate each of them out of His plenty. God is ever Embracing, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>131</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>131</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:131] To God belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth. We have charged those who were given the Scripture before you, and you, 'Fear God'. 'If you disbelieve, then to God belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth'; God is ever Independent, Praised.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>132</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>132</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:132] To God belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth; God suffices as a Guardian.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>133</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>133</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:133] If He will, He can remove you, O people, and bring others, surely God is ever able to do that.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>134</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>134</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:134] Whoever desires the reward of this world, then God has the reward of this world and of the Hereafter; God is ever Hearer, Seer.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>135</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>135</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:135] O you who believe, be upright in justice; witnesses for God, even though it be against yourselves; or parents and kinsmen, whether the person be rich or poor; God is closer to the two. So do not follow any whim, lest you swerve, for if you twist, or refrain, surely God is ever aware of what you do.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>136</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>136</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:136] O you who believe, believe in God and His Messenger and the Book which has been revealed to His Messenger; and the Book which was revealed before. And whoever disbelieves in God and His angels and His Books, and His messengers, and the Last Day, verily he has strayed far away.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>137</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>138</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:137-4:138] Verily, those who believed, and then disbelieved, and then believed, and then disbelieved, and then increased in disbelief - it was not for God to forgive them, nor to guide them to a way. * Give tidings to the hypocrites that for them there is a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>139</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>140</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:139-4:140] Those who take disbelievers for friends instead of believers - do they desire power with them? Truly, power belongs altogether to God. * It has been revealed to you in the Book that: 'When you hear God's signs being disbelieved in and mocked, do not sit with them until they engage in some other talk, for otherwise you would surely be like them'. God will gather the hypocrites and disbelievers, all together, into Hell.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>141</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>141</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:141] Those who wait in watch for you, and, if a victory comes to you from God, say, 'Were we not with you?'; but if the disbelievers have some luck, they say, 'Did we not gain mastery over you, and did we not defend you against the believers?' God will judge between you on the Day of Resurrection, and God will never grant the disbelievers a way over the believers.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>142</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>143</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:142-4:143] The hypocrites seek to trick God, but He is tricking them. When they stand up to pray, they stand up lazily and to be seen by people, and they do not remember God save a little. * Wavering, all the time - not to these, neither to those; and he whom God sends astray, you will never find for him a way.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>144</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>144</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:144] O you who believe, take not the disbelievers as friends instead of the believers: do you desire to give God over you a clear warrant?</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>145</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>145</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:145] Verily, the hypocrites will be in the lowest level of the Fire; and you will never find a helper for them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>146</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>146</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:146] Save those who repent, and make amends, and hold fast to God and make their religion purely God's; those are with the believers; and God will certainly give the believers a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>147</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>147</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:147] Why would God chastise you if you are thankful and believe? God is ever Thankful, Knowing.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>148</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>148</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:148] God does not like the utterance of evil words out loud, unless a person has been wronged. God is ever Hearer, Knower.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>149</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>149</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:149] If you show good, or conceal it, or pardon evil, then surely God is ever Pardoning, Powerful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>150</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>151</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:150-151] Those who disbelieve in God and His messengers and seek to divide between God and His messengers, and say, 'We believe in some, and disbelieve in some', and seek to adopt a way between them. ** Those are the disbelievers truly; and We have prepared for the disbelievers a humiliating chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>152</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>152</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:152] And those who believe in God and His messengers and do not seek to divide between any of them, those - We shall surely give them their wages. God is ever Forgiving, Merciful.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>153</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>153</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:153] The People of the Scripture will ask of you to cause a Book to be revealed to them from the heaven. They asked Moses for something greater than that, for they said, 'Show us God openly'; so the thunderbolt seized them for their evildoing. They then took to themselves the [golden] calf after clear proofs had come to them; yet We pardoned that; and We bestowed upon Moses clear authority.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>154</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>154</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:154] And We raised above them the Mount, by the covenant with them, and We said to them, 'Enter the gate, bowing'; and We said to them, 'Transgress not the Sabbath, and We took from them a firm covenant.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>155</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>155</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:155] So, for their breaking their covenant and disbelieving in the signs of God, and slaying the prophets wrongfully, and for their saying, 'Our hearts are covered up' - nay, but God sealed them for their disbelief; so they do not believe, except for a few.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>156</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>156</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:156] And for their disbelief, and their uttering against Mary a tremendous calumny.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>157</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>158</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:157-8] And for their saying, 'We slew the Messiah, Jesus son of Mary, the Messenger of God'. And yet they did not slay him nor did they crucify him, but he was given the resemblance. And those who disagree concerning him are surely in doubt regarding him. They do not have any knowledge of him, only the pursuit of conjecture; and they did not slay him for certain. Nay, God raised him up to Him. God is ever Mighty, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>159</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>159</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:159] And there is not one of the People of the Scripture but will assuredly believe in him before his death; and on the Day of Resurrection he will be a witness against them.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>160</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>161</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:160-4:161] And because of the evildoing of some of those of Jewry, We have forbidden them certain good things that were lawful for them, and because of their barring from God's way, many.* And because of their taking usury when they had been forbidden it, and their consuming people's wealth through falsehood, and We have prepared for the disbelievers among them a painful chastisement.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>162</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>162</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:162] But those of them who are firmly rooted in knowledge, and the believers, believing in what has been revealed to you, and what was revealed before you, and those who observe the prayer; and pay the alms, and those who believe in God and the Last Day - to them We shall surely give a great wage.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>163</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>163</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:163] We have revealed to you as We revealed to Noah, and the prophets after him, and We revealed to Abraham and Ishmael and Isaac, and Jacob, and the Tribes, and Jesus and Job and Jonah and Aaron, and Solomon, and We gave to David the Inscribed Book.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>164</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>164</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:164] And messengers We have told you of before, and messengers We have not told you of; and God spoke directly to Moses.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>165</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>165</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:165] messengers bearing good tidings and warning so that people might have no argument against God after the messengers. God is ever Mighty, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>166</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>166</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:166] But God bears witness with what He has revealed to you; He has revealed it through His knowledge; and the angels also bear witness; and God suffices as a Witness.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>167</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>169</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:167-4:169] Surely those who disbelieve and bar from the way of God, they have indeed gone far astray. Surely those who disbelieve and who have done wrong, it is not for God to forgive them, neither to guide them to any path, except for the path of Hell, abiding, therein, forever; and for God that is an easy matter.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>170</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>170</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:170] O people, the Messenger has now come to you with the truth from your Lord; so believe, it is better for you. And if you disbelieve, then surely to God belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth; and God is ever Knowing, Wise.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>171</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>171</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:171] O People of the Scripture, do not go to extremes, in your religion and do not say about God except the truth: the Messiah, Jesus the son of Mary, was only the Messenger of God, and His Word which He cast to Mary, and a spirit from Him. So believe in God and His messengers, and do not say, 'Three'. Refrain, it is better for you. Verily, God is but One God. Glory be to Him, that He should have a son! To Him belongs all that is in the heavens and in the earth. God suffices as a Guardian.</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>172</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>173</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:172-4:173] The Messiah would never disdain to be a servant of God, neither would the angels who are nigh. Whoever disdains to worship Him, and waxes proud, He will assuredly muster them to Him, all of them. * As for those who believed, who did righteous deeds, He will pay them in full their wages, and He will give them more of His bounty;</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>174</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>174</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:174] O people, a proof has now come to you from your Lord,</text>
    </commentary>
    <commentary>
      <firstVerse>175</firstVerse>
      <lastVerse>175</lastVerse>
      <text>[4:175] As for those who believe in God, and hold fast to Him, He will surely admit them to mercy from Him, and bounty, and He will guide them to Him by a straight path.</text>
    </commentary>
  </chapter>
  <chapter index="5" />
  <chapter index="6" />
  <chapter index="7" />
  <chapter index="8" />
  <chapter index="9" />
  <chapter index="10" />
  <chapter index="11" />
  <chapter index="12" />
  <chapter index="13" />
  <chapter index="14" />
  <chapter index="15" />
  <chapter index="16" />
  <chapter index="17" />
  <chapter index="18" />
  <chapter index="19" />
  <chapter index="20" />
  <chapter index="21" />
  <chapter index="22" />
  <chapter index="23" />
  <chapter index="24" />
  <chapter index="25" />
  <chapter index="26" />
  <chapter index="27" />
  <chapter index="28" />
  <chapter index="29" />
  <chapter index="30" />
  <chapter index="31" />
  <chapter index="32" />
  <chapter index="33" />
  <chapter index="34" />
  <chapter index="35" />
  <chapter index="36" />
  <chapter index="37" />
  <chapter index="38" />
  <chapter index="39" />
  <chapter index="40" />
  <chapter index="41" />
  <chapter index="42" />
  <chapter index="43" />
  <chapter index="44" />
  <chapter index="45" />
  <chapter index="46" />
  <chapter index="47" />
  <chapter index="48" />
  <chapter index="49" />
  <chapter index="50" />
  <chapter index="51" />
  <chapter index="52" />
  <chapter index="53" />
  <chapter index="54" />
  <chapter index="55" />
  <chapter index="56" />
  <chapter index="57" />
  <chapter index="58" />
  <chapter index="59" />
  <chapter index="60" />
  <chapter index="61" />
  <chapter index="62" />
  <chapter index="63" />
  <chapter index="64" />
  <chapter index="65" />
  <chapter index="66" />
  <chapter index="67" />
  <chapter index="68" />
  <chapter index="69" />
  <chapter index="70" />
  <chapter index="71" />
  <chapter index="72" />
  <chapter index="73" />
  <chapter index="74" />
  <chapter index="75" />
  <chapter index="76" />
  <chapter index="77" />
  <chapter index="78" />
  <chapter index="79" />
  <chapter index="80" />
  <chapter index="81" />
  <chapter index="82" />
  <chapter index="83" />
  <chapter index="84" />
  <chapter index="85" />
  <chapter index="86" />
  <chapter index="87" />
  <chapter index="88" />
  <chapter index="89" />
  <chapter index="90" />
  <chapter index="91" />
  <chapter index="92" />
  <chapter index="93" />
  <chapter index="94" />
  <chapter index="95" />
  <chapter index="96" />
  <chapter index="97" />
  <chapter index="98" />
  <chapter index="99" />
  <chapter index="100" />
  <chapter index="101" />
  <chapter index="102" />
  <chapter index="103" />
  <chapter index="104" />
  <chapter index="105" />
  <chapter index="106" />
  <chapter index="107" />
  <chapter index="108" />
  <chapter index="109" />
  <chapter index="110" />
  <chapter index="111" />
  <chapter index="112" />
  <chapter index="113" />
  <chapter index="114" />
</tafsir>